<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/49563</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/49563">dodis.ch/49563</ref>
               <title type="main">Memo<note xml:id="e1624">Memo (copy, translated from French):
                        <idno>Swiss Federal Archives CH-BAR#E2010-01A#1996/396#843* (B.58.2)</idno>.
                     Transmitted to René Felber by Guy Ducrey, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15378"
                        >dodis.ch/P15378</ref>: <orig>Having heard yesterday evening that you will
                        hold a press conference concerning the latest developments in the GDR, I
                        have taken the liberty of transmitting you hereafter some information and
                        appreciations, which may be useful for you</orig>.</note> for the Swiss
                  Minister of Foreign Affairs, René Felber<note xml:id="e1630">René Felber (*1933),
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P24533">dodis.ch/P24533</ref>, Swiss Foreign
                     Minister 1.1.1988–31.1.1993.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">GDR: Press Conference</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Bern, 14 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>1. Question: Has the government foreseen the events?</p>
            <p>– The events have been accelerating in such a way that it has caught everybody
               unprepared. Chancellor Kohl<note xml:id="e1644">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> himself was surprised by the events in Berlin while
               he was on an official visit to Poland.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>2. Question: First impressions and analyses?</p>
            <p>– Berlin has given us impressive, moving images: the inhabitants of the GDR have
               demonstrated that the notion of liberty is such a fundamental value for humanity that
               it has withstood more than 40 years of implacable dictatorship (failure of “the new
               man”, designed by the theorists of Marxism-Leninism). And with regard to the human
               rights, it is this value of free movement of people that Switzerland has defended
               constantly, notably since the beginnings of the CSCE.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>3. Question: How do you judge the future?</p>
            <p>– There is still a long way to go, less spectacular maybe than these historic images
               from Berlin, and it will require perseverance:</p>
            <p>a) Advances on the political level: the East German people still await the revision
               of the first article in the constitution of the GDR, which assures a dominant role
               for the Communist Party (reconvening of the party congress in mid-December).</p>
            <p>b) A long way to go to achieve economic reforms as well.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>4. Question: Swiss assistance? (Our actions in favor of Hungary and Poland).</p>
            <p>– From now on, it is necessary to think about the GDR as well. Federal Germany will
               undoubtedly play a crucial role at this level. But let us not forget that the GDR is,
               economically speaking, in a considerably less difficult situation than Hungary and
               especially Poland. On the other hand, the GDR still has a long way to go to catch up
               with these two countries when it comes to democratic liberties.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>5. Question: The reunification?</p>
            <p>– It is not up to Switzerland to give its opinion on this matter. This is a question
               that affects both Germanies and which is, of course, of interest to both the US and
               the USSR. In this regard, one can only welcome the great reticence and the
               comprehension of all agents involved, both demonstrators as well as leaders.
               Chancellor Kohl recalled the embedding of the FRG in Western Europe and Mr
                  Genscher<note xml:id="e1678">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and
                  Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note> stressed that
               the FRG will respect all the agreements signed and commitments made.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>6. Question: GDR–EEC</p>
            <p>– A rapprochement is conceivable, but to speak of integration is surely premature.
               The economic systems are at the moment incompatible. Just look at the difficulties
               caused by the European Economic Area, and this is between countries that share the
               same market economy.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>7. Question: Yalta Order called into question? Switzerland’s security (abolition of
               the army)?</p>
            <p>– The calling into question of the Communist Party’s monopoly, the elimination of the
               dictatorships may – and we hope will – finally erase the ideological barriers. But
               the military borders, the military facilities are still there, right next to each
               other. What we are hoping is that the situation will, from now on, facilitate and
               accelerate the current negotiations concerning arms control (START, CFE). It is not
               the moment for Switzerland to put the cart before the horse by disarming
               unilaterally.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>8. Question: Bulgaria?</p>
            <p>– Zhivkov<note xml:id="e1702">Todor Hristov Zhivkov (1911–1998), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P15343">dodis.ch/P15343</ref>, Secretary General of
                  the Communist Party of Bulgaria 1954–1989.</note>, Secretary-General of the C<add
                  type="edition">[ommunist]</add> P<add type="edition">[arty]</add> of Bulgaria has
               left the scene after having been in power for 37 years. For the moment, it is only
               the replacement of the main agent; this may be preventive action, announcing upcoming
               reforms.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>9. Question: The Bush<note xml:id="e1718">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the
                  United States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>-Gorbachev<note xml:id="e1724">Mikhail
                  Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>,
                  General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991,
                  Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and
                  President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> Summit?</p>
            <p>– The two presidents will have to observe this development and what is already being
               called the end of the Yalta Order. Soviet propositions are possible in favor of
               military cutbacks.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
