<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/49561</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/49561">dodis.ch/49561</ref>
               <title type="main">Political report<note xml:id="e6924">Political report No. 16
                     (translated from German): <idno>Swiss Federal Archives CH-BAR#E2010-02A#
                        1996/400#16* (A.21.31)</idno>. Copies to be given to Klaus Jacobi, <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P19511">dodis.ch/P19511</ref>, Franz Blankart, <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P22246">dodis.ch/P22246</ref>, and Silvio Arioli,
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P24523">dodis.ch/P24523</ref>. Copies directly
                     to the Swiss Embassy in Bonn and the Swiss Consulate general in West Berlin;
                     also published in: <idno>Die DDR aus Sicht schweizerischer Diplomaten.
                        Politische Berichte aus Ost-Berlin 1982–1990, ed. by Bernd Haunfelder,
                        Münster 2017, doc. 93.</idno></note> of the Swiss Ambassador in East Berlin,
                  Franz Birrer<note xml:id="e6936">Franz Birrer (*1932), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P16179">dodis.ch/P16179</ref>, Swiss Ambassador in
                     East Berlin 1.10.1987–18.12.1990.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">Goodbye, GDR!</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>East Berlin, 2 October 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Today, the history of the GDR ends. The GDR will “join” the German Federal Republic
               and thus disappear from the political landscape.</p>
            <p>When I came to Berlin three years ago, nothing suggested that this “first workers and
               farmers’ nation on German soil” would perish so soon and so completely. Honecker<note
                  xml:id="e6952">Erich Honecker (1912–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46563"
                     >dodis.ch/P46563</ref>, General Secretary of the SED and chairman of the GDR
                  State Council 29.10.1976–18.10.1989.</note> had just returned from an official
               visit in Bonn. In the late 80s, he also visited nearly all other Western capitals and
               continuously welcomed guests of state from there. The citizens of the GDR suffered
               neither economic nor social hardship. Even the exceedingly critical FAZ noted, as
               late as June 1989, that measured by the economic malaise of its socialist sister
               countries, including the Soviet Union, the GDR was “an out-and-out economic plateau”.
               Its problem was not unemployment but rather labour shortage, due to which tens of
               thousands from socialist sister countries were used in the production process. And,
               nota bene, our exports to the GDR recorded annual rates of growth of roughly 40%.</p>
            <p>In terms of interior policy, the regime showed itself to be more <emph>relaxed</emph>
               than a new arrival from the West might have expected. GDR citizens you ran into in
               restaurants or elsewhere typically talked very openly and did not refrain from
               critical remarks about the country’s conditions. Churches had much more leeway than
               in other socialist countries (with the exception of Poland). A certain glasnost was
               notable especially in literature, in the theatre and revue, and in film; some films
               that had been banned twenty or more years ago – such as “The Russians Are Coming” by
                  Carow<note xml:id="e6960">Heiner Carow (1929–1997), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54831">dodis.ch/P54831</ref>, GDR film maker.</note>
               – could now be shown. Travel permits for the West soared in number and in 1988
               reached more than 3 million visits to the FRG, 1.3 million of these people below
               retirement age. Legal emigration to the FRG, too, reached annual numbers of about
               100,000 people by 1988/89. And so as to mention Switzerland here as well: the number
               of visa issued for travelling to our country increased by 20% annually (1988:
               11,900).</p>
            <p>Still, <emph>Stalinist</emph> structures and behaviours constituted the GDR’s basic
               pattern. The centrepiece of Stalinism was and would remain the primacy of the SED or
               rather of the party leadership, personified in the Secretary General<note
                  xml:id="e6968">Erich Honecker.</note> and individual members of the Politburo in
               charge of state security, economy, and mass media. The other parties, congregated
               into the National Front and brought into line, and the mass organisations chiefly
               served alibi purposes. The economy was based on the principle of central planning,
               despite the GDR leadership’s claim to have come up with something special when it
               came to cooperatives in agriculture, autonomous combines in the industry, and private
               enterprises in crafts and trades. The private enterprises, for instance, were very
               strongly restricted by a limitation to 10 employees and by business-hostile tax laws.
               There were many indicators that the economy was hardly growing any more but was at
               best stagnating. Under these conditions, environment protection fell by the wayside
               in a catastrophic manner.</p>
            <p>The SED communists had originally aspired to provide everyone with <emph>apartments,
                  food,</emph> and convenience goods, as well as public transport, in sufficient
               amounts and at low prices. They had largely succeeded, too, by means of a massive
               system of subsidies and by accelerating the industrial building of houses. But they
               proved unable and unwilling to adjust this policy to changing needs, and to remedy
               grave disadvantages. Freezing rents at the post-war level meant that not just the
               private building of flats, but also the maintenance of extant houses and flats was
               rendered impossible. The desolate state of many urban and village centres is a strong
               indication of this policy’s shortcomings.</p>
            <p>Likewise, Stalinist were the system of across-the-board informers used by the
               so-called <emph>“State Security”</emph> as well as the bullying and bringing in line
               of <emph>mass media.</emph> At best, a kind of glasnost existed in the specialised
               press and in Church print-media. Daily press, radio, and television, by contrast,
               remained under strict control. In November 1988, even the Soviet journal “Sputnik”
               was prohibited, as the SED regime disliked a number of contributions. All this
               appeared profusely absurd, given that the population could easily learn about
               domestic events and events abroad from West German radio and TV.</p>
            <p>However, one cannot evaluate the GDR solely with a view to the SED. From the very
               beginning, the <emph>Soviet Union</emph> played a decisive role here. In a manner of
               speaking, the GDR was an accidental product of WWII and the Cold War. When, in
               1948/49, the Western Bloc states undertook a currency reform in the three Western
               zones as well as in the Western sectors of Berlin, and founded the German Federal
               Republic, the Soviet Union, for its part, founded the GDR and for a long time kept it
               on a short leash. This was initially still the case under <emph>Gorbachev</emph><note
                  xml:id="e6977">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707"
                     >dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union
               15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>. When Honecker first met with the new Kremlin chief on 5
               Mai 1985, he had to sign a joint communiqué that made a direct connection between the
               Soviet Union’s military victory over the German Reich and the formation of the GDR,
               by declaring: “the first nation of workers and farmers on German soil has its roots
               in this great victory…”. It was (for the SED leadership) a most humiliating
               acknowledgement of the GDR’s heteronomy. Gorbachev also stuck to this position in his
               book “Perestroika”, published in autumn 1987. He dedicated an entire chapter to
               Germany, titled “Two German states”, and explained that what had here been
               historically formed would have to be entrusted to history. He wrote that there were
               now two German states with different social and political structures; Western
               declarations claiming that the German question remained open and that “German Unity”
               had to be restored he deemed anything but “realpolitik”. Gorbachev thus cannot be
               considered the father of the two German states’ unification. Rather, it was wrested
               from him. He was no longer able to resist it, as the Soviet Union had become too
               weak.</p>
            <p>For most GDR citizens, the “big brother”, the Soviet Union, was never an example,
               yardstick, or a reference point for action and aspiration. There never was a
               fraternisation. The <emph>Soviet troops</emph> in the GDR and the population were
               kept strictly separate. The troops, which exceeded 400,000 in number, remained an
               occupational force and at the same time a visible guarantor that the GDR remained
               closely integrated in the tight “socialist community”.</p>
            <p>The <emph>older generation</emph>s of GDR citizens by and by resigned to what seemed
               inevitable and tried to adapt. Occasionally, there was also pride in having achieved
               more than the Soviet Union economically. This was even expressed in remarks by the
               GDR leadership regarding Soviet efforts towards economic reform, by way of wishing
               Moscow the best of luck in this and intimating that the GDR had long ago carried out
               such reforms. This in turn startled <emph>the younger and increasingly more impatient
                  generation,</emph> who concluded from this that no further development was to be
               expected under the old SED leadership.</p>
            <p>This resulted in the great flight or emigration movement via West German diplomatic
               missions in East Berlin, Prague, and Warsaw, as well as via the Austrian-Hungarian
               border once it had been opened by the Hungarian government in September 1989.
                  <emph>The FRG’s migrant policy</emph> played a decisive role in this. Every
               migrant from the GDR has always been automatically recognised as a federal citizen.
               He not only enjoyed preferential treatment in the housing and job markets, but
               received, in addition to the “welcome money”, a number of different financial
               allowances or interest-free loans, and possibly qualified for unemployment benefits,
               sickness benefits, and a pension, just like someone who paid his dues in the FRG for
               all his life.</p>
            <p>It was most likely this mass movement that prompted Gorbachev to remark, in the
               course of the 40<hi>th</hi> anniversary celebrations in East Berlin, that he was in
               favour of further reforms in the GDR and that the Soviet troops would remain alert.
               Mass demonstrations under the slogans “We are the people” und “We are staying here”
               subsequently brought down the SED leadership in a matter of weeks.</p>
            <p>How the <emph>Berlin Wall</emph> and the inner German border came to be
                  <emph>opened</emph> on 9 November has today not yet been explained. The Stoph<note
                  xml:id="e6996">Willi Stoph (1914–1999), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15220"
                     >dodis.ch/P15220</ref>, Chairman of the GDR Council of Ministers
                  21.9.1964–3.10.1973 and 29.10.1976–13.11.1989.</note> government, which has
               already resigned, had put forward for discussion a draft of a liberal travel law,
               which was criticised, however, as being still too restrictive (particularly by
               lawyers, such as Gregor Gysi<note xml:id="e7002">Gregor Gysi(*1948), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54811">dodis.ch/P54811</ref>, GDR lawyer and Leader
                  of the PDS, 1989–1993.</note>); but instead of revising the draft, the government,
               without further ado, opened the floodgates. Whatever was behind that decision, the
               opening was the beginning of the end of the GDR.</p>
            <p>Since then, the development has accelerated several times over, where the
               acceleration was usually attributed to public pressure. What was decisive in this
               process, however, were more likely the actions of <emph>Federal Chancellor
                  Kohl</emph><emph><note xml:id="e7010">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the
                     FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>,</emph> who single-handedly defined the
               central milestones and, as his critics acidly put it, regarded German Unity as a
               private matter of his. Recall here Kohl’s</p>
            <p>– refusal to abolish <emph>migrants’</emph> privileges after the opening of the
               border (the official “emergency process of admittance” and the financial incentives
               were only abolished on 1 July);</p>
            <p>– <emph>reunification address</emph> of 28 November, with a 10-point programme that
               had not been coordinated with anyone else;</p>
            <p>– suggestion (against the advice of all experts and economic politicians) of a
                  <emph>monetary union,</emph> i.e. the introduction of the DM in the GDR with a
               “social cushioning” of the negative consequences to be expected (in the campaign for
               the GDR People’s Chamber election of 18 March, the Western CDU chiefly operated on
               the promise that GDR citizens would have the DM before the summer holidays; the
               “first free and secret elections in the GDR”, conducted from the FRG, are perhaps to
               be considered not so much as democratic but rather as <emph>DM-crati</emph>c);</p>
            <p>– demand to regard Article 23 of the Bonn Basic Law as the “royal road” to German
               Unity, i.e. <emph>“accession”</emph> of the GDR to the German Federal Republic, not
               unification or fusion of the two German states according to Article 146;</p>
            <p>– suggestion on the evening of 13 May, when CDU and CSU had suffered electoral
               defeats in in North Rhine-Westphalia, Lower Saxony, and Bavaria, to hold nationwide
               elections the same year (Kohl evidently intended to seize the moment and to get the
               elections over and done with before the full extent of the fallout of the monetary
               union would become seen and felt).</p>
            <p>Chancellor Kohl was thus not the promoter, but the actual engine of German Unity. He
               believed his suggestions won him the support of the GDR’s population, which primarily
               pursued the DM and Western prosperity. President von Weizsäcker<note xml:id="e7028"
                  >Richard von Weizsäcker (1920–2015), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P5944"
                     >dodis.ch/P5944</ref>, President of the FRG, 1.7.1984–30.6.1994.</note>, for
               example, pointed out that Germany’s two parts must not be allowed to rampantly grow
               together, but should grow together. Prime Minister de Maizière<note xml:id="e7034"
                  >Lothar de Maizière (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54809"
                     >dodis.ch/P54809</ref>, GDR Prime Minister 12.4–2.10.1990.</note>, too, spoke
               out this June in favour of reasonable timeframes and declared that the future course
               of Germany’s unification must not be defined by an express pace set by Bonn. Kohl,
               however, ignored these and similar objections, and categorically refused any dispute
               with the opposition. From a purely managerial point of view, one can certainly admire
               Kohl’s approach and his successes, although from a political point of view they
               appear quite problematic.</p>
            <p>Superficial observers have praised Kohl’s idea of a rapid <emph>monetary union</emph>
               as a stroke of genius and pointed out that the monetary reform of 1948 soon produced
               an unforeseen boom. They overlook, however, that a monetary union and a monetary
               reform have only little in common and took place or take place in completely
               different contexts. The chancellor’s personal appointee in charge of the monetary
               union termed the latter an “experiment unique in history”, namely, “a uno-actu
               transformation of a centralised economy, which previously was socialist for over 45
               years and before that national socialist for 12 years, into a market economy”.
               Specifically, this means:</p>
            <p>– central planning was abolished overnight, which created chaos particularly in the
               industrial sector and doomed many enterprises that under different circumstances
               could have been restored to profitability (this apparently caused West German and
               other investors to hold off until they could obtain the GDR enterprises at no
               charge);</p>
            <p>– prices were decontrolled at a single stroke (exceptions until the end of this year:
               rents, some public transport fees, and energy prices);</p>
            <p>– the inner German border wasn’t just opened, but abolished, thus exposing the GDR
               economy, via the FRG and the European Community, to the full force of international
               competition;</p>
            <p>– agricultural subsidies or rather the subsidies, which were extremely large in the
               GDR, reducing prices on local foodstuffs (1988: 31.9 billion M or DM) were cancelled
               overnight, as a result of which the agricultural sector experienced further, enormous
               hardship, i.e. in addition to losing the protection of the border;</p>
            <p>– by throwing central planning overboard, the public sector lost most of its major
               revenue sources, namely contributions by the economy; a fiscal system based on the
               FRG’s example is only now under construction, and since the monetary union has also
               transferred the financial and monetary sovereignty to Bonn, and the federal
               government is urging spending cuts, the public funds are lacking that just now would
               be so direly needed in housing and road construction, in restoring health care, in
               cultural work, etc. (this is exacerbated by the fact that the GDR’s 15 districts will
               be eliminated, but the five states replacing them will only gradually be built from
               14 October onwards).</p>
            <p>The former GDR’s economy is thus running the risk of losing both the domestic market
               as well as that of the Eastern European countries, which until now has been very
               important for it (70% of the foreign trade volume). There can be little doubt that
               its current chances of success in Western markets are very small. In other words, the
               territories of the former GDR are facing the loss of production and of creation of
               value.</p>
            <p>Whereas the treaty creating an economic, monetary, and social union had been drafted
               and dictated exclusively in Bonn – its signing by the then GDR minister of finance
               seemed to outside observers like the signing of a capitulation – in the second
               contract, also called the <emph>Unification Treaty,</emph> the GDR was apparently
               able to preserve and defend certain specific interests of the five new federal
               states. This is true, for instance, of property issues (the land reform predating the
               founding of the GDR is not reversed), of interim rulings on abortion, etc., as well
               as of <emph>economic development.</emph> Based on Article 28, much as the former
               border territory was, the entire GDR territory has now become a development zone of
               the joint task “improvement of regional economic structures”. It thus becomes a
               recipient of many investment subsidies and low-interest loans. This can be seen as a
               kind of Marshall Plan for the former GDR.</p>
            <p>Yet on reading Article 7 of the treaty more closely, one gains a different
               impression. It basically provides for the FRG financial constitution to be extended
               to the acceded states. The extant states, however, have strictly <emph>refused</emph>
               to include the new states in the <emph>equalization payments</emph><emph> between
                  states</emph> and in the even distribution of states’ shares in <emph>value added
                  tax</emph>. They will not enter negotiations on equalization payments before 1994,
               and the GDR states’ share in value added tax is for now set at only 55% of the other
               states’ average share per capita. As a result, the “German Unity” fund, originally
               intended for the promotion of investment, now serves to close the new federal states’
               fiscal holes and is indirectly co-financed by the latter. The Hanover-based
               constitutionalist Schneider<note xml:id="e7058">Hans-Peter Schneider (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54833">dodis.ch/P54833</ref>, FRG constitutional
                  lawyer.</note> comments: “The GDR states will remain bound in the unity fund for
               years, depending on and patronised by the federation not only financially, but also
               politically”.</p>
            <p>From a general and European point of view, <emph>German Unity</emph> is doubtlessly
               to be welcomed.</p>
            <p>The division of Europe, Germany, and Berlin has always been an artificial, even
               absurd division and a germ of present and future conflicts.</p>
            <p>We now have on our border a country that will shortly rise to the status of a major
               power, perhaps even a superpower. Unlike in the past, however, this country has a
               federal structure, is firmly democratic, inimical to militaristic matters and
               moreover integrated into the European Community and NATO.</p>
            <p>Yet the rushed nature of German Unity must give us pause. It is not a unification,
               but an appropriation of the GDR by the FRG, which can for instance be seen in the
               fact that, starting tomorrow, West German officials, judges, economic leaders, etc.
               will “invade” this country and replace GDR people. “The Price of Unity is a New
               Foreign Rule”, as historian Jörg Fisch<note xml:id="e7072">Jörg Fisch (*1947), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P22386">dodis.ch/P22386</ref>, Swiss historian.</note>
               appropriately titled his article, which is well worth reading, in the Weltwoche of 20
               September 1990.</p>
            <p>Will the new state be able to become a native country, even a home, to all Germans?
               Will the East Germans be able to identify with it, or will they once again merely
               come to terms with it, as many of them did for so long with the “socialist home
               country GDR”? Can a mezzogiornalisation of East Germany, and a radicalisation that
               would almost necessarily follow from it, be avoided? All of these are questions that
               can only be answered in the years to come.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
