<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52282</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52282">dodis.ch/52282</ref>
               <title type="main">Political report<note xml:id="e5012">Political report No. 24 and
                     Telegram No. 97 (incoming, translated from German): <idno>Swiss Federal
                        Archives CH-BAR#E2010-02A#1996/400#19* (A.21.31)</idno>.</note> of the Swiss
                  Ambassador in Bonn, Alfred Hohl<note xml:id="e5015">Alfred Hohl (1930–2004), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P16080">dodis.ch/P16080</ref>, Swiss Ambassador in
                     Bonn 1.9.1987–16.11.1991.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">Too Early?</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 10 April 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>A state secretary of the Federal Foreign Office excitedly remarked to the signatory
               that Bonn had been confronted with the task of reunification 20 years too early, pure
               and simple. “We are not yet integrated into Europe fully enough and the chances of
               German-national upsurges remain much too real.”</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, in Europe, the perpetuum mobile of 19<hi>th</hi> / 20<hi>th</hi> century
               national problems, connected to the dissolution of empires, amongst other things, is
               keeping busy the Balkan states most of all, whose borders were arbitrarily drawn,
               back in the day, right through ethnic territories and thus from the start ensured
               considerable controversy. The same goes for the dissolution of the Soviet empire
               built by the Czars and their epigones that intended, for instance, to bring together
               Europe and Asia, Christianity and Islam in the grip of its party-bureaucratic manner
               of rule. Is Europe now about to face a general rise of those who came up short e.g.
               in Versailles, Potsdam, and Yalta?</p>
            <p>In Hessen, nationally inspired unknowns are thought to have recently painted the
               slogan “Ami go home” on a wall, and the press there discussed governor
                  Wallmann’s<note xml:id="e5039">Walter Wallmann (1932–2013), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P56923">dodis.ch/P56923</ref>, Minister President of
                  Hesse 1987–1991.</note> alleged plans to house one’s own lodgers and migrants in
               living quarters becoming vacant with the Americans’ withdrawal. In my opinion,
               however, this is for now only rumour-mongering by the media that is not to be taken
               seriously.</p>
            <p>We have already reported elsewhere, however, that the Germans’ basic mentality, a
               kind of penitent’s attitude combined with the readiness to help the weak and
               disenfranchised, has at least partially changed. The thinking here is once again
               German first, although most of my interlocutors attest to the chancellor’s<note
                  xml:id="e5047">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852"
                     >dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>
               reliability in term of European politics. Kohl possibly means to ultimately become
               not only the chancellor of reunification but also Europe’s deus ex machina. As the
               French have so far reserved this role for themselves, things will get interesting.
                  Delors<note xml:id="e5053">Jacques Delors (*1925), French politician, <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P47396">dodis.ch/P47396</ref>, President of the
                  European Commission 7.1.1985–24.1.1995.</note> surely has as little interest as
                  Mitterand<note xml:id="e5059">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> in letting Kohl pave the way for European success. But
               the chancellor’s ambitions are apparently growing increasingly more global: a
               German-German monetary union, reunification, united Germany participating in Europe,
               a European monetary union, the relinquishing of national prerogatives of political
               sovereignty to a European executive and its parliamentary substructure.</p>
            <p>A daring transformation from the German “Michel” to Euro-citizen. At times, it almost
               seems this way.</p>
            <p>One may thus honestly wonder why the above-cited state secretary of the Federal
               Foreign Affairs Office thinks that the reunification barged in 20 years too early.
               Are there really still national territorial ambitions here as in the times of the
               Prussian kings, of Bismarck<note xml:id="e5069">Otto von Bismarck (1815–1898), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P3822">dodis.ch/P3822</ref>, Chancellor of the German
                  Empire 1871–1890.</note>, or of Hitler<note xml:id="e5075">Adolf Hitler
                  (1889–1945), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P535">dodis.ch/P535</ref>, Führer of
                  the German Third Reich 1933–1945.</note>? As far as Kohl is concerned: no. With
               him, one rather feels a true willingness to let Germany come to bloom as a part of
               Europe. This is genuine and reminiscent of Walter Hallstein<note xml:id="e5081"
                  >Walter Hallstein (1901–1982), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P2869"
                     >dodis.ch/P2869</ref>, Civil servant in the FRG Foreign Office who had the
                  “Hallstein Doctrine” that meant that the FRG would regard it as an unfriendly act
                  if third countries were to recognize the FRG, named after him and President of the
                  Commission of the European Economic Community 1958–1967.</note> – with the one
               nuance that the chancellor reasons more sentimentally. When he speaks of the
               German-French handshake over the graves of Verdun, he does so with a tearful voice.
               Compared to this attitude, the advocates of federations of Expellees, including
                  Schönhuber’s<note xml:id="e5087">Franz Schönhuber (1923–2005), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54840">dodis.ch/P54840</ref>, journalist and
                  politician of the FRG, founder and later chairman of The Republicans.</note>
               camarilla, remain a rather ephemeral Don Quixotism.</p>
            <p>Generally speaking, nationalism these days appears to have become the religion of the
               poor. It rages in Kosovo, Romania, or Bulgaria – soon perhaps also in Albania. Here,
               German saturation in the context of the materialism fuelled by Erhard’s<note
                  xml:id="e5095">Ludwig Erhard (1897–1977), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P2893"
                     >dodis.ch/P2893</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1963–1966.</note>
               “Wirtschaftswunder” seems to have mostly eradicated the infamous appetite for
               “Lebensraum”. One rather pursues ideas of qualitative growth.</p>
            <p>Kohl may ultimately disappoint many ambitions and hopes: for instance, the still
               existing feelings of entitlement regarding lost territories in the East, or GDR hopes
               for prosperity through an automatic bonanza, French aspirations to push for European
               integration according to concepts created in Paris, etc.</p>
            <p>Whether reunification, then, is coming around 20 years too early is hard to tell.
               Such fears are based on the assumption that, preferably, the FRG would have been
               irrevocably and strongly rooted in Europa for now. But revolutions elude all timing.
               And no one can say whether a process of Europeanization controlled by French
               computers and coupled with a postponed reunification would have produced more
               suitable results.</p>
            <p>In fact, why does no one make use of Kohl’s almost clumsily lovable openness to
               Europe? Why does everyone suspect the ponderous giant from the Palatinate of deviant
               Germanic Machiavellianism? Why, by contrast, the premium for Oskar<note
                  xml:id="e5107">Oskar Lafontaine (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54839"
                     >dodis.ch/P54839</ref>, Minister President of Saarland 1985–1998 and SPD
                  candidate for Chancellor in the German federal elections of 1990.</note> the tin
               drummer from the Saarland?</p>
            <p/>
            <p>Europe has often seen dishonest politics. But in my opinion, Bonn is not currently a
               target of legitimate suspicions in this regard. Perhaps the reunification came too
               early for the keepers of the grail of European distrust, but so far, the chancellor
               seems to be coping just fine with the enormous problems he is facing.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
