<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53169</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52918">dodis.ch/52918</ref>
               <title type="main">Minutes<note xml:id="e1955">Minutes: <idno>UK National Archives
                        CAB 128/94</idno>. Present at this meeting were: Margaret Thatcher (Prime
                     Minister), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>,Geoffrey
                     Howe (Lord President of the Council), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54804"
                        >dodis.ch/P54804</ref>, James Mackay (Lord Chancellor), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57494">dodis.ch/P57494</ref>, Douglas Hurd
                     (Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57401">dodis.ch/P57401</ref>, John Major
                     (Chancellor of the Exchequer), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57495"
                        >dodis.ch/P57495</ref>, David Waddington (Secretary of State for the Home
                     Department), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57484">dodis.ch/P57484</ref>, Peter
                     Walker (Secretary of State for Wales), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P50851"
                        >dodis.ch/P50851</ref>, Norman Fowler (Secretary of State for Employment),
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57485">dodis.ch/P57485</ref>, Tom King
                     (Secretary of State for Defence), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57496"
                        >dodis.ch/P57496</ref>, Nicholas Ridley (Secretary of State for Trade and
                     Industry), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P48293">dodis.ch/P48293</ref>, Kenneth
                     Baker (Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57498">dodis.ch/P57498</ref>, Kenneth Clarke
                     (Secretary of State for Health), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57486"
                        >dodis.ch/P57486</ref>, John MacGregor (Secretary of State for Education and
                     Science), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57500">dodis.ch/P57500</ref>, Malcom
                     Rifkind (Secretary of State for Scotland), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57487">dodis.ch/P57487</ref>, Cecil Parkinson
                     (Secretary of State for Transport), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P55897"
                        >dodis.ch/P55897</ref>, John Wakeham (Secretary of State for Energy), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57488">dodis.ch/P57488</ref>, John Ganzoni (Lord
                     Privy Seal), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P55622">dodis.ch/P55622</ref>,
                     Antony Newton (Secretary of State for Social Security), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57490">dodis.ch/P57490</ref>, Christopher Patten
                     (Secretary of State for the Environment), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57499"
                        >dodis.ch/P57499</ref>, Peter Brooke (Secretary of State for Northern
                     Ireland), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57491">dodis.ch/P57491</ref>, John
                     Gummer (Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57501">dodis.ch/P57501</ref> and Norman Lamont
                     (Chief Secretary, Treasury), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57502"
                        >dodis.ch/P57502</ref>.</note> of the 34<hi>th</hi> Meeting of the Cabinet
                  held at 10 Downing Street on 15 November 1989 at 9.30 a.m.</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add><add type="edition"><emph>Extract</emph></add>Secret</add>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add type="edition">[…]</add>
               <note xml:id="e2035">For the complete version of the document cf. <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/52918">dodis.ch/52918</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>Foreign Affairs: German Democratic Republic</emph>
            </p>
            <p>3. <emph>The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary</emph><note xml:id="e2046">Douglas
                  Hurd (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57401">dodis.ch/P57401</ref>, British
                  Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs,
                  26.10.1989–5.7.1995.</note> said that events in East Germany had moved very
               rapidly, particularly following the measures taken to introduce freer travel between
               East and West Berlin. The key question now was whether the East German government
               would agree to hold free elections. Their intentions were still obscure. The new
               Prime Minister, Herr Hans Modrow<note xml:id="e2052">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                  Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note>, the former Party Secretary in
               Dresden, had been elected on 13 November. He had the reputation of a reformer. The
               Party Congress had been brought forward to 15/17 December. This was bound to be a
               crucially important occasion. The opposition groups were pressing for free elections,
               but did not want these to take place immediately since they were not yet ready. There
               had been intensive diplomatic activity as events in East Germany unfolded. The Prime
                  Minister<note xml:id="e2058">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of the
                  United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note> had been in close touch with other
               allied leaders. Despite excessive press speculation, allied governments had reacted
               steadily and with caution. This had emerged clearly at the Western European Union
               Ministerial meeting on 13/14 November. The French President, M. Francois
                  Mitterrand<note xml:id="e2064">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note>, had organised a meeting of European Community (EC)
               leaders on 18 November. It was to be hoped that EC leaders would express their
               support and welcome for the changes taking place in Eastern Europe while agreeing on
               the need for a careful and steadfast approach, based on existing well-tried
               institutions. Account had to be taken of the position of the Soviet President, Mr
               Mikhail Gorbachev.<note xml:id="e2070">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the
                  Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet
                  Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> He faced a difficult situation but it was very
               much in the interests of Western governments that he should remain in power. The
               question of German reunification was extremely sensitive. Given the German
               Constitution and political life in West Germany, it was inevitable that there should
               be some discussion of reunification. All the allied governments had been committed to
               this general principle for many years. At the same time no-one in a position of
               influence in the West or East believed that reunification was likely to happen
               rapidly, or that this would be desirable in the near future. This view was also
               shared by reformers inside East Germany. President Mitterrand’s purpose in organising
               the meeting on 18 November was probably to try to dispose of developments in Eastern
               Europe before the European Council meeting in Strasbourg on 8/9 November. This was
               unrealistic. Much was likely to happen in the intervening period before the European
               Council. Moreover, these issues were so important for the future of the EC that they
               would need to be discussed again in depth at the European Council. Nevertheless, on
               the whole the allied response in Eastern Europe had been sensible and prudent.</p>
            <p>In discussion, the following points were made:</p>
            <p>a) A clear framework for dealing with the changes in Eastern Europe had been laid
               down, most recently in the Prime Minister’s speech at the Lord Mayor’s Banquet on 13
               November. It was essential to maintain existing institutions, especially the North
               Atlantic Treaty Organisation. Ministers should not raise the issue of German
               reunification, which was not an immediate issue. Progress had already been achieved
               on strengthening the EC’s economic relations with East European countries. The EC had
               signed trade agreements with Poland and Hungary, and an association agreement with
               Yugoslavia. In due course Poland and Hungary might want to negotiate association
               agreements. Such a development was unlikely to cause major problems for the Soviet
               leadership. If events moved too quickly or Western governments did not continue to
               take a measured and prudent attitude, there was a risk that President Gorbachev might
               be swept away. This would cause grave damage to the broader Western objective of
               promoting democracy throughout both parts of Europe, and ultimately from the Atlantic
               through the Soviet Union to the borders of China. The EC could not ignore these
               crucially important processes of historic change which would have a profound effect
               on developments within the Community.</p>
            <p>b) The West German Finance Minister, Herr Waigel<note xml:id="e2082">Theo Waigel
                  (*1939), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54838">dodis.ch/P54838</ref>, Finance
                  Minister of the FRG 21.4.1989–27.10.1998.</note>, had made clear both in the
               formal and informal meetings of the Economic and Finance Council on 13 November that
               West Germany saw its future as remaining an integral member of the EC and Western
               Europe. Herr Waigel had emphasised that West Germany was not seeking reunification at
               the present time. The same line had been taken by the West German Foreign Minister,
               Herr Genscher<note xml:id="e2088">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and
                  Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>, and the
               Defence Minister, Herr Stoltenberg<note xml:id="e2094">Gerhard Stoltenberg
                  (1928–2001), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46108">dodis.ch/P46108</ref>, Defence
                  Minister of the FRG 21.4.1989–1.4.1992.</note>, at the Western European Union
               Ministerial meeting. Nevertheless, these statements contrasted with the greater
               attention paid to the theme of reunification by Chancellor Kohl<note xml:id="e2100"
                  >Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852"
                     >dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> in
               recent speeches, though it should be remembered that he had always been one of the
               foremost advocates of reunification among German political leaders.</p>
            <p>c) Against this background, the West German government was likely to show an
               increasing tendency to examine new proposals for greater integration within the EC in
               the light of the implications for closer relations between East and West Germany and
               eventual reunification. In certain cases this tendency might be helpful to Britain’s
               own interests.</p>
            <p>d) In reality there were already close links between East and West Germany. West
               German companies were able to take advantage of cheap labour in East Germany in their
               manufacturing processes. Goods from East Germany were admitted to West Germany, and
               hence into the EC, without tariffs or quotas. Hitherto West German companies had been
               deterred from major investment in East Germany because of the political situation
               there. The recent changes were likely to stimulate a significant flow of new West
               German investment in East Germany. The Polish and Hungarian governments had stressed
               recently that they attached importance to securing increased investment from Britain
               and other EC countries to maintain the preponderant weight of West German trade and
               investment flows. On the other hand, East Germany and the other reforming East
               European countries would have great difficulty in practice in implementing the
               structural changes necessary to create genuine market economies based on private
               enterprise. This was likely to be a long process.</p>
            <p>e) West Germany had a trade surplus of £35 billion with the rest of the EC in 1988.
               Closer economic links between East and West Germany would present a formidable
               challenge to the other members of the EC. With a combined population of nearly 80
               million people this economic entity would have a major distorting effect on EC
               projects for closer economic and financial unity and the concept of a Single Market.
               The EC could not afford to ignore the EC’s relations with the European Free Trade
               Area (EFTA). The EC’s import standards would need to be maintained both in relation
               to East Germany and EFTA.</p>
            <p/>
            <p><emph>The Prime Minister</emph> summing up the discussion, said that it was of
               cardinal importance for Western governments that all these complex questions should
               be handled carefully and prudently. Allied governments should remain in close touch,
               especially Britain, France and the United States who had Four Power rights and
               obligations. Although Western governments had taken a formal position since 1955 in
               favour of East German self-determination, German reunification should not be treated
               as an immediate issue. Governments should take due account of the implications of the
               present turn of events for President Gorbachev’s position. A change in the Soviet
               leadership would inflict major damage on the prospects for the further spread of
               democracy in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. The EC would need to discuss these
               issues in depth both at President Mitterrand’s dinner and at the European Council in
               Strasbourg. EC member states could not simply concentrate on internal developments
               within the Community without taking account of trends in Europe as a whole. A single
               European currency was no answer to these wider changes. Although events were moving
               in a favourable direction, Europe faced a difficult decade ahead.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
