<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52915</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52915">dodis.ch/52915</ref>
               <title type="main">Information Memorandum<note xml:id="e646">Memorandum (copy):
                        <idno>Bush Presidential Library CF01414-008</idno>. Written by James F.
                     Dobbins, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57393">dodis.ch/P57393</ref>, and
                     transmitted through Robert M. Kimmitt, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57396"
                        >dodis.ch/P57396</ref>.</note> for the United States Secretary of State,
                  James A. Baker<note xml:id="e655">James A. Baker (*1930), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P56605">dodis.ch/P56605</ref>, United States
                     Secretary of State 25.1.1989–23.8.1992.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">The Wall Breached: Implications for Malta, Your Trip to Europe,
                  Relations with the GDR, and the Reunification Debate</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Washington, D.C., 10 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>The East German decision to lift travel restrictions has created a new situation in
               Europe. This memo is a first attempt to address the implications for the Malta
               meeting and your December trip, for relations with the GDR, and for our handling of
               the debate on reunification.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>The Malta Meeting</emph>
            </p>
            <p>Events in Germany further demonstrate the wisdom of the President’s<note
                  xml:id="e675">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> decision to hold an early, informal exchange
               with Gorbachev<note xml:id="e681">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the
                  Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet
                  Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>. Attention will very much be on Europe and
               German events. At the same time, it is all the more important to avoid creating the
               impression that these issues will dominate the Malta discussion. We need to avoid
               both any suggestion of superpower condominium (the “Malta rhymes with Yalta” concern)
               and also recognize that the results of a Bush-Gorbachev discussion on Germany and
               Eastern Europe are liable to be meager and thus for the public disappointing.
               Consequently, we should begin to emphasize that the Malta discussions are designed to
               move the US-Soviet dialogue forward across the board, and that we are looking for
               substantial exchanges on arms control, regional and transnational issues as well as
               on the situation in Europe. We should also consider how events in the GDR might
               affect our approach to the economic issues. Gorbachev’s support for open borders in
               Germany, combined with Soviet passage of their own immigration legislation, could
               provide a basis for early forward movement on Jackson-Vanik, MFN and perhaps even
               Ex-Im Bank lending restrictions.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>Pre- and Post-Malta Consultations and Your Trip to Europe</emph>
            </p>
            <p>The NSC<note xml:id="e693">National Security Council.</note> has said the President
               wants to enhance pre-Malta consultations, and asked our advice. We recommend an early
               Presidential message to the NATO colleagues, followed by a pre-Malta briefing here of
               Allied Ambassadors. We anticipate high interest among your Foreign Minister
               colleagues in an early post-Malta readout. If you agree, we should contact
                  Genscher<note xml:id="e696">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and
                  Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>, Dumas<note
                  xml:id="e702">Roland Dumas (*1922), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15651"
                     >dodis.ch/P15651</ref>, Foreign Minister of France 10.5.1988–28.3.1993.</note>,
               and Hurd<note xml:id="e708">Douglas Hurd (*1930), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57401">dodis.ch/P57401</ref>, British Secretary of
                  State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs 26.10.1989–5.7.1995.</note> to see
               whether they would be ready to travel to Brussels for an immediate post-Malta
               debrief. If at least two out of these three are prepared to participate, we recommend
               you schedule such a session. The quickened pace of events in Europe also makes the
               full range of consultations under consideration for the following week (the EC, a
               G-24, and NATO Ministerials) all the more important. Finally, we continue to
               recommend a visit to Bonn and West Berlin to accentuate our solidarity with the FRG
               and the central role of the United States in promoting a peaceful change in Europe.
               If you concur, we could begin arranging for such visits, but hold up on announcement
               till somewhat closer to the event.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>Relations with the GDR</emph>
            </p>
            <p>Assuming they do not back-pedal from the steps already announced, we should move to
               expand our relations with the GDR. An early Presidential message to Krenz<note
                  xml:id="e720">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54794"
                     >dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and
                  Chairman of the GDR State Council 18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note> expressing approval
               for the travel liberalization and support for further reforms should be considered.
               If the new permanent GDR travel regime, reportedly to be promulgated in a few weeks
               leaves the borders open, we should consider a Jackson-Vanik waiver for the GDR.</p>
            <p>An early senior level visit to East Berlin (e.g., by Eagleburger<note xml:id="e728"
                  >Lawrence S. Eagleburger (1930–2011), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57397"
                     >dodis.ch/P57397</ref>, United States Deputy Secretary of State
                  20.3.1989–8.12.1992.</note>, Kimmitt<note xml:id="e734">Robert M. Kimmitt (*1947),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57396">dodis.ch/P57396</ref>, United States
                  Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs 2.3.1989–23.8.1991.</note> or
                  Seitz<note xml:id="e740">Raymond G. H. Seitz (*1940), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57399">dodis.ch/P57399</ref>, United States Assistant
                  Secretary of State for European and Canadian Affairs 8.8.1989–30.4.1991.</note>)
               would demonstrate our interest in an improved relationship, launch serious talks to
               remove some old bilateral obstacles (i.e., unresolved claims issues), and open the
               way for yet higher level contacts next year (e.g., a visit by yourself). Any actual
               U.S. economic assistance to the GDR, of the sort we are providing Hungary and Poland,
               should be tied to the holding of genuinely free elections, as Kohl has recently done.
               Given the FRG stake, the amount of US assistance would in any case be minimal, but
               even a symbolic US participation might be useful in the context of a truly reformed
               GDR.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>Discussing German Reunification</emph>
            </p>
            <p>The reunification debate will become all the more immediate, concrete, and delicate.
               There will be pressures both domestic and from Allies for the United States to take
               the lead in sketching out a blueprint and timetable for the new European order. With
               the Germans increasingly seizing control of their own destiny, there will be those
               who will urge us to reassert more forcefully our own rights and responsibilities for
               Germany, growing out of the war and the four power Yalta and Potsdam agreements. The
               problems with such an approach are that it puts the onus on us to come forward with
               plans for a new European architecture, that it legitimizes the Soviet veto, and that
               it makes us appear a possible obstacle to German aspirations. We should, therefore,
               keep the emphasis where we have put it, upon the principle of self-determination.</p>
            <p>The time has come, however, to begin to address more concretely with the FRG, the
               British and the French the issues which the prospect of reunification in some form
               pose. We should seek agreement among these Allies, and then among NATO more
               generally, not on a blueprint, let alone a timetable for reunification, but on a set
               of guidelines for channeling any developments in this direction. The key guideline is
               that the process of West European integration, and of transatlantic cooperation
               should continue to be intensified, and that any new relationship between the two
               German states must not weaken Germany’s Western ties. Kohl<note xml:id="e754">Helmut
                  Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>,
                  Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>, of course, has stressed this
               very theme repeatedly. We now need to begin considering how Germany’s Western ties
               can in practice be assured in a transformed European context. The British and French
               will welcome such a discussion, while the Germans will hold back. But we need to make
               an effort. The next Quad meeting, which Dumas, Genscher and Hurd are proposing be
               held over dinner December 13, provides an occasion to launch this exchange.</p>
            <p>I have reviewed these recommendations with Ray Seitz, who concurs.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
