<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52929</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52929">dodis.ch/52929</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum of conversation<note xml:id="e2408">Memorandum of
                     conversation (translated from German): <idno>Austrian State Archive ÖStA, AdR,
                        BMAA, II-Pol 1989, GZ. 518.01.12/89</idno>. Written by Eva Nowotny, <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57522">dodis.ch/P57522</ref>; also published in
                     Wilson Center, doc. 165715. Forwarded to the Cabinet of the Foreign Minister on
                     4 December 1989. The Head of the Cabinet Emil Staffelmayr took notice and
                     forwarded the memorandum to the Political Section. No further circulation was
                     initiated.</note> by the Austrian Federal Chancellery</title>
               <title type="sub">Conversation of the Chancellor<note xml:id="e2416">Franz Vranitzky
                     (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57523">dodis.ch/P57523</ref>,
                     Chancellor of Austria 16.6.1986–28.1.1997.</note> with Prime Minister
                     Modrow<note xml:id="e2422">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                     Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note>, 24.11.1989</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Vienna, 2 Dezember 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Prime Minister Modrow thanks at the outset for this visit, which is particularly
               important given the current situation in the GDR and is thus highly appreciated.</p>
            <p>First, the following has to be said concerning the GDR’s internal situation:</p>
            <p>The resignation of the old government and the initiation of reform measures were
               delayed beyond any comprehensible extent. This caused the population, especially the
               “youth fraction”, to become active, and the resignation of the old and the formation
               of the new government have taken place against a backdrop of massive demonstrations
               and rallies. There has been little time for him to form a government and create a
               program of action.</p>
            <p>As a first step, he decided to reduce the government (coalition distribution 28:11).
               This was a good decision, which also found public approval. The debate on the
               election of the new executive committee and the questioning of the old government in
               the People’s Chamber were also good because a lot of steam was discharged this way.
               He is aware that he was being given great trust, which could be taken away at any
               time. Now it is necessary to turn this leap of faith into real trust.</p>
            <p>The political situation in the country is very complicated. The established sources
               of political influence are no longer significant. In rallies and demonstrations, new
               political movements and forces that must now be included have articulated. He had
               made the offer of a round table, which was more or less accepted. He considers this
               an important part of his political work. On the one hand, you must respond to the
               mood of the country, on the other hand you need all political forces to be involved
               in a role of responsibility. It is not acceptable that a large group should be
               content with only questioning those responsible.</p>
            <p>For all reform measures, economic stability is the prerequisite and given the
               economic situation of the GDR, foreign economic relations are especially meaningful.
               Austria has always been an important partner for the GDR. Relations have been
               sustained with continuity and trust and must further develop on this basis.</p>
            <p>Among the socialist countries, the overall economic development of the GDR offers the
               most favorable conditions for a process of renewal, but with regard to contents a new
               mobilization must take place. Some instruments of the modern economy that had been
               rejected by the former government now have to be implemented – especially terms such
               as joint ventures, transfer of capital, etc.</p>
            <p>It is of utmost importance to gradually change the bureaucratically encrusted
               centralized management of the economy, however, in a step-by-step process to avoid
               instability.</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is necessary to renew the societal system as a socialist one, therefore
               a program of legal decisions and a list of legislation to be enacted were created.
               The parliament will have a lot of work to do in the next few weeks. The People’s
               Chamber has already appointed two commissions, one that has been assigned to deal
               with the amendments to the constitution (for example, rephrasing the leadership role
               of the working class, creation of a constitutional court), and the other to draw up a
               new electoral law.</p>
            <p>In foreign policy, he attaches great importance to European policy. This particular
               priority for European initiatives is new in the overall design of foreign policy.
               Also in this sense, the visit of the Chancellor is especially important. Of course,
               all alliance relations will be maintained, and relations with the USSR will remain
               especially important because of the mutual economic interdependence.</p>
            <p>Regarding relations with the FRG, it was felt in the exploratory talks with
                  Seiters<note xml:id="e2453">Rudolf Seiters (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57431">dodis.ch/P57431</ref>, Head of the Office of
                  the Chancellery and Minister for Special Affairs of the FRG 1989–1991.</note> that
               an important stage of work is still necessary. The constant meddling by the FRG
               showed that there was little trust in and respect for the sovereignty of the GDR.</p>
            <p>Of course, the decision in favour of an open border has qualitatively changed the
               situation. The offer of the GDR has been put forward, and it has coined the term
               “treaty community” – how broad and how versatile this treaty community might be
               remains to be explored.</p>
            <p>Trade and economic relations with Austria have developed well, and we are very
               interested in its continuation. This is underscored by Austria’s high level of
               participation at the Autumn Fair and the interest of Austrian entrepreneurs. We
               expect to go on working with continuity and stability. Given the annual framing
               contract, we have gone the farthest with Austria in the development of economic
               relations.</p>
            <p>The Chancellor expressed his thanks for the comprehensive and frank presentation.
               Relations between Austria and the GDR are excellent in all areas, including culture
               and tourism, and the framework agreement is a good signal that this should continue
               in the future. In the economic sphere, Austria attaches great importance to
               cooperation in environmental technology, and it would like to develop some such
               initiatives. The Chancellor then gave a short overview of the outstanding Austrian
               economic development, as well as Austrian integration policy, and referred in this
               context to Austria’s adherence to neutrality and its neutrality policy, which is very
               important at present given the transformation in the Eastern European neighboring
               countries.</p>
            <p>The Chancellor mentioned that he had heard an ORF<note xml:id="e2467"
                  >Österreichischer Rundfunk (Austrian Broadcasting Corporation).</note> interview
               with Mr. Krenz<note xml:id="e2470">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54794">dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and Chairman of the GDR State Council
                  18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note> upon his departure, where he was confronted with the
               question of German reunification. Krenz expressed his opinion that it was not an
               urgent interest for the people of the GDR. Austria sees this primarily as a decision
               that has to be made by the German states and would also respect this decision. On the
               other hand, one needs to take the pan-European context into consideration, and in
               this sense, the decisions made by the CSCE on the stability of Europe.</p>
            <p>The transition to a plurality of the political spectrum and its constitutional
               anchoring has triggered much active interest and sympathy in Austria, which would
               also have an impact on cooperation and support. With the “East-West Fund”, a new
               structure for financial cooperation has been found that offers a sound basis for
               joint investment projects and joint ventures, etc. Austria would also actively engage
               in international forums in favor of Eastern European countries. Unfortunately,
               Austria recently lost some economic projects in the GDR (for example, Buna<note
                  xml:id="e2478">The <orig>Beuna Werke</orig> were a chemical company specializing
                  in the production of polymer materials.</note>, Leuna<note xml:id="e2481">The
                     <orig>Leuna Werke</orig> were the largest chemical procution site in the
                  GDR.</note>), and especially in the light of this he would like to emphasize
               Austria’s interest in strengthening economic cooperation.</p>
            <p>Prime Minister Modrow then briefly explained his position on the issue of
               reunification. This has various aspects: on the one hand, it corresponds with a
               natural human need, but on the other hand has some chauvinistic aspects (restoration
               of Germany’s 1937 borders). The situation in today’s Europe is bound to the existence
               of two German states, and that must be the understanding from which one starts. Of
               course, one must look at history as a process that does not stand still, but every
               change in this regard will take a long time and involve international thinking over
               long periods. He could imagine a solution to this problem only within the “federal
               structures of a wider Europe”. For him, it is particularly important in this context
               to connect the process of inner renewal with everything that shows European
               responsibility.</p>
            <p>In the afternoon of 24.11, the Chancellor held meetings with Mr. de Maizière<note
                  xml:id="e2488">Lothar de Maizière (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54809"
                     >dodis.ch/P54809</ref>, GDR Prime Minister 12.4–2.10.1990.</note> (CDU), Mr.
               Steffen Reiche (SPD)<note xml:id="e2494">Steffen Reiche (*1960), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57524">dodis.ch/P57524</ref>, co-founder of the
                  Social Democratic Party in the GDR.</note>, and Professor Jens Reich (Forum)<note
                  xml:id="e2500">Jens Reich (*1939), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57525"
                     >dodis.ch/P57525</ref>, co-author of the appeal<orig> Aufbruch 89 – Neues
                     Forum</orig>.</note> as well as with Mayor Momper<note xml:id="e2506">Walter
                  Momper (*1945), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57440">dodis.ch/P57440</ref>,
                  Governing Mayor of West Berlin 16.2.1989–24.1.1991.</note>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
