<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52930</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52930">dodis.ch/52930</ref>
               <title type="main">Memo<note xml:id="e6203">Memo (translated from German):
                        <idno>Austrian State Archive ÖStA, AdR, BMAA, II-Pol 1990, GZ.
                        22.17.01/173-II.1/90</idno>. Written by Marius Calligaris, <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57521">dodis.ch/P57521</ref> and signed by Johann
                     Plattner, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57520">dodis.ch/P57520</ref>; also
                     published in Wilson Center, doc. 165725. Distributed to the Federal Minister,
                     the General Secretary, the section heads, all departments of the Political
                     Section, and the Austrian diplomatic representations in member states of the
                     CSCE. The information was also part of the preparation file for Franz Vranitzky
                     on the occasion of the visit by Lothar de Maizière to Austria scheduled for 25
                     and 26 July 1990. See <idno>ÖStA Arbeitsbesuch von MP Lothar de Maizière
                        25./26. Juli 1990, Kreisky Archives, Depositum Franz Vranitzky, AP, box BM
                        Choonhavan Chatichai (Thailand), MP Calfa CSFR 1990 PM Silva (Portugal), MP
                        Singh (Indien), Pres. Dubcek (CSFR), PM Kang Young-Hoon (Korea), PM Bhutto
                        (Pakistan), Pres. George Vassiliou (Zypern), MP Maiziere Lothar (DDR)
                        25.7.90)</idno>.</note> by the Austrian Ministry of Foreign Affairs</title>
               <title type="sub">German Unity; State of Affairs in Mid-July 1990</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Vienna, 18 July 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <emph>I. Inner-German Aspects</emph>
            </p>
            <p>The Economic, Monetary and Social union of the two German states entered into effect
               on 1 July 1990. The most essential measure was the introduction of the Deutschmark in
               the GDR. An agreement on the legal and constitutional unification of the two parts of
               Germany is in preparation and should be signed by the autumn of this year.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>All-German Elections</emph>
            </p>
            <p>The next Bundestag election was scheduled for 2 December 1990. In its place,
               all-Germany elections should now take place on that day. The mode of election is
               still at issue. The GDR-CDU advocates for carrying out voting separately in the FRG
               and the GDR (electoral threshold 5%) and the accession of the GDR to the Bonn Basic
               Law only afterwards. The SPD and FDP in both parts of the country are for a unitary
               election in all of Germany (electoral threshold for the whole territory 5%) and the
               accession of the GDR before the election. (This proposal i. a. would mean that the
               PDS, the successor party to the SED in the GDR, may fail to reach the 5% threshold in
               unified Germany.) The West German CDU is divided on the issue.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>II. External Aspects</emph>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the occasion of the recent visit of Chancellor Kohl<note xml:id="e6233">Helmut
                  Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor
                  of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> to Moscow, President Gorbachev<note
                  xml:id="e6239">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707"
                     >dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>
               gave a de facto green light to German unity. The agreement achieved includes the
               following main points:</p>
            <p>– Unified Germany consists of the FRG, GDR and Berlin</p>
            <p>– Full sovereignty of Germany, after unification</p>
            <p>– Soviet consent to NATO membership of unified Germany</p>
            <p>– Soviet troop withdrawal from the territory of the GDR in 3–4 years (a treaty will
               be concluded on this)</p>
            <p>– During which time no extension of NATO structures on GDR territory, however,
               validity of the NATO alliance obligation for it (commitment from Kohl that, also
               later, there will be no non-German troops east of the Elbe)</p>
            <p>– Western Allies military presence in Berlin until completion of the Soviet troop
               withdrawal</p>
            <p>– Reduction of total German forces to 370,000 (Compromise Genscher<note
                  xml:id="e6259">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and
                  Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>-Stoltenberg<note xml:id="e6265">Gerhard Stoltenberg
                  (1928–2001), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46108">dodis.ch/P46108</ref>, Defence
                  Minister of the FRG 21.4.1989–1.4.1992.</note>)</p>
            <p>– Renunciation of ABC weapons by unified Germany</p>
            <p>Gorbachev expressly pointed out that his change of attitude on the issue of German
               NATO membership was made possible by the Moscow-positive result of the recent summit
               of the Alliance in London.</p>
            <p>Chancellor Kohl has furthermore assured massive economic aid to the Soviet Union and
               promised also to advocate for such assistance from other Western states.</p>
            <p>By summer of 1991 a German-Soviet agreement is to be completed, which according to
               Chancellor Kohl will contain co-operation in various fields and regular political
               consultations.</p>
            <p>Reactions to the German-Soviet agreement are unanimously positive worldwide (the case
               of Ridley<note xml:id="e6281">Nicholas Ridley (1929–1993), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P48293">dodis.ch/P48293</ref>, British Secretary of
                  State for Trade and Industry 24.7.1989–13.7.1990.</note> in Great Britain shows
               however the existence of subliminal reservations in individual Western European
               countries towards the weight of the future unified Germany).</p>
            <p>Given the agreement reached in Moscow, the “2+4” talks in Paris on 17 July went
               without controversy. The foreign ministers decided to work out a declaration on
               Germany, in which the external aspects of German unity should be regulated. The
               declaration will be discussed at the next “2+4” round on 12 September in Moscow.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>Polish Western Border</emph>
            </p>
            <p>At the recent “2+4” talks, where the Polish Foreign Minister<note xml:id="e6295"
                  >Krzysztof Skubiszewski (1926–2010), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57377"
                     >dodis.ch/P57377</ref>, Polish Minister of Foreign Affairs
                  12.9.1989–26.10.1993.</note> also participated, the question of the Polish western
               border was at center (the Bonn Bundestag and the GDR People’s Chamber on 21 June
               adopted a statement on the inviolability of the Oder-Neisse line and a border treaty
               to be concluded between Germany and Poland). At this point Poland dropped its final
               demand, whereby the full sovereignty of Germany should only be restored after
               ratification of this border treaty. Agreement has now been reached that the treaty
               will be signed in the shortest possible time after the realization of German unity
               and submitted to the parliament of unified Germany for ratification. (The FRG has
               promised Poland economic aid too.)</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>III. Assessment</emph>
            </p>
            <p>It can now be expected that the unification of the two German states will become
               reality before the end of the year.</p>
            <p>Through the agreements in Moscow and Paris, respectively, the following has been
               achieved:</p>
            <p>The FRG: the realization of German unity</p>
            <p>The West: NATO membership of unified Germany</p>
            <p>The USSR: satisfying its security interests (German troop strength, German
               renunciation of ABC weapons, first steps to change NATO as a condition for the
               reached agreement, beyond this the bargaining chip of a troop presence east of the
               Elbe for 3–4 years) and economic assistance by the FRG or the West.</p>
            <p>From a pan-European perspective, the agreement paves the way for a rapid continuation
               of military negotiations in Vienna and for the objective of setting up a new
               political architecture in Europe.</p>
            <p>For Austria, a point of interest will be i. a. how much impact the efforts of the
               Western European states to firmly “bind Germany to the West” will have on the
               development of the EC (deepening, European Union!).</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
