<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52948</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52948">dodis.ch/52948</ref>
               <title type="main">Extract from the Diary<note xml:id="e573">Diary (translated from
                     German). The diary is privately owned. These extracts were published in German
                     in the <idno>Federal Foreign Office staff magazine “InternAA”, 2012, No. 12, p.
                        8.</idno> Also published in: <idno>Die Einheit. Das Auswärtige Amt, das
                        DDR-Außenministerium und der Zwei-plus-Vier-Prozess, ed. by Horst Möller et.
                        al. on behalf of the Institute for Contemporary History Munich–Berlin,
                        Göttingen, 2015, doc. 19.</idno></note> of the Protocol Officer at the
                  Embassy of the FRG in Warsaw, Rüdiger Freiherr von Fritsch<note xml:id="e576"
                     >Rüdiger Freiherr von Fritsch (*1953), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57375"
                        >dodis.ch/P57375</ref>, Protocol officer at the Embassy of the FRG in Warsaw
                     23.10.1989–15.11.1989. He had served as a Protocol Officer at the Embassy in
                     Warsaw from 1986 to the autumn of 1989 and had already been posted to Nairobi
                     when he was summoned back to Warsaw at short notice in late October 1989 to
                     work on Chancellor Kohl’s long-planned visit to Poland from 9 to 14 November
                     1989.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">Kohl’s Visit and the Fall of the Wall</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Warsaw, 9 and 10 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><emph>Thursday, 9 November 1989</emph>: Early in the morning, Deutsche Welle says:
               “Everything is finally ready. The route has been planned, the communiqués written and
               the Chancellor<note xml:id="e588">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> can now travel to Poland …” If they only knew! The
                  Ambassador<note xml:id="e594">Günther Knackstedt (1929–2012), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57376">dodis.ch/P57376</ref>, Ambassador of the FRG
                  in Warsaw 3.11.1989–1.6.1992.</note> is trying desperately to contact the Foreign
                  Minister<note xml:id="e600">Krzysztof Skubiszewski (1926–2010), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57377">dodis.ch/P57377</ref>, Polish Minister of
                  Foreign Affairs 12.9.1989–26.10.1993.</note>, but is not getting anywhere. Not
               only is the visit programme still up in the air, but the planned joint declaration by
               Kohl and Mazowiecki<note xml:id="e606">Tadeusz Mazowiecki (1927–2013), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57378">dodis.ch/P57378</ref>, Prime Minister of
                  Poland 24.8.1989–12.1.1991.</note>, which has been discussed for months, isn’t
               finished either. The Chancellor has let it be known that he will not leave Bonn until
               it is ready. Yesterday, the discussion focused on whether we should say “of German
               ethnic origin” or “of German descent”. Today, the talk concerns an “and” or “or” in
               some part of the text I’m not familiar with. At some point, that too is resolved. Can
               the Chancellor and his entourage really set off? Warsaw is shrouded in fog! At around
               12.30 p.m., we got the go-ahead from Polish security. The flight was scheduled to
               leave Bonn at 1.00 p.m. … We set off for the airport just after two, the delegation
               arrived and we drove back to the city. Chancellor Kohl has rejected the suggested
               programme for the weekend once again and wants to discuss it with Mazowiecki
               himself.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>At around 6.30 p.m., Genscher<note xml:id="e616">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor
                  and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note> met Adam
                  Michnik<note xml:id="e622">Adam Michnik (*1946), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57379">dodis.ch/P57379</ref>, Member of the Sejm for
                  Solidarnosz and editor-in-chief of the Gazeta Wyborcza.</note>, one of the leading
               figures in the democratic (hitherto) opposition and now editor-in-chief of “Gazeta
               Wyborcza”, Solidarity’s new daily. It was an interesting meeting. Michnik is
               preoccupied with the German Question. For the first time, he said, it feels as if the
               GDR actually exists as a state. Formerly, it was not merely a state with a Soviet
               basis, but rather a Soviet basis with a state. In his opinion, that gives rise to
               entirely new opportunities, also as regards the question of reunification. He said
               people only want to reform the GDR, not renounce it. He’s worried about growing
               nationalism in Europe, particularly in hitherto socialist countries, and sees this as
               a result of radical anti-communism, with the pendulum now swinging the other way.
               This is tangible in Poland, he said, but also in Hungary and the Soviet Union. –
               Earlier on, I heard the news that put everything else in the shade – the GDR has
               opened its borders. Incredible! How will Europe live with that? National
               reunification or European integration, as planned from 1992? Germany must become the
               main topic (of conflict) in Europe in the near future.</p>
            <p><emph>Friday, 10 November 1989</emph>: The events in Germany are all anyone is
               talking about in the government guest house. The Chancellor’s office is talking about
               him flying back at around 5.00 or 5.30 p.m. today. He would then return to Poland,
               maybe tomorrow. It’s all go in the delegation office. Special guests on the
               delegation want to know what’s going on and the journalists are already packing.
               Shortly afterwards, we hear that the Chancellor has decided to fly as early as 2.30
               p.m. Hectic attempts are made to inform the flight crew. Shortly after that, I meet a
               colleague outside the Council of Ministers building who tells me the Chancellor wants
               to fly at 1.30 p.m.! We speed out to the airport, where I speak to the airport
               management by phone. They immediately dispatch security staff and the necessary
               technicians who see what can be done. The plane hasn’t even been refuelled yet. They
               allow our car onto the airfield – the military section!</p>
            <p><emph>12.45 p.m.</emph> The captain doesn’t know yet that the departure has been
               brought forward. “2.00 p.m. at the earliest if it all goes well.” But that means
               there won’t be any food on board. No worries, the main thing is to get away. After
               some discussion, the Polish side is prepared to let the plane take off from its
               parking position, thus saving 20 minutes.</p>
            <p><emph>1.45 p.m.</emph> The plane is ready for take-off. The Polish security people
               are very cooperative and obliging. They don’t bother inspecting passports or
               anything.</p>
            <p>Kohl and Genscher arrive five minutes later. They give a short statement to the press
               and the plane leaves. We draw up a tourism programme from scratch for the special
               delegation members who have been left behind.</p>
            <p>A colleague and I meet Adam Michnik at “Gazeta Wyborcza” at <emph>10.00 p.m.</emph>
               He signs a copy of today’s paper for us. The front page has a picture of Kohl and
               Mazowiecki and the headline “Europe without Walls”. At the dinner afterwards, there
               is a very lively discussion, as always. We talk about Germany, Poland, Russia and
               Europe. We discuss the church, nationalism, republicans and socialism. We cover
               Solidarity and the future, as well as European integration and the German
               Question.</p>
            <p>Michnik is surprised and fascinated by the events in the GDR, which have not changed
               his positive attitude towards German unification in the slightest. In fact, he feels
               the events back up his analysis. He wants to know what we think will happen. What
               would be possible in a situation like this? It’s hard to say what will happen
               tomorrow.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
