<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52949</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52949">dodis.ch/52949</ref>
               <title type="main">Memo<note xml:id="e2122">Memo (translated from German):
                        <idno>Political Archive of the German Federal Foreign Office PA/AA B 32, Bd.
                        179532, file reference 204-322.00 D</idno>. Written by Gebhardt von Moltke,
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57380">dodis.ch/P57380</ref> and Eberhard
                     Kölsch, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57381">dodis.ch/P57381</ref> and signed
                     by Gebhardt von Moltke and Frank Lambach, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57395"
                        >dodis.ch/P57395</ref>. Seen on 16 November 1989 by Karl Heinz Kuhna, <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57382">dodis.ch/P57382</ref> and Dieter Kastrup,
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57383">dodis.ch/P57383</ref>, on 17 November
                     1989 by Jürgen Sudhoff, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57384"
                        >dodis.ch/P57384</ref> and on 20 November 1989 by Hans-Dietrich Genscher.
                     Also published in: <idno>Die Einheit. Das Auswärtige Amt, das
                        DDR-Außenministerium und der Zwei-plus-Vier-Prozess, ed. by Horst Möller et.
                        al. on behalf of the Institute for Contemporary History Munich–Berlin,
                        Göttingen, 2015, doc. 22</idno>.</note> for the Foreign Minister of the FRG,
                  Hans-Dietrich Genscher<note xml:id="e2143">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016),
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor
                     and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">US Reaction to the Events in Berlin and the GDR since 9
                  November</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>
                  <emph>Extract</emph>
               </add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 16 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><emph>For information</emph> (ahead of the forthcoming talks in Washington<note
                  xml:id="e2157">Hans-Dietrich Genscher held talks in Washington on 20 and 21
                  November 1989.</note>)</p>
            <p>1. The events in Berlin and the GDR have <emph>dominated the US media</emph> for
               days. Interest in Germany and German/European-US relations has increased enormously
               among the public (top TV journalists have been sent to Berlin; evening news
               programmes have been broadcast in front of the Wall, with clips of historic scenes;
               there have been special features in the “Washington Post” and “New York Times” and
               Ambassador Ruhfus<note xml:id="e2162">Jürgen Rufus (1930–2018), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57385">dodis.ch/P57385</ref>, Ambassador of the FRG
                  in Washington 16.11.1987–31.8.1992.</note> has given several TV interviews).
               Moving scenes (cheering, joy, spontaneous celebrations) and highly symbolic images
               (the Wall, Brandenburg Gate, people embracing and shedding tears of joy) reflect
               Americans’ tendency to be emotional and preference for images. A <emph>large wave of
                  sympathy</emph> has gripped the entire country. This is of great help to our
               public diplomacy work and we should certainly make use of it. The Embassy and German
               Information Centres are working flat out to do so. The large number of requests for
               interviews provides a unique opportunity for Federal Government officials to present
               Germany and its policies to a broad and receptive US audience.</p>
            <p>2. The resounding echo in the media and among the US public made the
                  <emph>Administration’s reaction</emph>, which largely reflects our own, look
               rather subdued in contrast. The focus is on realism, safeguarding stability and, most
               importantly, preserving unity in NATO. On the evening of 9 November, Bush<note
                  xml:id="e2170">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> said (in Baker’s<note xml:id="e2176">James
                  Baker (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P56605">dodis.ch/P56605</ref>, United
                  States Secretary of State 25.1.1989–23.8.1992.</note> presence and with no
               expression on his face) that he was “very pleased” about the opening of the GDR
               borders. He praised the Federal Government for having “done a magnificent job”, but
               was reserved about further developments and said it was “way too early” to speak
               about reunification. Asked why he did not seem to be “elated”, Bush said he was “just
               not an emotional kind of guy”.</p>
            <p>On the following day, <emph>Baker</emph> said he was “extremely happy”; however, in
               interviews he described an implied connection between the events and reunification as
               “premature” (10.11.1989 MacNeil/Lehrer<note xml:id="e2184">The US journalists Robert
                  MacNeil (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57386">dodis.ch/P57386</ref> and
                  Jim Lehrer (*1934), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57387">dodis.ch/P57387</ref>,
                  hosted <orig>The MacNeil/Lehrer NewsHour</orig> on the TV channel PBS.</note>).
               For his part, Vice-President Quayle<note xml:id="e2193">Dan Quayle (*1947), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57388">dodis.ch/P57388</ref>, Vice-President of the
                  United States, 1989–1993.</note> has said that “the reunification of Germany is
               inevitable”.</p>
            <p>There are <emph>three reasons</emph> for Bush and Baker’s cautious statements:</p>
            <p>– the <emph>desire</emph> to signal to the Soviet Union in the run-up to the summit
               near Malta that the US does not wish to see the <emph>stability of
                  developments</emph> in Central and East Europe and Gorbachev’s<note xml:id="e2203"
                  >Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707"
                     >dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>
               position in light of critics of his reform process <emph>endangered</emph> by
               thoughtless expressions of feelings of triumph. Bush and Baker are thus interpreting
               Gorbachev’s concerns correctly (cf. Gorbachev’s message to Bush on the night of 10/11
               November, in which he said that he was “very concerned about the possibility of
               destabilisation”; similar reaction by Ambassador Kotchemassov<note xml:id="e2209"
                  >Vyacheslav Kotchemasov (1918–1998), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57389"
                     >dodis.ch/P57389</ref>, Soviet Ambassador in East Berlin 1983–1990.</note> in a
               meeting with Ambassador Walters<note xml:id="e2215">Vernon A. Walters (1917–2002),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54605">dodis.ch/P54605</ref>US Ambassador in
                  Bonn 1989–1991.</note> in East Berlin on 11 November.) Referring explicitly to
                  <emph>your telephone call</emph> (10 November), Baker underlined that the
               development in the GDR was also an <emph>achievement resulting from the united stance
                  shown by the US and NATO</emph> (10.11. MacNeil/Lehrer, 12.11. Brinkley<note
                  xml:id="e2221">The US journalist David Brinkley (1920–2003), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57390">dodis.ch/P57390</ref>, hosted the news
                  broadcast <orig>This Week</orig> on the TV channel ABC.</note>). <emph>Secretary
                  of Defence Cheney</emph><note xml:id="e2227">Dick Cheney (*1941), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57391">dodis.ch/P57391</ref>, United States Secretary
                  of Defense 21.3.1989–28.6.1992.</note> reacted in a similar, but more forceful
               way;</p>
            <p><emph>– concern</emph> that a more emphatic reaction would inevitably lead to the
               question of <emph> practical measures</emph> to support reform in the GDR, with
                  <emph>financial implications</emph> – and at a time when the Administration was
               being criticised for not providing enough financial support for the reform process in
               Poland and Hungary.</p>
            <p>– Bush and Baker’s <emph>characters</emph> and governing style based on a
               case-by-case approach to crisis management, which deliberately refrains from using
               far-reaching concepts.</p>
            <p>The <emph>summit with Gorbachev</emph> on 2 and 3 December has become even more
               relevant on account of the events in the GDR. The Administration is doing everything
               it can to counteract the impression that it wants to make decisions over the allies’
               heads at this summit on far-reaching arrangements on a postwar order in Central
               Europe. On the other hand, Bush’s and Baker’s reactions, as far as we have seen so
               far, <emph>merely hint</emph> that the West already has a concept for a European
               peace order and proven instruments for West East dialogue in the form of the
                  <emph>Harmel Report</emph><note xml:id="e2239"><orig>Report of the Council on the
                     Future Tasks of the Alliance (Harmel Report)</orig> of 13 and 14 December 1967,
                     <ref target="https://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/topics_67927.htm"
                     >https://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/topics_67927.htm</ref>.</note> and the
                  <emph>CSCE process</emph>.</p>
            <p>The Administration has not commented so far on the German side’s (Bahr<note
                  xml:id="e2247">Egon Bahr (1922–2015), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P39530"
                     >dodis.ch/P39530</ref>, Member of the SPD.</note>, Geiger<note xml:id="e2253"
                  >Michaela Geiger (1943–1988), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57392"
                     >dodis.ch/P57392</ref>, Member of the CSU and Bundestag 1980–1998.</note>;
                  Gaus<note xml:id="e2259">Günter Gaus (1929–2004), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P55113">dodis.ch/P55113</ref>, Journalist.</note>)
                  <emph>proposal to hold a four-power conference</emph> on Germany.</p>
            <p>
               <add type="edition">[…]</add>
               <note xml:id="e2268">For the complete version of the document in German cf. <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/52949">dodis.ch/52949</ref>.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
