<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52941</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52941">dodis.ch/52941</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e6402">Telegram No. ZQGR1429 (incoming):
                        <idno>Global Affairs Canada file 25-3-3-5-Germany / Confidential</idno>.
                     Ref: <idno>Tel. ZQGR1224 16 Jul 90.</idno> Info to Moscow, Washington, London,
                     Paris, Paris-OECD, Copenhagen, Stockholm, Rome, Hague, Oslo, Brussels-EEC,
                     Brussels-NATO, Military Representation to NATO, Vienna, Delegation to the
                     Organization for Securtiy and Cooperation in Europe, Warsaw, Belgrade,
                     Bucharest, Budapest, Permanent Mission New York, Geneva, Prague, Privy Council
                     Office, Office of the Prime Minister, Department of Finance, National Defence
                     Headquarters.</note> from the Canadian Ambassador in Bonn, Thomas W.
                     Delworth<note xml:id="e6405">Thomas W. Delworth (1929–2012), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P51338">dodis.ch/P51338</ref>, Canadian Ambassador
                     in Bonn 1987–1992.</note> , to the Canadian Department of External
                  Affairs</title>
               <title type="sub">Germany: The Summer of 1990</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 23 July 1990 </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Summary: an unbelievable summer continues to contribute to an improbable year. Last
               week’s Soviet concession that united German membership in NATO was now acceptable and
               the Two-Plus-Four agreement in Paris on Polish western borders have effectively
               removed the final international barriers to German reunification. The devil, to adapt
               an old German adage, may reside in the remaining details, but at the moment at least
               there is confidence on all sides that they will be overcome, and on schedule. It is,
               however, already clear that the impact on Europe of its reunited centre will be
               profound. Still to be gauged is the precise nature of this impact. The presence of a
               united Germany – and the momentous change that gave rise to it – will affect
               virtually all aspects of the way in which Canada and Canadians have thought not only
               about Europe but also about the transatlantic relationship. A reunited Germany could
               well necessitate the readjustment of some of the fundamental assumptions in Canadian
               foreign policy, including our views of the role of the alliance, and our place in
               East/West relations.</p>
            <p>2. Report: in retrospect it is clear that Soviet intentions behind the chain of
               events that led to the breach of the Wall on 9 November 1989 were foreshadowed in the
               joint Soviet/FRG declaration of 13 June of that year. In it, Gorbachev endorsed the
               principle of national self-determination, thus effectively burying the Brezhnev
               doctrine of limited sovereignty and of the irreversibility of Communism. At the time,
               German officials who had worked on the declaration were jubilant, but few others took
               its implications to heart. By November, the SED ideologist, Otto Reinhold<note
                  xml:id="e6422">Otto Reinhold (1925–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57476"
                     >dodis.ch/P57476</ref>, Member and ideologist of the SED.</note>, was saying on
               West German television that a GDR without socialism would lose its legitimacy. The
               end of Honecker<note xml:id="e6428">Erich Honecker (1912–1994), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P46563">dodis.ch/P46563</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED and chairman of the GDR State Council 29.10.1976–18.10.1989.</note> by the
               turn of the year, and the reduction of the SED in the spring elections to a splinter
               party proved his point: the GDR had voted to abolish itself. What happened between
               then and now looks like the working out of some sort of inexorable logic of history,
               but there was also virtually unbelievable German good luck, combined with political
               courage and determination not only on Gorbachev’s<note xml:id="e6434">Mikhail
                  Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>,
                  General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991,
                  Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and
                  President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> part but also by East
               Europeans. Among the latter were members of the then Hungarian government who in the
               autumn of 1989 took the brave decision to break their treaty commitments with their
               East German partners by permitting GDR refugees in Hungary to flow west, knowing full
               well that such a decision was crossing a Communist Rubicon, and would create a crisis
               within the Eastern Bloc from which recovery was unlikely.</p>
            <p>3. So greatly have times changed at this point that Chancellor Kohl<note
                  xml:id="e6442">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852"
                     >dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> went
               to Moscow last week, returning with Soviet agreement on a united Germany in NATO.
               This agreement is more striking because it was reached independent of any visible,
               direct relationship to the Two-Plus-Four process, and removed in detail from anything
               but the broadest NATO imprimatur (so far as we know there was no prior NATO
               consultation on the reduction of German troop levels offered by Kohl, or on the
               agreement that the 380,000 Soviet troops leave Germany no later than 1994). A strong
               USA profile in this deal was, moreover, noticeable by its absence: the Bush<note
                  xml:id="e6448">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> administration had already accepted that
               Germany would go its own way on economic support to the East, whatever decisions were
               or were not taken at the Houston Summit. This laissez-faire approach on the mechanics
               of German unification seems generally shared by other allies, the Ridley<note
                  xml:id="e6454">Nicholas Ridley (1929–1993), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P48293"
                     >dodis.ch/P48293</ref>, British Minister of Trade and Industry
                  24.7.1989–13.7.1990.</note> affair notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>4. This is a great Western victory: removing the Iron Curtain from Central Europe and
               opening the way to the final achievement of the goals we set for ourselves at the
               beginning of the CSCE process in the 1970s, this is the much-to-be-welcomed
               culmination of a remarkable team effort, despite occasional doubts, hiccups and false
               starts. According to Foreign Minister Shevardnadze<note xml:id="e6462">Eduard
                  Shevardnadze (1928–2014), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54603"
                     >dodis.ch/P54603</ref>, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union
                  2.7.1985–26.12.1990.</note>, the London NATO Summit, in transforming the purpose
               of the alliance, prepared the way for Soviet agreement on a united Germany in NATO.
               On 19 November, everything will culminate at the Paris CSCE meeting when German union
               will be recognized (presumably in a declaration) by all participating states and
               where new security structures under CSCE auspices will be established at the same
               time as CFE I concludes and the final agreement on the elimination of Four Power
               rights in Germany is reached. A breathtaking agenda for a single relatively brief
               meeting.</p>
            <p>5. The original deal at Potsdam looking to a democratic Europe is thus being
               implemented after a delay of some 40 years. German reunification and its concomitant
               twin, the revolution in Eastern Europe, have drastically changed what the Russians
               used to call the correlation of forces in Central Europe. With German union, the
               Western European political and economic equilibrium at least symbolically shifts its
               centre of gravity away from the Rhine towards the Elbe. Despite various studies that
               we and our allies have undertaken, the shape of such a transformed Europe is barely
               visible; many studies have focussed on the processes of German union, implications
               for NATO etc., but few on the facts, as rearranged, following union. These latter are
               virtually upon us. First among them is that the West German identity assumed by the
               FRG which virtually everyone has taken as a given, will perforce begin its
               disappearance the day a united Germany is proclaimed. A reunited Germany will be much
               greater than the sum of its parts, the FRG plus the GDR plus Berlin. But what in fact
               will it be?</p>
            <p>6. The Federal German Republic had already emerged as the Western European primus
               inter pares, and with de facto Soviet withdrawal in the East, a united Germany will
               become the predominant power in an area which Germans (and their Austrian cousins)
               have historically contested with the Russians. Here, the paradox is that as the FRG
               emerged as the dominant economic power in Europe it remained only a quasi-sovereign
               country, militarily limited in many respects by the terms of various NATO agreements,
               and by a kind of political self-censorship in its dealings with both East and West,
               particularly on security issues. With the imminent emergence of a fully sovereign,
               united Germany (with of course, one or two transitional arrangements) this era is
               virtually at an end.</p>
            <p>7. Obviously, the effects of German union on the allied military presence in the FRG
               will be direct and immediate, with long-term implications for force levels and
               structures. As Soviet withdrawals in the East continue, a vacuum could well be
               created, generating a host of other security problems which CSCE mechanisms now under
               negotiation are designed to address: in theory, the old East/West security structures
               will be replaced by an institutional role for the CSCE, inter- and intra-alliance
               cooperation and non-aggression treaties with the USSR and Poland. This may well be a
               promising beginning but it is unlikely to be the end of the story. Whatever role CSCE
               mechanisms may eventually play, the reassertion of German economic power and
               political influence in Eastern Europe is a process already begun. Unification will
               intensify this process as Germany becomes primus inter pares in Central Europe as
               well. The Maoist dictum that political power grows out of the barrel of a gun has
               been disproved by German bankers, and mere possession of nuclear weapons by the UK
               and France as a means for wielding political influence has proven no match for the
               Deutsche Mark.</p>
            <p>8. Chancellor Kohl has sought to play down the significance of the profound changes
               now underway, speaking of a united Germany as the “rational centre of Europe” and of
               the German ability to act as a clearing house of ideas between Western and Eastern
               Europe. For some time yet, a united Germany will indeed be preoccupied with internal
               matters. There are dislocations in the GDR created by the onset of capitalism – its
               aggressive West German variety has so far been underplayed by the FRG coalition, but
               already the effects on GDR agriculture and industry have been profound. The
               complexity of the issues involved in the new Germany’s European vocation are
               miniaturized in the debate over whether the capital of a united Germany should be
               Berlin. De Maiziere<note xml:id="e6476">Lothar de Maizière (*1940), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54809">dodis.ch/P54809</ref>, GDR Prime Minister
                  12.4–2.10.1990.</note> has unwisely made this a pre-condition for union, and
               President von Weizsäcker<note xml:id="e6482">Richard von Weizsäcker (1920–2015), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P5944">dodis.ch/P5944</ref>, President of the FRG
                  1.7.1984–30.6.1994.</note> (for unknown reasons) has also entered an intensely
               political debate on the side of Berlin. There is thus revealed a second debate about
               whether Germany should now turn to the East as much as it had turned to the West.
               With big metropolitan Berlin – a major European city by any standards – the vision of
               an Eastern empire comes virtually to mind. For many Germans, to opt for Berlin is to
               opt for an eastern “empire”, an eastern economic hinterland. This is feared as much
               by many Germans as it is by others.</p>
            <p>9. In the rush of events over German unification and the transformation of Eastern
               Europe, one overarching fact is occasionally missed. The strongest military power in
               Europe remains the Soviet Union, and in many respects, and in ways still difficult to
               measure, the Soviet Union retains its full potential as arbiter of events in Central
               Europe, perhaps now less in conjunction with its transatlantic superpower partner and
               more with the new Germany: the determination of events in Europe is now more firmly
               in the hands of Europeans in ways not thought possible only a few months ago.</p>
            <p>10. Even as German preoccupations over completing the integration of its eastern with
               its western parts will continue, post-unification, it is certain that German
               reticence internationally will disappear. Of necessity and inevitability, there will
               be pressure for the building of a truly global German foreign policy beyond the range
               of relatively narrowly-focused matters as now practised by the FRG. The effects of
               the emergence of this Central European superpower on our present transatlantic
               relationship with the FRG is as yet discernable in only the vaguest outline. As
               Germany unites, grows together and begins to flex its new muscles many of the
               assumptions Canada has so long held vis-à-vis the FRG will need the closest
               re-examination if we are to maximize the strengths we can draw from relationships
               with a transformed Europe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
