<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53168</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-05-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53168">dodis.ch/53168</ref>
               <title type="main">Draft memo<note xml:id="e47">Draft memo (translated from Polish):
                        <idno>Archives of the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs AMSZ, Dep. IV
                        31/92, w. 3.</idno></note> by the Director of the 4<hi>th</hi> Department of
                  the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Janusz Fekecz<note xml:id="e53">Janusz
                     Fekecz (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P53484">dodis.ch/P57377</ref>,
                     Polish Minister of Foreign Affairs 12.9.1989–26.10.1993.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">Memorandum Concerning the Citizens of the German Democratic
                  Republic who Remain at the Embassy of the Federal Republic of Germany in
                  Warsaw</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Warsaw, 14 September 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">I. On 13 September, Minister K. Skubiszewski<note xml:id="e67">Friedrich Bauer
                  (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P51060">dodis.ch/P51060</ref>, Austrian
                  Ambassador in Bonn 1986–1990.</note> received the Director of the MFA’s Political
               Department Kastrup<note xml:id="e73">Dieter Kastrup (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57383">dodis.ch/P57383</ref>, Political Director in
                  the FRG Foreign Ministry, 1988–1991 and head of delegation to the 2+4
                  conference.</note>, who arrived in Poland as Minister Genscher’s<note xml:id="e79"
                  >Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414"
                     >dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the
                  FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note> special envoy to discuss the group of GDR citizens
               remaining at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw. The talks were also attended by Ambassador
                  Schoeller<note xml:id="e85">Franz Jochen Schoeller (*1926), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57583">dodis.ch/P57583</ref>, Ambassador of the FRG
                  in Warsaw 1987–1989.</note> and Deputy Director of the MFA’s 4<hi>th</hi>
               Department Sułek<note xml:id="e94">Jerzy Sułek (*1939), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57584">dodis.ch/P57584</ref>, Deputy Director of the
                     4<hi>th</hi> Department in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and from May 1990
                  Director of the Polish MFA’s Europe Department.</note>.</p>
            <p>Director Kastrup explained that the aim of his trip to Poland was to hold talks with
               over 50 GDR citizens who are currently at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw and seeking to
               leave for the FRG for a permanent stay, and to present the official position of the
               West German side to the Polish authorities.</p>
            <p>He referred to a conversation between Minister Genscher and L. Wałęsa<note
                  xml:id="e107">Lech Wałęsa (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57585"
                     >dodis.ch/P57585</ref>, Chairman of the Independent Self-Governing Trade Union
                  “Solidarity” and President of Poland 22.12.1990–22.12.1995.</note> held in Bonn on
               8 September, during which the West German foreign minister praised the Hungarian
               authorities for their approach to the departure of GDR citizens from the FRG Embassy
               in Budapest and the Hungarian territory for the FRG via Austria, and requested L.
               Wałęsa, as a representative of the new Poland, to apply “the Hungarian solution” to
               the group of GDR citizens remaining at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw. At the same time,
               Minister Genscher emphasized the historic importance of this issue for the West-East
               relationship in Europe, and to human rights in general. According to Kastrup, L.
               Wałęsa promised Genscher that the “Hungarian model” would be followed in Poland.</p>
            <p>Director Kastrup made it clear that the FRG would not set out German legal positions
               in the case at hand (“it would be irrelevant which travel documents entitled the GDR
               citizens to leave Poland”). The FRG would prefer a pragmatic solution that took
               account of humanitarian considerations. To that end, they would be ready to get the
               Polish Red Cross, the German Red Cross and possibly also the International Committee
               of the Red Cross in Geneva on board. Both Kastrup and Ambassador Schoeller expressed
               their hope that the Polish authorities would show understanding and support for West
               German efforts to arrange the departure of GDR citizens for the FRG. They emphasized
               that the focus of attention of the West German public and media was on the GDR
               citizens at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw, just as it was for those at the FRG Embassy in
               Prague. In reply to Minister Skubiszewski’s question, Director Kastrup described the
               Hungarian authorities’ decision to allow GDR citizens to leave for the FRG en masse
               as a “humanitarian gesture in a European spirit”. In this context, he recalled
               Genscher’s words to the Hungarian authorities: “We will never forget what you
               did.”</p>
            <p>Minister Skubiszewski observed that the Polish side was also in favour of a pragmatic
               and humanitarian solution to the issue of the GDR citizens remaining at the FRG
               Embassy in Warsaw. From our standpoint, the best option would be an amicable
               settlement reached by the East and West German authorities, one that would respect
               the interests of both governments as well as the people concerned. Poland advocated
               the observance of human rights, including the principle of free flow of people. In
               the case at hand, however, we had to bear in mind the good of Poland’s relations with
               West and East Germany. He explained that he had not had the opportunity to
               familiarize himself with the content of Minister Genscher’s conversation with L.
               Wałęsa. The stance of the Polish authorities would be determined by arrangements to
               be made directly by the governments of the two German states with respect to the GDR
               citizens remaining at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw.</p>
            <p>Director Kastrup recalled that the FRG had held talks with the GDR about the East
               German citizens staying at the FRG Permanent Representation in Berlin and at FRG
               diplomatic missions accredited in socialist countries. In contrast to the
               arrangements that had regulated similar cases in the past, this time the GDR
               authorities were reluctant to issue a “silent guarantee” allowing such people to
               leave for the FRG (the GDR’s policy at the time had been to “consider favourably”
               applications for an exit permit). This time round, the GDR would only be willing to
               guarantee its citizens staying at the Embassies in Prague and Warsaw (until recently
               also Budapest) that after their return to the GDR, they would avoid punishment or
               consequences at their workplace, and would be granted representation by a lawyer when
               they appeared before East German administrative authorities. What the GDR authorities
               would not accept was that such citizens should be able to leave a third state
               directly for the FRG, as had been happening under “the Hungarian solution”.
               Consequently, people who were staying at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw could only have “a
               very vague hope” of leaving for West Germany. In Kastrup’s view, the GDR authorities
               were unlikely to change their position at that stage, which was why talks between
               both German states had stalled.</p>
            <p>Minister Skubiszewski concluded the meeting by reiterating that we appreciated the
               importance of the humanitarian aspect involved in the issue of GDR citizens remaining
               at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw, and were aware of the possible ramifications for our
               relations with West and East Germany. He promised to look into the matter and give a
               concrete reply setting out the Polish position.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">II. On 13 September, Director Kastrup and Ambassador Schoeller were also
               received by J. Czyrek<note xml:id="e125">Józef Czyrek (1928–2013), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P44031">dodis.ch/P44031</ref>, member of the Political
                  Bureau and Secretary of the Central Committee of the Polish United Workers’ Party
                  and Minister of State in the Office of the Polish President 1989–1991.</note>, the
               Minister of State at the President’s Office. One of the topics discussed was the
               problem of over 50 GDR citizens staying at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw and wanting to
               leave for West Germany.</p>
            <p>Director Kastrup emphasized that he was aware of the fundamental differences on legal
               matters between the People’s Republic of Poland and the Federal Republic of Germany.
               Even so, the West German side sought a pragmatic solution with humanitarian
               dimensions. Minister Czyrek asked for an explanation of the political context of the
               problem, given recent declarations by the Federal Republic of Germany that it was not
               interested in destabilizing the GDR, and was keen to ensure the appropriate standards
               in that country in order to stem emigration. Did the current situation point to a
               shift in West German policy? (The FRG was creating many incentives to encourage
               immigration). K<add type="edition">[astrup]</add> emphasized that “human matters”
               could not be separated from politics. Young East Germans saw no opportunities for
               themselves (this went beyond mere economic motivation); they had been following news
               about the progress of reforms in the USSR, Poland and Hungary. Meanwhile, the current
               East German leadership was unable to solve these problems. “Mass fleeing” had its
               roots solely in the GDR, so a policy change in the FRG was not a factor here. K<add
                  type="edition">[astrup]</add> underscored that he was requesting “humanitarian
               assistance in solving this problem, while taking account of human rights”. Minister
               Czyrek replied that he appreciated the humanitarian dimension of the issue. We would
               not try to “turn it into a problem”. From the logical and substantive points of view,
               this was primarily a matter to be settled between East and West Germany, however, and
               as such should be resolved by way of an understanding between the two countries. Such
               an understanding would be decisive for Poland, as we could be loyal both to the FRG
               and GDR. Minister Czyrek referred to Minister Skubiszewski’s decision as presented
               during the talks with K<add type="edition">[astrup]</add> , whereby a working group
               would be set up as a matter of urgency to draft proposals for a Polish position.</p>
            <p>Minister Czyrek went on to underline that the matter was very difficult for Poland,
               as we viewed our friendly relations with the GDR as a serious issue and, unlike
               Hungary, we have no direct border with any Western states.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">III. Conclusions</p>
            <p>a) The issue of GDR citizens remaining at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw could have
               negative repercussions for either of the two German states, depending on which
               solution we support. If we side with the GDR, we risk negative effects in the context
               of Kohl’s<note xml:id="e150">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> visit to Poland<note xml:id="e156">Helmut Kohl
                  visited Poland on 9–10 and 12–14 November 1989 (following the fall of the Berlin
                  Wall, Chancellor Kohl interrupted his visit to go back to the FRG).</note>; if we
               go along with West German proposals, the political fallout could affect our
               relationship with the GDR.</p>
            <p>b) From our point of view, the best way out would be if the two German states
               achieved an amicable settlement between themselves. At this stage, however, such a
               solution is unlikely and we are under permanent pressure from representatives of both
               countries (see J. Mąkosa’s<note xml:id="e161">Jerzy Mąkosa, <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P50485">dodis.ch/P50485</ref>, Director of the
                     1<hi>st</hi> Department at the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                  1989–1990.</note> memo of 12 September on the conversation with GDR Ambassador J.
               van Zwoll<note xml:id="e170">Jürgen van Zwoll (*1939), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57587">dodis.ch/P57587</ref>, Ambassador of the GDR
                  in Warsaw 1988–1990.</note>).</p>
            <p>c) In these circumstances, the MFA has set up a working group headed by B.
                  Kulski<note xml:id="e178">Bolesław Kulski, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P50550"
                     >dodis.ch/P50550</ref>, Polish Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs
                  1988–1990.</note> to come up with possible solutions. What could prove helpful for
               us would be a solution to be adopted in the next few days in the similar case in
               Prague.</p>
            <p>d) One should bear in mind that the problem will continue to grow (the number of GDR
               citizens at the FRG Embassy in Warsaw increased to 50 in the course of two
               weeks).</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
