<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53172</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53172">dodis.ch/53172</ref>
               <title type="main">Circular telegram<note xml:id="e3466">Telegram No. 775 (copy,
                     translated from Polish): <idno>Archives of the Polish Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs AMSZ, ZD 33/92</idno>. Delivered to the Cryptography Section:
                        <orig>1 February 1990, 2.30 p.m.</orig> Addressed to the heads of post in
                     Moscow, Berlin A., Prague, Budapest, Sofia, Bucharest, Belgrade, II Paris, I
                     London, I Rome, I Berlin – I Mission, Cologne, I The Hague, II Madrid, I
                     Lisbon, I Vienna, I Bern, II Athens, II Stockholm, I Copenhagen, II Helsinki, I
                     Oslo, I Washington, IV Ottawa, IV Mexico City, IV Buenos Aires, Brasilia, New
                     Delhi, Beijing, Tokyo, Canberra, New York – Mission, IV Geneva – Mission
                     II.</note> by the Polish Minister of Foreign Affairs, Krzysztof
                     Skubiszewski<note xml:id="e3469">Krzysztof Skubiszewski (1926–2010), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57377">dodis.ch/P57377</ref>, Polish Minister of
                     Foreign Affairs 12.9.1989–26.10.1993.</note></title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Urgent</add>
               <dateline>Warsaw, 1 February 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>With regard to the ongoing discussion about German reunification, please find below
               the position to be presented during talks:</p>
            <p>The Polish government set out its position on the unity of the German nation under
               international law or as a state in the foreign minister’s statement to the Sejm of 7
               December 1989. The Polish government made it clear that it respects the right of the
               Germans to self-determination. However, this right can be realized in the framework
               of European order and stabilization. This order includes the existing borders between
               the two German states and their neighbours. Both German states can only unite – in
               one form or another – provided that Poland’s western border along the Oder and
               Lusatian Neisse rivers is maintained. The rapprochement and ultimately fusion of the
               two German states should proceed gradually even as our continent’s unity is restored
               and a new security system is built in Europe. This is a complex and multi-stage
               process. The unity of the German nation cannot be restored with a one-off declaration
               or act. Changes across German territory must go hand-in-hand with changes in Europe
               that support building structures that would encompass the whole of Europe. This does
               not rule out regional institutions made up of certain countries, however. A reunited
               German state will have its place in a thoroughly reformed and united Europe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
