<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53174</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53174">dodis.ch/53174</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum<note xml:id="e7087">Memorandum (translated from
                     Polish): <idno>Archives of the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs AMSZ, Dep. IV
                        15/94, w. 1</idno>. Prepared by Jerzy Sułek, <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57584">dodis.ch/P57584</ref>.</note> by the Polish
                  Minister of Foreign Affairs, Krzysztof Skubiszewski<note xml:id="e7093">Krzysztof
                     Skubiszewski (1926–2010), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57377"
                        >dodis.ch/P57377</ref>, Polish Minister of Foreign Affairs
                     12.9.1989–26.10.1993.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">Urgent Note Concerning the Talks between Prime Minister T.
                     Mazowiecki<note xml:id="e7100">Tadeusz Mazowiecki (1927–2013), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57378">dodis.ch/P57378</ref>, Prime Minister of
                     Poland 24.8.1989–12.1.1991.</note> and Chancellor H. Kohl<note xml:id="e7106"
                     >Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852"
                        >dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>
                  in Frankfurt an der Oder and Slubice on 8 November this Year</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Warsaw, 11 November 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I. In the course of talks held by Prime Minister T. Mazowiecki and the FRG’s Federal
               Chancellor H. Kohl in Frankfurt an der Oder and Slubice on 8 November the following
               was arranged:</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>1. Treaties</emph>
            </p>
            <p>a) This November in Warsaw, the Foreign Ministers are to sign a Treaty between the
               Republic of Poland and the Federal Republic of Germany confirming the existing border
               between them<note xml:id="e7123"><orig>Treaty between the Republic of Poland and the
                     Federal Republic of Germany Concerning the Demarcation of the Established and
                     Existing Polish-German State Frontier</orig> signed in Warsaw on 14 November
                  1990.</note>.</p>
            <p>b) The process to negotiate the Treaty on Good Neighbourhood and Friendly Cooperation
               is to be completed by late January 1991<note xml:id="e7128"><orig>Treaty between the
                     Republic of Poland and the Federal Republic of Germany on Good Neighbourly
                     Relations and Friendly Cooperation</orig> signed in Bonn on 17 June
                  1991.</note>.</p>
            <p>c) The two aforementioned treaties will be submitted together for ratification by the
               parliaments of Poland and FRG, by late February 1991 at the latest.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>2. Movement of people</emph>
            </p>
            <p>a) The FRG government has already decided to lift the visa requirement for Polish
               citizens (on a reciprocal basis) and intends to implement this decision later this
                  year<note xml:id="e7139"><orig>Agreement on the Abolition of the Visa
                     Requirement</orig> concluded in the form of exchange of notes on 4 April
                  1991.</note>. With this in mind, it entered into official consultations with
               France and the Benelux countries (the so-called Schengen group). A positive decision
               by the Schengen Five is due in late November; it would make it possible to remove
               visas for travel to these countries, before Christmas if possible (by way of an
               exchange of diplomatic notes).</p>
            <p>b) Polish consular, passport, and customs services will take actions — in
               coordination with their counterparts from the FRG, France, Belgium, the Netherlands,
               and Luxembourg — to ensure smooth handling of the expected increased movement of
               people from and to Poland and to ensure it is not abused for purposes that contradict
               the agreement about to be concluded (e.g. illicit trade, smuggling, taking up work
               without permit). The number of border crossings will be expanded; they will be
               extended and upgraded; passport and customs clearances will be simplified and
               streamlined but with the simultaneous introduction of more stringent customs checks
               and more severe administrative measures against people who abuse the freedom of
               visa-free travel, etc.</p>
            <p>c) As soon as possible, i.e. to the extent practicable in the first quarter of 1991,
               a pilot project will be launched: the construction, at the FRG’s cost, of a
               10km-section of a six-lane motorway on both sides of the border (5km from Frankfurt
               an der Oder into Germany + 5km from Swiecko into Poland.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>3. Regional cooperation, especially between border regions</emph>
            </p>
            <p>a) The following will be established: A Joint Inter-Governmental Commission for
               Regional Cooperation and a Joint Border Commission (composed of representatives of
               Polish provinces, border towns, communes and FRG Länder located along the
               border).</p>
            <p>b) In 1991, a separate Poland-FRG treaty will be made on regional cooperation.</p>
            <p>c) Relevant provisions will be adopted in the Treaty on Good Neighbourhood and
               Friendly Cooperation.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>4. Youth exchange</emph>
            </p>
            <p>Youth exchanges should grow several times in 1991 as compared with this year
               (expected levels of 6,000–7,000 people). The composition of the Polish-German Youth
               Exchange Council will be considerably changed. Furthermore, a joint Office for the
               organisation of youth exchanges will be established (modelled after the
               Deutsch-Französisches Jugendwerk).</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>5. Aid for forced labourers and concentration camp prisoners</emph>
            </p>
            <p>In January 1991, the heads of government of the two countries will reach agreement
               about using a pragmatic approach (foundation, fund) with respect to the
               aforementioned category of Polish citizens who had suffered under the Third
               Reich.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>II. On <emph>economic and financial cooperation</emph> between Poland and the
               FRG:</p>
            <p>1. A list of our most important proposals and suggestions will be drawn up, together
               with a short statement of grounds (non-paper), which will be conveyed to the FRG
               accompanied by a personal letter from Prime Minister T. Mazowiecki to Chancellor
               Kohl; this will be a working basis for talks between Deputy Prime Minister L.
                  Balcerowicz<note xml:id="e7174">Leszek Balcerowicz (*1947), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57596">dodis.ch/P57596</ref>, Polish Deputy Prime
                  Minister and Minister of Finance 1989–1991.</note> and H. Kohl (the FRG Chancellor
               reiterated his invitation for a visit). On this basis, H. Kohl will support relevant
               Polish efforts at the EEC summit (14 December this year), in the Paris Club, and
               among the 24 countries. The non-paper should specifically address such issues as
               Poland’s association with the EEC, write-off of Poland’s debts, compensation for the
               losses over the Gulf crisis, cooperation projects within the FRG-Poland-USSR triangle
               (e.g. construction of homes for Soviet soldiers returning from the former GDR, food
               shipments for the USSR), or perhaps the issue of Poland’s losses in connection with
               the reunification of Germany.</p>
            <p>2. <emph>Employment of Polish contract workers in Germany:</emph> Our consent to
               signing a new Polish-German pension agreement has been made conditional on the
               acceptance of our proposal, i.e. retention of the current employment limits (11,000
               in the FRG, 35,000 in the former GDR).</p>
            <p>
               <emph>3. Financial and economic costs of German reunification</emph>
            </p>
            <p>If this issue cannot be resolved still this year, the heads of Polish and FRG
               governments will raise the issue of <emph>rouble conversions</emph> in our trade with
               the former GDR area in January 1991.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>III. Other</emph>
            </p>
            <p>1. <emph>Transfer of military equipment, weapons and ammunition from the FRG to
                  Poland from the stocks of the former GDR National People’s Army:</emph> H. Kohl
               has agreed to meet some of the Polish side’s requests (mainly with respect to
               ammunition, rifles, and combat vehicles); this matter will be conclusively settled
               during the coming FRG visit of the Polish Minister of National Defence<note
                  xml:id="e7192">Piotr Kołodziejczyk (*1939), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57612"
                     >dodis.ch/P57612</ref>, Polish Minister of National Defence
                  6.7.1990–23.12.1991.</note>. It will be also essential for Poland to obtain
               approval from the USSR. At H. Kohl’s request, this matter should for the time being
               be given a low profile (pending its successful conclusion), among others because of
               similar efforts by Hungary and the Czech and Slovak Federative Republic.</p>
            <p>2. <emph>Transit of Soviet troops from the former GDR through Poland into the
                  USSR</emph> (costs to be covered by the FRG). A joint panel of experts will be set
               up to discuss this issue. It will be also raised during the FRG visit of the Polish
               Minister of National Defence.</p>
            <p>3. <emph>Reinstallation of a TV/radio transmitter on Sniezka</emph> (removed in 1980
               at the request of the GDR), funded by the FRG, for broadcasting in Polish, German,
               and Czech. Prime Minister T. Mazowiecki has promised to grant this FRG request; at
               the same time he noted the need to implement projects to launch TV/radio channels for
               the Polish diaspora and emigrants in the FRG.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>IV. I ask the ministries concerned to promptly contact the relevant FRG authorities
               in order to implement the aforementioned decisions. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs
               is to be updated on an ongoing basis on progress in this area.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
