<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53320</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53320">dodis.ch/53320</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e1161">Telegram No. 105/2 (copy, translated
                     from Turkish): <idno>Turkish Diplomatic Archives 3211439</idno>. Delivered to
                     the duty officer at the communications centre: 1<orig>1 November 1989 2.10
                        p.m.</orig> Copy to the Turkish Embassy in Bonn. Ref: <idno>a)
                        non-confidential telegram No. 905 b) non-confidential telegram No.
                        941</idno>.</note> from the Turkish Ambassador in East Berlin, Metin
                     Mekik<note xml:id="e1164">Metin Mekik (1932–2013), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57531">dodis.ch/P57531</ref>, Turkish Ambassador
                     in East Berlin.</note> , to the Turkish Ministry of Foreign Affairs</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Extremely urgent</add>
               <dateline>East Berlin, 11 November 1989, 1.00 p.m.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>1) Following the opening of the Berlin Wall, the important information and
               observation gathered by our embassy from the western and local media concerning the
               recent developments which occurred in Berlin during the night of 10 November and this
               morning (11 November) are summarized as submitted below:</p>
            <p>On 10 November, more than 40 thousand citizens of the German Democratic Republic
               crossed to West Berlin. The crossing process continues at a rate of 100 vehicles and
               3,000 people per hour. It is estimated that approximately one million East Berlin
               citizens will cross to West Berlin for touristic purposes during the weekend. The
               police of the German Democratic Republic are providing the necessary convenience on
               the border and around the Wall, and their demeanor is moderate and pleasant. The
               Berlin subway has been opened.</p>
            <p>Over the last 24 hours, a mere 2,500 people crossing to the west indented for
               permanent migration.</p>
            <p>The citizens of East Germany are being welcomed in a festive atmosphere by their
               cognates in West Berlin. The traffic police are not fining them for parking illegally
               (negative), city-dwellers are distributing gifts, and the banks in the Federal German
               Republic are distributing an allowance of 100 DM to each arriving guest. In the bars
               of West Berlin, the East German Mark was also accepted last night.</p>
            <p>At the border gates along the Berlin Wall, there is a stampede. All the families
               seeking to cross over together with the intention to “visit” formed queues of tens of
               thousands of people at the train and subway stations by the border gates.</p>
            <p>The west and east side of the Berlin Wall, built 28 years ago over one night and
               responsible for the deaths of 71,000 innocents trying to escape from the east over
               the course of its existence, was demolished during the night of 10 November 1989
               under the supervision of engineers from the German Democratic Republic, opening the
               way for easy transits.</p>
            <p>In addition to these gates, four additional gates will be opened on Tuesday, 14
               November. It was indicated that the number of gates for crossing to West Berlin would
               be increased from 13 to 31. It has been suggested that the historic Brandenburg Gate
               will also be opened; thousands of Berlin’s youths are sitting on the Wall at this
               point and protesting.</p>
            <p>During the night of 10 November, Helmut Kohl<note xml:id="e1191">Helmut Kohl
                  (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>,
                  Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>, the Prime Minister of the
               Federal Republic of Germany and Willy Brandt<note xml:id="e1197">Willy Brandt
                  (1913–1992), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15409">dodis.ch/P15409</ref>,
                  Governing Mayor of West Berlin 3.10.1957–1.12.1966 and Chancellor of the FRG
                  22.10.1969–7.5.1974.</note>, who was the mayor of West Berlin when the Berlin Wall
               was built in the summer of 1961, arrived in Berlin and made speeches in front of the
               Wall.</p>
            <p>In his speech, the Prime Minister of the Federal Republic of Germany said “we are one
               nation, let’s struggle together.”</p>
            <p/>
            <p>2) During the meeting of the Central Committee of the said party, decisions
               concerning the realisation of free democratic elections, ensuring a secret ballot,
               providing for the freedom of press and submitting the secret police for trial were
               taken.</p>
            <p>Thanks to the maturity of the people of the German Democratic Republic, who are aware
               of having suffered hard times and the moderate and rationalist attitudes of their
               leaders, the incidents that are occurring are adding momentum to the shift towards
               democracy.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
