<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52912</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52912">dodis.ch/52912</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum<note xml:id="e2279">Memorandum: <idno>Bush Presidential
                        Library 91116-001</idno>. Signed by Brent Scowcroft, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57408">dodis.ch/P57408</ref>.</note> for the
                  President of the United States, George H. W. Bush<note xml:id="e2285">George
                     Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United States,
                     20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">The Soviets and the German Question</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Secret</add>
               <dateline>Washington, D.C., 29 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">This paper responds to your request for further analysis of the Soviet Union’s
               policy toward Germany in light of changes in the GDR and Eastern Europe.</p>
            <p>Soviet policy toward Germany is – like everything else – in a state of flux. The
               Soviets have lost control of their policy toward Eastern Europe and are largely
               reacting to events on a day to day basis. Gorbachev<note xml:id="e2301">Mikhail
                  Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>,
                  General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991,
                  Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and
                  President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> foresaw neither the
               pace nor the direction of change there and is increasingly powerless to do anything
               about it. The threat of the use of Soviet military power to reverse events
               increasingly lacks credibility and no one knows where Moscow’s tolerance will
               end.</p>
            <p>The Soviet reaction to events in the GDR is the clearest indication to date that
               Moscow has come to believe that peaceful economic and political change is the only
               alternative to a popular explosion. Earlier Gorbachev probably hoped that reform in
               these countries would take place within the boundaries of a single party system – a
               kind of mirror of Soviet perestroika. But he was mistaken.</p>
            <p>The GDR is not Poland or Hungary and the likelihood of a noncommunist East Germany
               has reopened the long dormant core issue of Soviet security – the German question. If
               the communists lose power in the GDR, the rationale for a divided Germany goes away.
               Yet the reunification of Germany would rip the heart out of the Soviet security
               system since East Germany and the 390,000 Soviet forces based on its territory
               constitute the fulcrum of the Warsaw Pact.</p>
            <p>Gorbachev’s communication to you on the issue of German reunification was unequivocal
               – he emphasized the “political realities of the postwar era, namely the existence of
               two German states.”</p>
            <p>The reunification of Germany conjures up deeply held memories and residual fears of
               repeated German invasions of Russia and the Soviet Union. The Soviet Union’s worst
               nightmare is a reunified Germany allied with NATO or, alternatively, nominally allied
               with the West and heavily militarized. The Warsaw Pact, having lost its East German
               anchor, would quickly disintegrate and the Soviet line of defense would begin at the
               Ukrainian border. A companion fear is that this reunified Germany would be able to
               dominate East-Central Europe economically, including a weak Soviet Union.</p>
            <p>No Soviet leader can allow German reunification on these terms: The gains of World
               War II, achieved at the cost of 20 million lives, would be gone.</p>
            <p>The best outcome for Moscow would be the continued existence of two viable German
               states. The GDR would reform politically and economically, maintain its identity and
               develop closer economic and political ties with FRG. The continued existence of two
               German states would allow the GDR to anchor the Warsaw Pact, keeping the Soviet
               security system nominally intact. At the same time, Moscow would enjoy not only the
               benefits of direct economic cooperation with the FRG but the contribution of an
               improved East German economy to COME‑ CON.</p>
            <p>The problem for Moscow now is to design a new policy to promote a favorable outcome
               when Soviet control over events in Eastern Europe is weak. The Soviets can still use
               force to stop unwelcomed events. Were there instability and violence in the GDR, the
               Soviets would most certainly act to protect the 390,000 Soviet troops stationed
               there. But short of that, it is hard to imagine a pretext for the use of Soviet force
               which would not discredit perestroika. Even a Soviet response to instability in the
               GDR carries risks for Gorbachev since the use of force, whatever its rationale, would
               destroy the chances for full Soviet economic and political rapprochement with the
               FRG.</p>
            <p>Moscow’s most likely diplomatic approach is to try and blunt the impact of change in
               the GDR by solidifying international support for two German states. Betting that
               there is little true enthusiasm for German reunification in the West – particularly
               in France and Britain – the Soviets would take every opportunity to stabilize the
               existing system of alliances while holding out the “common Eu‑ ropean home” as the
               promised end-point. While Soviet rhetoric might continue to call for the dissolution
               of blocs, we could expect a constant stream of new proposals for alliance to alliance
               talks and negotiations. Gorbachev might even use the CFE process, with its timetable
               for partial withdrawal of U.S. and Soviet forces, to give the Soviet presence a
               longer life in Europe than it might have if pressures for Soviet withdrawal grow from
               the populations of Eastern Europe. Finally, we could expect Soviet efforts to
               strengthen the CSCE’s role in inter-German affairs and European security in order to
               draw upon the angst of smaller European states about a stronger Germany. But like
               Gorbachev’s earlier tactics toward Eastern Europe, this policy is likely to fail
               too.</p>
            <p>There is currently no evidence of panic in Moscow on the German issue but if the
               Soviets begin to see their influence over European affairs deteriorating more
               rapidly, Gorbachev could revert to Soviet calls from the 1950s for a general treaty
               on collective security in Europe or a German peace treaty. The goal would be to
               regain control of the pace and form of German reunification. The Soviets might count
               on the British and French as natural allies in delaying German reunification or
               pushing it toward confederation.</p>
            <p>Gorbachev will come to Malta with these issues uppermost in his mind. There is, to
               date, no evidence that the Soviets have worked out a new policy toward Eastern Europe
               or Germany. As one Soviet commentator recently remarked, the Soviets have decided
               that their security interests are not served by the Brezhnev<note xml:id="e2327">Leonid Brezhnev (1906–1982), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15543">dodis.ch/P15543</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 14.10.1964–10.11.1982, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  16.6.1977–10.11.1982.</note> doctrine’s emphasis on preservation of the leading
               role of the Party in Eastern Europe. They have not, however, defined a new set of
               limits. Reformers in Eastern Europe seem to believe that membership in the Warsaw
               Pact is Moscow’s last line in the sand. But reform in the GDR and the attendant
               specter of German reunification call even that requirement into question. That is why
               the German question is – in a way that it has not been for many years – high on the
               Soviet security agenda and they are clearly uncertain about how best to protect their
               interests over the long-term.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>