<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52917</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52917">dodis.ch/52917</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum<note xml:id="e4080">Memorandum: Bush Presidential
                     Library CF-00182.20. Written by Brent Scowcroft, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57408">dodis.ch/P57408</ref>.</note> for the
                  President of the United States, George H. W. Bush<note xml:id="e4086">George
                     Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United States,
                     20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">Preparing for the Six Power German Peace Conference</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Sensitive</add>
               <dateline>Washington, D. C., 19 February 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">We are about to enter into the most crucial period for American diplomacy
               toward Europe since the formation of NATO in 1949. The Six Power discussions on the
               future of Germany could become the principal forum in which Europe’s security
               framework and the American role in it is determined. The U.S. must find a way to
               steer this new process on the future of Germany toward an outcome that sanctions full
               membership for a united Germany in NATO; provides for the continuation of a
               significant American military presence on German soil; and maintains nuclear
               deterrence as a pillar of NATO’s defense.</p>
            <p>Kohl’s<note xml:id="e4102">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> meeting with Gorbachev<note xml:id="e4108">Mikhail
                  Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>,
                  General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991,
                  Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and
                  President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> clearly showed that
               Moscow is resigned to German unity. The Six Power talks will, however, give the
               Soviet Union a chance to shape directly the terms of German unification. Moscow’s
               primary concern will be that there be no further shift – in perception or reality –
               in the East-West strategic balance. The Soviets are at last feeling the full negative
               impact of reform in Eastern Europe as government after government there demands the
               removal of Soviet forces. Germany is, in that sense, the final East-West battleground
               and has – with its still deep emotional import in the Soviet Union – become a crucial
               domestic issue for Gorbachev.</p>
            <p>When Yegor Ligachev<note xml:id="e4116">Yegor Ligachev (*1920), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57414">dodis.ch/P57414</ref>, Second Secretary of
                  Communist Party of the Soviet Union 10.3.1985–14.7.1990.</note> attacked
                  Shevardnadze<note xml:id="e4122">Eduard Shevardnadze (1928–2014), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54603">dodis.ch/P54603</ref>, Minister of Foreign
                  Affairs of the Soviet Union 2.7.1985–26.12.1990.</note> and Gorbachev for a
               foreign policy that has allowed the emergence of a united Germany “which looms
               militarily and economically powerful”, he sounded a chord that resonates in the
               Soviet political elite, even among those who otherwise support perestroika. The Six
               Power talks, designed to give Moscow a sense of participation in the resolution of
               Germany’s future and to shore up Gorbachev’s position, could instead force his hand
               on the details of Germany’s future – something that to now he has avoided. Vague
               ramblings, such as Gorbachev expressed to Kohl, about a united Germany within an
               all-European security system will in the Six Power context no longer do: Moscow must
               find some way to prevent the unification of Germany on wholly Western terms. This
               places us on a probable collision course with the Soviets on the question of the
               continued full membership of a united Germany in NATO.</p>
            <p>The Soviets likely know that a completely neutral Germany is a non-starter with the
               United States, Britain and the FRG. But for Moscow some weaker form of association
               for Germany with NATO – perhaps excluding the Bundeswehr from the integrated military
               command and capping the size of the German armed forces – would be almost as good.
               The Soviets know that without German forces, NATO’s integrated military command would
               be a shell. They might figure that it would not be long before pressures from the
               Germans and within the U.S. Congress would force the size of the American presence
               down and eventually out as well. The Soviets could also seek to negotiate in the Six
               Power forum their own continued presence in the GDR, or explicitly demand the removal
               of all U.S. forces from the FRG concurrent with the withdrawal of Soviet forces from
               East Germany.</p>
            <p>One potential consequence of a shift in Moscow’s attention to the Six Power talks is
               that the Soviet leadership may feel less pressure to conclude a CFE agreement. From
               the Soviet perspective, the Six Power forum can be used to attempt to emasculate the
               West German army, push U.S. ground forces out of Europe, disrupt the solidarity and
               viability of NATO itself, and provide political cover for their own withdrawal. These
               were among their principal objectives in CFE. While CFE retains its uses for Moscow,
               the Six Power mechanism would now allow the Soviets to pursue many of these key goals
               in a better forum than CFE, one that gives disproportionate weight to an East Germany
               dominated by the SPD, and exploits a West German government subject to extreme
               domestic political turbulence, while excluding lesser Allies who would join with us
               and London in arguing for stronger German links to NATO. The threat of Soviet
               reliance on the Six Power vehicle as a surrogate for CFE should be yet another spur
               for NATO to rapidly conclude a CFE agreement – before the Soviets shift their efforts
               to the higher-profile talks on Germany.</p>
            <p>In any case, the Soviets can be expected to make in the Six Power talks a
               comprehensive proposal on European security and Germany’s role in it. Along with the
               current GDR leadership, the Soviets will likely insist on severe constraints on a
               united Germany’s association with NATO. Moscow will also use its waning influence in
               the Warsaw Pact – and play on Czechoslovak, Hungarian, and especially Polish fears of
               the new Germany – to forge a common front behind its position. (On February 14,
               Polish Prime Minister Mazowiecki<note xml:id="e4134">Tadeusz Mazowiecki (1927–2013),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57378">dodis.ch/P57378</ref>, Prime Minister of
                  Poland 24.8.1989–12.1.1991.</note> demanded Warsaw be involved in negotiations on
               German reunification.)</p>
            <p>The degree to which this process threatens our interests depends on how carefully we
               structure the mandate of the Six Power discussions and whether we and our major
               Allies remain united on a common approach to these profound security questions. Our
               goal should be to keep the focus of the Six Power talks as limited as possible –
               dealing only with the legal issues related to the end of Four Power rights, the
               consequences of the absorption of the GDR into the FRG, and the issue of what becomes
               of forces on the territory of Germany’s eastern half. But the Soviets will press hard
               to widen the mandate so that all questions, including Germany’s membership in NATO
               will be on the table. Should they succeed, you will have a difficult challenge in
               holding NATO viably together.</p>
            <p>As the Six Power talks unfold, Kohl will come under pressure to find a formula for
               German security that is acceptable to Moscow. The Soviets will use the Six Power
               mechanism to try and influence German public opinion as well as others in Kohl’s
               coalition – particularly Genscher<note xml:id="e4144">Hans-Dietrich Genscher
                  (1927–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>,
                  Vice-Chancellor and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note> who will want for domestic political reasons to
               separate himself from Kohl on the future of European security. The Soviets could
               argue to an emotional German electorate that a weaker form of association with NATO
               is a small price to pay for German unity.</p>
            <p>The effect of this within the FRG will be to drive German opinion to the left and to
               strengthen the opposition parties’ influence in the domestic debate about
               unification. The SPD will respond to Moscow’s preferences (and those of the SPD’s
               sister party in the GDR) by moving still more to the left, toward a Germany
               completely out of NATO. This will drive Genscher further left (in search of the new
               middle ground), which in turn will pull Kohl in the same direction. Kohl would then
               face a situation in which Moscow, the GDR, the opposition SPD and Greens, and his own
               Foreign Minister<note xml:id="e4152">Hans-Dietrich Genscher.</note> are all calling
               for a loosening of Germany’s ties to NATO.</p>
            <p>There is no reason to doubt Kohl’s desire to keep his commitment to membership in
               NATO or his willingness to stand with us on the key issues of Western security. But
               Kohl will do what he must –even at the expense of NATO and the U.S. link – to become
               the Chancellor who united Germany. With history beckoning, all else will become for
               him secondary and negotiable.</p>
            <p>Our crucial task will be to find a way to avoid forcing Kohl to choose between unity
               and full NATO membership, and simultaneously to avert a crisis with Gorbachev over
               the future of Germany.</p>
            <p>Management of relations with the British and French will not be easy either. Mrs.
                  Thatcher<note xml:id="e4161">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of the
                  United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note> will undoubtedly support our position
               regarding Germany’s full membership in NATO but she may try to use the Six Power
               forum to slow down German unification. And, in any case, Mrs. Thatcher’s strongly
               pro-NATO position will fall on deaf ears in the Federal Republic.</p>
            <p>The French will have mixed objectives. Mitterrand<note xml:id="e4169">François
                  Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France 21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> may for
               the present support NATO membership for Germany because the French are concerned both
               to keep the Bundeswehr constrained within the integrated military command and to
               legitimize the continuation of nuclear deterrence. But France’s voice is weaker
               because of its own position outside NATO’s integrated military command.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">Moreover, in the longer term, Mitterrand has his own plans for a Confederation
               of Europe without the United States – including ultimately a new security mechanism –
               and for strengthening Franco-German bilateral military arrangements. This could give
               the French incentives to support a loose NATO structure which would, in turn, allow
               Paris a greater voice as the Atlantic link between the U.S. and NATO weakens. In any
               case, the Soviets are likely to think that they will find Paris sympathetic and we
               can expect an intensification of Franco-Soviet diplo‑ macy.</p>
            <p>Thus, if we are not careful, the dynamics of domestic politics in the FRG and
               diplomacy between the Allies and the Soviets could at best leave you and Kohl alone
               to defend effectively a Germany fully within NATO and with undiminished transatlantic
               security links.</p>
            <p>In order to avoid these pitfalls, we must have a coherent strategy for the Six Power
               talks that plays on our strengths – the GDR’s imminent collapse, Kohl’s desire to do
               the right thing, our leadership role in NATO, and Moscow’s lack of real leverage –
               and minimizes the potential dangers inherent in the Six Power framework. Above all,
               it is not in our interest to hurry this effort along, though Moscow will press for
               early talks. It would be a major mistake to proceed to any discussion with the
               Soviets before we have had an opportunity to forge a common end-game position with
               the British, French and West Germans. Your meeting with Kohl at Camp David will be a
               key in this process of consultation, giving you an opportunity to discuss the
               significant challenges that the Six Power process poses for Western unity and the
               future of the Alliance. Once we have hammered out a position among the key Allies,
               NATO must also have a chance to discuss and endorse the Western position.</p>
            <p>All the Allies need a part in this process. In Ottawa several Allied ministers,
               notably the Italians and Dutch, protested their exclusion from the Six Power forum
               that would affect their security interests as Germany’s neighbors. After the Italian
               Foreign Minister<note xml:id="e4185">Gianni De Michelis (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57415">dodis.ch/P57415</ref>, Italian Foreign
                  Minister 22.07.1989–28.06.1992.</note> made one such plea for involvement,
               Genscher turned to him and said, brutally, “You’re not in the game.” Genscher is
               wrong.</p>
            <p>NATO as an institution needs to forge a bottom line for the outcome of the Six Power
               discussions on the future of the European security system. One way to do this would
               be for the Alliance to commission a study by a group of “Wise Men” to consider the
               future goals and strategy of NATO in light of the political transformation of Europe.
               Then you could host a Summit meeting of NATO leaders, perhaps in Washington in July
               immediately after the G-7 meeting in Houston<note xml:id="e4193">Handwritten note:
                     <orig>interesting idea??</orig>
               </note>, to endorse this new concept for the Alliance – and Germany’s role in it.
               With this added reinforcement, Kohl would find it easier to resist Soviet and
               domestic pressures.</p>
            <p>In a larger sense, a delay in these Six Power discussions is favorable for us because
               the longer that German unity proceeds without direct Soviet involvement, the stronger
               will be the position of the West. As absorption of the GDR into the FRG becomes a
               fait accompli, Soviet leverage to reshape the new FRG will decline. It is worth
               noting that Kohl has managed so far, including during his visit last weekend to
               Moscow, to move German unity along while holding fast to his promise to keep the
               reunified Germany in NATO. Kohl does not himself seem to be pushing for early Six
               Power discussions – in your recent telephone conversation he appeared to foresee the
               first Six Power Ministerial meeting taking place sometime this summer<note xml:id="e4198">Handwritten note: <orig>Don’t recall this.</orig>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>Ideally, no meetings of any kind would take place within the Six Power framework
               until after the elections in the GDR on March 18<note xml:id="e4203">Handwritten
                  note: <orig>Correct according to JRB</orig>.</note>. We would simply say that the
               GDR’ s government is not legitimate and cannot speak for the German people residing
               there, and that we are preparing a united Western position for the talks. Indeed, we
               should try to delay any real discussion of security arrangements in this forum until
               the GDR is so weak that the Six, in fact, dissolves into Five as Germany unites.</p>
            <p>At the present time, the Modrow<note xml:id="e4208">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                  Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note> government is nothing but a
               second voice for Moscow. And after the East German elections, should the SPD win as
               expected, the new GDR government will argue for German neutrality. But with the
               passage of time – and if East Germany is simply absorbed into the FRG, the GDR
               government will cease to exist. Then Kohl would speak authoritatively on security
               arrangements for all of Germany which is, of course, our best bet.</p>
            <p>Finally, the Administration needs a breathing spell to formulate a position for what
               could be the most important set of discussions of European security in the postwar
               period. It is critical that Dick Cheney<note xml:id="e4216">Dick Cheney (*1941), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57391">dodis.ch/P57391</ref>, United States Secretary
                  of Defense 21.3.1989–28.6.1992.</note> and Colin Powell<note xml:id="e4222">Colin
                  L. Powell (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57416">dodis.ch/P57416</ref>,
                  Chairman of the United States Joint Chiefs of Staff 1.10.1989–30.9.1992.</note> be
               involved because Six (or Five) Power negotiations on Germany’s external security
               arrangements will cut to the heart of NATO and ultimately American defense
               strategy.</p>
            <p>As Manfred Woerner<note xml:id="e4230">Manfred Wörner (1934–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57417">dodis.ch/P57417</ref>, Secretary General of
                  NATO 1.7.1988–12.8.1994.</note> said to you at Camp David, we are entering the
               end-game of the Cold War and your own role will be decisive. The United States and
               the West must be impeccably prepared so that when the end-game is over, the North
               Atlantic Alliance and the U.S. position in Europe remain the vital instruments of
               peace and stability that we inherited from our predecessors.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>