<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52914</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52914">dodis.ch/52914</ref>
               <title type="main">Draft letter<note xml:id="e3701">Draft letter (copy): <idno>Bush
                        Presidential Library CF00182-020</idno>. Written by Robert D. Blackwill,
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57409">dodis.ch/P57409</ref>. Cf. the
                     memorandum from Robert D. Blackwill to Brent Scowcroft, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57408">dodis.ch/P57408</ref>, from 8 February
                     1990: <orig>The attached memorandum to the President proposes that he send a
                        letter to Kohl before Kohl sees Gorbachev this weekend. In drafting the
                        letter, I have tried to take into account the substance and tone of Horst
                        Teltschik’s concerns as expressed to us on Saturday in Munich. I understand
                        that Bob Kimmitt is also recommending to Baker in Moscow that the President
                        dispatch such a letter and you may wish to be in touch with Baker on the
                        subject. Recommendation: That you sign the attached memorandum to the
                        President. </orig>Cf. also the memorandum from Brent Scowcroft to George H.
                     W. Bush: <orig>Helmut Kohl’s visit to Moscow this weekend will be the most
                        important trip to the Soviet Union by a German Chancellor since Konrad
                        Adenauer’s visit there in September, 1955. Now, like then, the main subject
                        will be the future of Germany and its relationship with the West. Despite
                        great pressure from Khrushchev, Adenauer stuck to his position that West
                        Germany would remain anchored in NATO and other Western institutions. Kohl
                        says he intends to do the same in his talks on Saturday and Sunday with
                        Gorbachev. That may be a bitter pill for Gorbachev to swallow, especially in
                        the immediate aftermath of the greatest internal challenge yet to his
                        authority. Thus, Gorbachev may well push Kohl hard on Germany’s future
                        relationship with NATO, perhaps including the role of American troops and
                        nuclear weapons. With Kohl travelling to what may be the most portentous
                        foreign meeting of his life, I believe you should both give him all the
                        personal support you can and make clear to him our preferences concerning
                        the future of a united Germany. The attached message is designed to
                        accomplish both these objectives, while avoiding giving Kohl any impression
                        that we are anxious about his meeting with Gorbachev. Recommendation: That
                        you approve the attached letter from you to Helmut Kohl. </orig>For the
                     definitive version of the letter dated from the 9 February 1990 cf.
                        <idno>Dokumente zur Deutschlandpolitik. Deutsche Einheit: Sonderedition aus
                        denAkten des Bundeskanzleramtes 1989/90, ed. by Hanns Jürgen Küsters and
                        Daniel Hoffman, München 1998, doc. 170. </idno>Two additions were made to
                     the draft, cf. notes 7 and 8.</note> from the President of the United States,
                  George H. W. Bush<note xml:id="e3710">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the
                     United States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>, to the Chancellor of the FRG,
                  Helmut Kohl<note xml:id="e3716">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the
                     FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>
               </title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Secret</add>
               <dateline>
                  <add type="edition">[Washington,]</add> 9 February 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">Dear Helmut:</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">I know you will be hearing before your talks with Gorbachev<note xml:id="e3734">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>
               about the details of Jim Baker<note xml:id="e3740">James A. Baker (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P56605">dodis.ch/P56605</ref>, United States Secretary
                  of State 25.1.1989–23.8.1992.</note>’s discussions with the Soviets on the future
               of Germany. And we will have an opportunity to sit back and talk at length about some
               of these issues when you join me at Camp David later this month. But, as you know so
               well, the pace of events lately has been accelerating, and I wanted to share with
               you, directly, some of my thoughts about Germany and Europe’s future.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">As you predicted when we last talked on the phone,<note xml:id="e3750">Cf.
                  document 30, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52913">dodis.ch/52913</ref>.</note> the
               situation in the GDR seems to be deteriorating quickly, forcing the pace of
               unification. I know this was not your preference. Still, these new developments do
               not alter the complete readiness of the United States to see the fulfillment of the
               deepest national aspirations of the German people. If events are moving faster than
               we expected, it just means that our common goal for all these years of German unity
               will be realized even sooner than we had hoped.</p>
            <p>As unification comes ever closer to being a reality, people will be talking more and
               more about the role and responsibilities of the Four Powers. Let me tell you my
               attitude toward this question. After the end of the Second World War, going back to
               the time of the occupation, the main American goal for your nation was to aid in the
               creation of a new Germany wedded to democratic values, part of what I have called the
               commonwealth of free nations. Our legal rights in Germany, and in Berlin, were all
               aimed at protecting this objective and those values.</p>
            <p>As I see it, no one can doubt the strength and vitality of the Federal Republic’s
               democratic institutions. So, whatever the formal legal role of the Four Powers may be
               in recognizing the freely expressed will of the German people, I want you to
               understand that the United States will do nothing that would lead your countrymen to
               conclude that we will not respect their choice for their nation’s future. In no event
               will we allow the Soviet Union to use the Four Power mechanism as an instrument to
               try to force you to create the kind of Germany Moscow might want, at the pace Moscow
               might prefer.</p>
            <p>I would also like to confirm again to you my view of the role of a unified Germany in
               the Western Alliance. Naturally, this is again something for the German people, and
               its elected representatives, to decide. So I was deeply gratified by your<note xml:id="e3762">Addition in the definitive version: <orig>your rejection of
                     proposals for neutrality</orig>.</note> firm statement that a unified Germany
               would stay in the North Atlantic Alliance<note xml:id="e3765">Addition in the
                  definitive version: <orig>In this connection I endorse the idea put forward that a
                     component of a united Germany’s membership in the Atlantic alliance could be a
                     special military status for what is now the territory of the GDR. We believe
                     that such a commitment could be made compatible with the security of Germany,
                     as well as of its neighbours, in the context of substantial, perhaps ultimately
                     total, Soviet troop withdrawals from Central and Eastern Europe.</orig>
               </note>. In support of your position, l have said I expect that Germany would remain
               as a member of NATO, while noting that NATO will have a changing mission, with more
               emphasis on its original political role. I know we also agree that the presence of
               American forces on your territory and the continuation of nuclear deterrence are
               critical to assuring stability in this time of change and uncertainty.</p>
            <p>Even if, as we hope, the Soviet Union withdraws all its troops from Eastern Europe,
               it will still remain far and away the most powerful single military power in Europe.
               U.S. troops in Germany, and elsewhere on the continent, backed by a credible
               deterrent, must in my view continue to help preserve the security of the West as long
               as our Allies desire our military presence in Europe as part of the common defense.
               As our two countries journey together through this time of hope and promise, we can
               remain confident of our shared ability to defend the fruits of freedom. Nothing Mr.
               Gorbachev can say to Jim Baker or to you can change the fundamental fact of our deep
               and enduring partnership.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">Let me finally say how much I understand the challenges you have had to face
               over the last few months, and how much I admire the way you, as a leader, have met
               them. Barbara<note xml:id="e3774">Barbara Bush (1925–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57406">dodis.ch/P57406</ref>, United States First
                  Lady 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> and I look forward to seeing you and
                  Hannelore<note xml:id="e3780">Hannelore Kohl (1933–2001), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57407">dodis.ch/P57407</ref>, Wife of Helmut
                  Kohl.</note> in a few weeks.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>