<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52913</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52913">dodis.ch/52913</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum<note xml:id="e2961">Memorandum (copy). <idno>Bush
                        Presidential Library 91111-005</idno>. Participants: George H. W. Bush,
                     Helmut Kohl, Philip Zelikow, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57411">dodis.ch/P57411</ref> and Erika Konuk, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57412">dodis.ch/P57412</ref>. The conversation
                     took place in the Oval Office on 26 January 1990, 1989, 1.19–1.55PM.</note> by
                  the United States National Security Council</title>
               <title type="sub">Telephone Conversation with Chancellor Helmut Kohl<note xml:id="e2972">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>
                  of the Federal Republic of Germany</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Sensitive</add>
               <dateline>Washington, D.C., 26 January 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>
               <note xml:id="e2985">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>: Hello, Helmut.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: All the best. I hear all is going well. I am pleased
               the Panama matter<note xml:id="e2995">The United States invasion of Panama occurred
                  between 20 December 1989 and 31 January 1990.</note> went so well. The
                  scoundrel<note xml:id="e2998">Manuel Noriega (1934–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54758">dodis.ch/P54758</ref>, de facto ruler of
                  Panama 1983–1989.</note> is where he belongs.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: I appreciate your views very much. If you have a moment,
               I want to talk to you today about the way the political situation is developing in
               Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, and how these events relate to our position in
               the talks on conventional arms in Vienna.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I would be very pleased. Take all the time you
               need.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Our proposal on the table is for both the United States
               and the Soviet Union to have no more than 275,000 troops stationed in Europe when the
               CFE reductions are complete, in the mid-1990s. The Soviets have been putting out
               hints the figure is completely unrealistic, and I believe, given recent events, they
               are correct.</p>
            <p>The Czech and Hungarian governments are negotiating now for Soviet troop pullouts by
               the end of this year or next.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I do believe they will pull out.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Meanwhile, President Havel<note xml:id="e3026">Václav
                  Havel (1936–2011), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P52679">dodis.ch/P52679</ref>,
                  President of the CSSR 29.12.1989–20.7.1992.</note> has indicated that he plans to
               ask in February for greater U.S. and Soviet troop cuts than those now in our CFE
               proposal.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">We have heard from various people, including the Soviet negotiator in
                  Vienna<note xml:id="e3036">Oleg Grinevsky (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57632">dodis.ch/P57632</ref>, Chief Soviet Arms
                  Control Negociator for the CFE Treaty in Vienna.</note>, that Moscow is moving
               toward our position on capping U.S. and Soviet stationed forces, but we understand
               they’ll come at us with a number well below 275,000.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: That is quite possible too.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: We need to be out in front. It would otherwise seem to
               the East Europeans as if we were trying to keep Soviet troops where they are not
               wanted.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">In my view, nothing we do should in any way complicate or delay achieving CFE
               in 1990 and we should redouble our efforts to accomplish this.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I completely agree. It is of the utmost importance.
               I’ll wait until you finish; then I’ll make a proposal.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: We believe, after talking to our military experts about
               this, that a force of 195,000 U.S. troops in the Central zone in Europe in the
               mid-1990s is a significant and sustainable level to maintain forward defense and
               implement the NATO strategy of flexible response. 195 U.S. in the Central Zone
               (interpreter repeated only “195 U.S.”). I am persuaded that the best way to make
               these manpower reductions and to sustain the new force levels is within an arms
               control negotiating process, keeping the U.S. in Central Europe and NATO strong.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I believe that is something. Do you plan to introduce
               this into the negotiations now?</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: I want to send Larry Eagleburger<note xml:id="e3070">Lawrence S. Eagleburger (1930–2011), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57397">dodis.ch/P57397</ref>, United States Deputy Secretary of State
                  20.3.1989–8.12.1992.</note> and Bob Gates<note xml:id="e3076">Robert M. Gates
                  (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57404">dodis.ch/P57404</ref>, United
                  States Deputy National Security Advisor 20.3.1989–6.11.1991.</note> over to talk
               to you quietly, and to Rome, London, and Paris, to be sure how key allies feel on
               this.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: It is a very good idea, and we should soon set a date
               for these two gentlemen.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: I propose early next week, or in a few days. We should
               get out front with our objective so it will not seem as if we’re being dragged there
               by the Soviets or East Europeans.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: That is exactly the point.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: We have pressure from our Congress, as you do with your
               Bundestag. We should get out front so they won’t take the heart out of our defense
               programs.</p>
            <p>What do you think about this? How do you think the key allies will react?</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: First, it is absolutely correct and right to take the
               initiative, and state this openly. The most important improvement in this
               Administration, compared to previous ones, is that you are always taking the
               offensive – for the Federal Republic, the US, and Europe in general. This is also my
               view with Eastern Europe, and I’ll have more on that later.</p>
            <p>So, first, the principle of the idea is very good and useful. We’ll have to discuss
               the details. In Europe: Margaret<note xml:id="e3106">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of
                  the United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note> will be difficult for various
               reasons not necessarily involved with this issue. I believe Mitterrand,<note xml:id="e3112">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> if he is consulted sufficiently to defer to his
               psychological judgment, will probably follow my position. Let me phrase it
               differently: You know my old assessment – salute the flag of the FRG once, but the
               tricolor three times. That is very important, because there are French domestic
               policy issues. But I have a very friendly feeling about that. If you address
               Mitterrand directly, it will be OK.</p>
            <p>Italy and Spain will most likely take the same position as we do, as will the Benelux
               and other countries. The most important thing is that Europeans see George Bush as
               taking the initiative, not just getting it from the Soviets.</p>
            <p>When your people are over here next week, in my view next Thursday would be most
               convenient, I’ll talk to them for 3 or 4 hours and we can easily establish a
               German-US position.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Is there any way you could see them on Monday or Tuesday?
               I have a State of the Union message next week on January 31. If we could do it before
               then, we’d like to announce this idea on January 31. This will be an enormous
               nationally and internationally noted speech.</p>
            <p>I have one alternative proposal: If in principle this sounds agreeable, I could send
               it to you in writing and we could agree to work ·on the details after January 31, or
               have our people talk to your experts.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I am interested in talking to your people. I could
               accommodate them on Tuesday, at 1500 our time.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: They’ll be there.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: That will be 0900 in the morning your time. Our talks
               will be complete by noon your time, and that should be sufficient for you. So,
                  Teltschik<note xml:id="e3140">Horst M. Teltschik (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57413">dodis.ch/P57413</ref>, Head of Division in the
                  Foreign Ministry of the FRG.</note> will call on Monday to arrange the details.
               Then we could also talk on the phone on Tuesday evening, if that should be useful. I
               also agree that it is very important to announce this idea during your State of the
               Union address.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Thank you my friend. Eagleburger and Gates will call on
               your office at 1500 Bonn time on Tuesday, January 30. Following that, if necessary,
               we’ll talk on the telephone.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: OK. So, I would like to add a short remark on
               developments in Europe.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Yes, I am very interested.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I hear the problems are increasing in Moscow, but there
               is no alternative with the personnel – I mean the number one<note xml:id="e3162">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union
               15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>. But I think the situation is one where we should think
               on how we can help them, perhaps simply with food, food for some major cities.
               Apparently he has tremendous difficulties in moving supplies of food. This would not
               be as a gift, but with as few conditions for them as possible. I will call you again
               when I’ve progressed further in my considerations. Perhaps I will talk about this
               with Eagleburger.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: That would be very timely.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: On Poland, Hungary, and Czechoslovakia, they are
               developing. It needs much time; the problems there are serious. But I believe they
               can handle them.</p>
            <p>The situation is dramatic in the GDR. The reason is, <emph>that</emph> administration
               is having a very hard time in pushing things forward in a sensible manner. The reason
               is not that they don’t want to do it. They just <emph>cannot</emph> do it right.
               There is a considerable difference with Czechoslovakia. Havel has strong moral
               authority; Mazowiecki<note xml:id="e3178">Tadeusz Mazowiecki (1927–2013), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57378">dodis.ch/P57378</ref>, Prime Minister of
                  Poland 24.8.1989–12.1.1991.</note> too, and the government in Hungary has much
               less authority, but some authority plus the support of the opposition. The
                  Modrow<note xml:id="e3184">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                  Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note> administration has hardly any
               authority at all.</p>
            <p>I myself am pushing necessary reforms forward piece by piece. There is some success
               in the economic field, but things that should take one day take weeks. The result:
               confidence of the population in the administration is catastrophic. People are
               leaving in the thousands, and the rest are sitting on packed suitcases. Since January
               1,043,000 have come over. In the long term this is unsustainable. Those are the good
               people – doctors, engineers, specialists. They cannot be replaced.</p>
            <p>I will be meeting with Modrow a week from Sunday in Switzerland for an hour, and he
               will be here on February 13, and I’ll do all I can to stabilize matters.
               Destabilization would have tremendous consequences for everyone else. I try to see
               this from an overall perspective, in connection with all the things to be considered
               like NATO, the EC, and disarmament questions. My job is now to stop destabilization
               in Central Europe. That is the matter I work on day and night now.</p>
            <p>George, it’s my great wish that soon we might have a few hours to talk, just the two
               of us, with only a few people present. I’d like you to think about whether I could
               come over for a few hours. In November we talked about a possible visit to Camp
               David. Could we realize that in the next few weeks?</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: I am very enthusiastic about that. Come and spend the
               night, perhaps on a weekend. I will talk to Eagleburger and give you some dates. It
               is very important that we sit down in just that setting.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: I have some concrete ideas. I would have called you.
               I’m considering coming on a Saturday, returning on Sunday, in the evening.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Perfect. I’ll be flexible on that.</p>
            <p>Also, let’s keep this other idea in our confidence. If it leaks, the Soviets could
               get out in front.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: That was understood. Rest assured.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: It worked last time. Baker is here; he sends his
               best.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: My best to him too. Looking at my calendar, the best
               days would be February 24 and 25.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Those look good for me.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: Good. We’ll confirm in the next few days. Please accept
               my best wishes. Hannelore<note xml:id="e3230">Hannelore Kohl (1933–2001), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57407">dodis.ch/P57407</ref>, Wife of Helmut
                  Kohl.</note> says goodbye.</p>
            <p>(The President briefly conversed with Hannelore Kohl and assured her that she was
               welcome to come to Camp David and, if she came, Barbara<note xml:id="e3238">Barbara
                  Bush (1925–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57406">dodis.ch/P57406</ref>,
                  United States First Lady 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> would also be there.)</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>