<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52911</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52911">dodis.ch/52911</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum<note xml:id="e871">Memorandum (copy): <idno>Bush
                        Presidential Library 91111-004</idno>. Participants: George H. W. Bush,
                     Helmut Kohl and Robert M. Gates. The conversation took place in the Oval Office
                     on 10 November, 1989, 3.29–3.47PM.</note> by the United States’ Deputy National
                  Security Advisor, Robert M. Gates<note xml:id="e874">Robert M. Gates (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57404">dodis.ch/P57404</ref>, United States Deputy
                     National Security Advisor 20.3.1989–6.11.1991.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">Telephone Conversation with Helmut Kohl<note xml:id="e881">Helmut
                     Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>,
                     Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>, Chancellor – Federal
                  Republic of Germany</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Washington, D.C., 10 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Chancellor Kohl</emph>: The reforms in Poland are moving ahead. They have a new
               government with fine people. They are too idealistic with too little professionalism.
               Many of their professionals have spent the last couple of years in prison, not a
               place where one can learn how to govern. They are committed to democracy and market
               economics; we must help them. My request is as follows.</p>
            <p>I just told Margaret Thatcher<note xml:id="e896">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of the
                  United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note> and will tell Mitterrand<note xml:id="e902">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> tomorrow that we should give instructions to our
               representatives at the IMF that the negotiations with Poland should be completed
               speedily. These negotiations are not nice for the Poles but they are aware of the
               need and they seek clarity and clear cut conditions. We should help to get an
               agreement completed by the end of November. So I ask you, help us. Go and do this in
               the interest of the people. With respect to the rest of my trip to Poland, I will
               tell you next week after I return. Do you have any questions on Poland.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>
               <note xml:id="e912">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>: I have no questions; I’ll be interested to
               hear from you next week. I’m very interested in the GDR.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Kohl</emph>: I’ve just arrived from Berlin. It is like witnessing an enormous
               fair. It has the atmosphere of a festival. The frontiers are absolutely open. At
               certain points they are literally taking down the Wall and building new checkpoints.
               At Checkpoint Charlie, thousands of people are crossing both ways. There are many
               young people who are coming over for a visit and enjoying our open way of life. I
               expect they will go home tonight. I would cautiously tell you that it appears that
               the opening has not led to a dramatic increase in the movement of refugees. It may be
               with the frontier open, people will simply go back and forth, looking, visiting and
               going home. This will work only if the GDR really reforms and I have my doubts.
                  Krenz<note xml:id="e922">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54794">dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and
                  Chairman of the GDR State Council 18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note> will carry out
               reforms but I think there are limits. One of those limits seems to be one party rule,
               and this simply will not work. Certainly, in particular, it will not work without
               pluralism, free trade unions and so forth. I could imagine that this will continue
               for a few weeks – that for a few weeks people will wait to see if the reforms come
               and if there is no light at the end of the tunnel they will run away from the GDR in
               great numbers. This would be a catastrophe for economic development; good people are
               leaving. The figures this year – 230,000 have come. Their average age has been
               between 25 and 30. This is a catastrophe for the GDR. They are doctors, lawyers,
               specialists who cannot be replaced. They can earn more here. This is a dramatic
               thing; an historic hour. Let me repeat. There were two major manifestations
               (political gatherings) in Berlin. One was in front of the Berlin Town Hall where
               there were a lot of left wing rowdies, these are the pictures that will be shown on
               TV around the world. The second was at the Kurfurstendamm organized by our political
               friends. It was at about· 6:30PM and the estimates are that there were
               120,000–200,000 people. The overall spirit was optimistic and friendly. When I
               thanked the Americans for their role in all of this, there was much applause. Without
               the US this day would not have been possible. Tell your people that. The GDR people
               in the protests and demonstrations have been sincere, not aggressive. This makes it
               very impressive. There have been no conflicts, even though in East Berlin, Leipzig
               and Dresden hundreds of thousands have been in the streets. I hope they will continue
               to be calm and peaceful. This is my short report.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: First, let me say how great is our respect for the way
               the FRG has handled all of this. Second, my meeting with Gorbachev<note xml:id="e932">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>
               in early December has become even more important. I want to be sure you and I spend
               enough time on the telephone so I have the full benefit of your thinking before I
               meet with him.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Kohl</emph>: We should do that. It’s important.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: I will call Brady<note xml:id="e946">Nicholas F. Brady
                  (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57405">dodis.ch/P57405</ref>, United
                  States Secretary of the Treasury 15.9.1988–17.1.1993.</note> today or tomorrow to
               tell him of your suggestion for a rapid completion of the IMF agreement on Poland.
               Fourth, I want to see our people continue to avoid especially hot rhetoric that might
               by mistake cause a problem.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Kohl</emph>: That’s very good of you.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The Presiden</emph>t: Fifth, I want to tell the US press of our talk, that you
               gave me a thorough briefing, that you did publicly acknowledge the role of the US,
               and that you and I agreed to talk later next week.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Kohl</emph>: Excellent.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: Take care, good luck. I’m proud of the way you’re
               handling an extraordinarily difficult problem.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Kohl</emph>: Thank you. Give my best to Barbara<note xml:id="e972">Barbara Bush
                  (1925–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57406">dodis.ch/P57406</ref>, United
                  States First Lady 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>The President</emph>: I’m in Dallas. Same to Hanalore<note xml:id="e982">Hannelore Kohl (1933–2001), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57407">dodis.ch/P57407</ref>, Wife of Helmut Kohl.</note>.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">
               <emph>Kohl</emph>: Thank you and kind regards. Tell her to save her money that I
               intend to send sausages for Christmas.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>