<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title> Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz, Band 27 </title>
				<author> Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz </author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher> Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz </publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="doc">
				<head>
					<ref target="http://dodis.ch/52923"> dodis.ch/52923 </ref>
					<title type="main"> Telegram <note xml:id="e736"> Telegram No. 381 (incoming):
								<idno type="UK-NA"> UK National Archives FCO 33/10154 </idno> . Ref.
							My Telegram No. 377. Repeated for Information Immediate to the British
							Embassies in Bonn, Washington, Moscow and Paris, the British Military
							Government in Berlin, the UK Delegation to NATO; Information Routine to
							Eastern European posts; Information Saving to EC posts, the UK
							Representation in Brussels and the British Embassy in Peking. </note>
						from the British Ambassador in East Berlin, Nigel Broomfield <note xml:id="e491"> Nigel Broomfield (1937–2018), <ref target="http://dodis.ch/P57477"> dodis.ch/P57477 </ref> , British
							Ambassador in East Berlin, 1988–1990. </note> , to the British Secretary
						of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, Douglas Hurd <note xml:id="e504"> Douglas Hurd (*1930), <ref target="http://dodis.ch/P57401"> dodis.ch/P57401 </ref> , British
							Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs,
							26.10.1989–1995. </note>
					</title>
					<title type="sub"> Future developments in the GDR </title>
				</head>
				<opener>
					<add> Confidential, Immediate </add>
					<dateline>
						<placeName> East Berlin, </placeName>
						<date when="1989-11-13"> 13 November 1989, 9.10 am </date>
					</dateline>
				</opener>
				<p>
					<title type="doc"> Summary </title> 1. A new chapter in Germany’s post war
					history. <title type="doc"> Detail </title> 2. It is not for me to comment on
					the effect on West Berlin and the FRG of the influx of some three million East
					Germans over the past four days. But viewed from East Berlin the last four days
					mark a decisive change in the political life of the GDR. </p>
				<p> 3. Even though 4.2 million visas were issued since 9 November, only 10,144 were
					for emigration according to GDR figures. This is an encouraging ratio for the
					leadership, and indeed there are reports of people returning. But the situation
					remains fluid, the exodus could begin again at any time if the leadership
					started to resile on the numerous promises they have given in the last few days
					about new policies. The Politburo will have to learn to live under this sword of
					Damocles. </p>
				<p> 4. The breaching of the Berlin Wall, the opening of a new crossing at Potsdamer
					Platz, the scene of the 1953 uprising and the heart of old Berlin, by the mayors
					of East and West Berlin <note xml:id="e603"> Walter Momper (*1945), <ref target="http://dodis.ch/P57440"> dodis.ch/P57440 </ref> , Governing
						Mayor of West Berlin 16.2.1989–24.1.1991 and Erhard Krack (1931–2000),
						dodis.ch/P55386, Mayor of East Berlin 11.2.1974–15.2.1990. </note> , are
					deeply symbolic acts. The millions who crossed into West Berlin and the FRG
					since 9 November are fundamental political facts for the future of this country. </p>
				<p> 5. The tears and euphoria will die down and no doubt aggravations and
					resentments will surface in some areas but first-hand knowledge of the other
					German state and of their friendly reception there over this weekend has spread
					very widely among the population here and not just as before, among the
					privileged few with relatives in the West. This cannot be taken away again
					without risking an overwhelming political reaction. </p>
				<p> 6. Krenz <note xml:id="e616"> Krenz (*1937), <ref target="http://dodis.ch/P54794"> dodis.ch/P54794 </ref> , General
						Secretary of the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and Chairman of the GDR State
						Council 18.10.1989–6.12.1989. </note> may claim as he did on GDR television
					on 11 November after talking to Kohl2 and agreeing to meet “soon”, that what had
					happened were sovereign decisions by the GDR and that for him reunification was
					not on the agenda. But power has passed in substantial measure to the people and
					it is they who from now on will increasingly decide the future of this country.
					How they will decide is not yet clear. </p>
				<p> 7. Unless a cataclysm occurs in the Soviet Union and sets back with it the
					reforms in Poland and Hungary I cannot see how a rapid process of growing
					together of the two German states can be avoided. Krenz may be replaced by
					Modrow <note xml:id="e634"> Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="http://dodis.ch/P54796"> dodis.ch/P54796 </ref> , Chairman of
						the GDR Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990. </note> , who may succeed
					for a time in making the party popular again. There is wide support among the
					bloc parties as well as the protest groups for the principles of socialism
					variously defined. But the present system of planning the economy based on
					widespread public ownership cannot satisfy the peoples, demands sharpened as
					they will be by increasing familiarity with West Berlin and the FRG. </p>
				<p> 8. Whether in a dramatic move to stave off economic collapse in the next few
					months or in a more gradual process, the strength of the FRG economy acting on
					the structural and systemic weaknesses of the GDR is bound to have a profound
					effect. (I think it impossible that the structural alterations to the GDR’s
					economy can take place by the time Kohl and Krenz have their first meeting in
					November/December. And without these alterations Kohl has said, quite sensibly
					in my view, investment from the FRG will not be attracted to the GDR. The threat
					of imminent economic collapse looks to be a more likely trigger for West German
					assistance than slow structural change.) </p>
				<p> 9. I do not think it fanciful to see something of the same process happening on
					the political front with existing links between parties in East and West
					Germany. The CDU (West) has just begun to have contact with the CDU (East). The
					same is true for the SPD (West) and the SPD (East, still unofficial) whose
					membership of the socialist international the former will support. The FDP
					(West) has long had links with the LDPD (East, “liberal”). The SED will derive
					little benefit from its close contacts with DKP (West) and the SEW (West
					Berlin). </p>
				<p> 10. There will no doubt be many twists and surprises in the way events actually
					work out between the two German states. But from the point of view of our policy
					towards the GDR we should take note of underlying realities which the events of
					the last few days and weeks have exposed so clearly. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>