<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52939</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52939">dodis.ch/52939</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e3866">Telegram No. USS0039 (incoming):
                        <idno>Global Affairs Canada file 25-3-3-5-Germany / Confidential</idno>.
                     Written by Jeremy Kinsmann, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57447">dodis.ch/P57447</ref>. Addressed to Brussels, Copenhagen, Paris, Bonn,
                     Athens, Rome, Luxembourg, Hague, Ankara, Oslo, Lisbon, Madrid, London,
                     Washington, Moscow, Warsaw, Prague, Budapest, Bucharest, Belgrade, Geneva,
                     Brussels-EEC, Brussels-NATO, Delegation to the Organization for Securtiy and
                     Cooperation in Europe, Dublin, Vienna, Helsinki, Stockholm, Bern, Tokyo, UN-New
                     York, OECD, Office of the Prime Minister, Privy Council Office, National
                     Defence Headquarters.</note> from the Canadian Under-Secretary of State for
                  External Affairs, de Montigny Marchand<note xml:id="e3872">Marchand de Montigny
                     (*1936), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57449">dodis.ch/P57449</ref>, Canadian
                     Under-Secretary of State for External Affairs 1990–1991.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">Ottawa Conference: East-West Relations</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Secret</add>
               <dateline>Ottawa, 15 February 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. We had all predicted that ministerial portion of the Open Skies conference
               would become significant because of its unique positioning of key players at a key
               time in history. Three-line full page headline of NY Times 14 Feb more than
               vindicates prediction: “Accord in Ottawa: West and Soviets Agree with Two Germanys on
               Rapid Schedule for Unification Talks: Gorbachev Accepts Bush’s Troop Ceiling.”</p>
            <p>2. Ottawa meeting has obviously been unique venue for countless high level
               behind-the-scenes negotiations and conversations, many involving SSEA<note xml:id="e3888">Charles Joseph Clark (*1939), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P55844">dodis.ch/P55844</ref>, Canadian Secretary of State for External Affairs
                  17.9.1984-20.4.1991.</note> and PM<note xml:id="e3894">Brian Mulroney (*1939),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57450">dodis.ch/P57450</ref>, Canadian Prime
                  Minister 17.9.1984–25.6.1993.</note>. Baker<note xml:id="e3900">James Baker
                  (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P56605">dodis.ch/P56605</ref>, US Secretary
                  of State 25.1.1989–23.8.1992.</note> and Shevardnadze<note xml:id="e3906">Eduard
                  Shevardnadze (1928–2014), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54603">dodis.ch/P54603</ref>, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union
                  2.7.1985–26.12.1990.</note>, for example, had five separate negotiating sessions
               on Tuesday. SSEA and Shevardnadze had six hours of discussion during bilaterals on
               Wednesday alone. This telegram attempts to provide some of the more central
               assessments that were made privately to Canadians in last several days, or to others
               as reported to us, to inform your own discussion and analysis of events, bearing in
               mind that Canada is not to be a mere observer of what is taking place but a
               participant in the process, with views to offer, and interests to advance.</p>
            <p>3. This telegram will not be about Open Skies. That part of conference is proceeding
               very well. Idea was applauded by ministers as most important confidence-building
               measure yet and though differences of approaches remain, there is every likelihood
               they will be settled in time for a treaty to be presented to ministers in Budapest in
               May. This will be a very considerable accomplishment. As PM put it privately, a
               treaty is a tangible proof of achievement and progress, and we Canadians should press
               and press to ensure its importance is appreciated so that this achievement is
               realized.</p>
            <p>4. It would be obvious to say that it was issue of German unification which dominated
               Ottawa meeting. Certainly this was all that Genscher<note xml:id="e3916">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the
                  FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note> had on his mind and the driving home in corridor
               negotiations of the “2 plus 4” formula for its discussion with other countries was
               very major accomplishment (though tarnished by vivid and bitter contestation in NATO
               caucus of the unfortunate wording of its mandate.)</p>
            <p>5. But to USA and USSR, the hurtling of events in Germany toward de facto unification
               in only several weeks’ time was part, albeit major part, of bigger tableau of
               unpredictability and instability which is even more major preoccupation. As
               Shevardnadze put it to SSEA, “situation is so complex, so urgent, and so dangerous”.
               It is search for predictability and stability while accommodating forces of
               democratization and reform which characterises the two great powers policy
               objectives. It is clear that they will work together in this search. Our talks with
               Soviets and Americans alike reveal unprecedented level of cooperation, and from USA
               side strenuous effort to support Gorbachev<note xml:id="e3924">Mikhail Gorbachev
                  (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General
                  Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman
                  of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the
                  Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> and (Shevardnadze) politically.</p>
            <p>6. Baker and his colleagues stressed in private discussion that while Gorbachev is
               secure in his control, the USSR is imploding. Government can probably cope, but not
               if it is subject as well to external pressures. Shevardnadze had stressed to both
               Baker and Genscher the shock of having been criticized by the central committee for
               recent USSR “losses”. “What are you doing with our security”, conservatives are
               saying. Unification of Germany is by far the most explosive development in view of
               these critics.</p>
            <p>7. USA is therefore determined to watch its language in describing USA-USSR
               relations. Soviets made a fundamental shift in Ottawa bilateral talks in accepting
                  Bush<note xml:id="e3934">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> force reduction formula in that it is
               asymmetric both in cuts and in end results. But they made it clear that this was not
               a concession. What USA side understood from that is that it would provide
               unacceptably volatile fuel to Moscow conservative critics if it were. USA purpose is
               to establish “dignity” in bilateral relations for that reason, as two sides build
               toward June bilateral summit with an intensity in political level discussion that is
               without precedent (2 more major Baker-Shevardnadze negotiations between now and
               June).</p>
            <p>8. In many respects, sensitivity to USSR interests is the driving reason behind 2
               plus 4 formula for handling the unification of Germany. Everyone accepts that
               unification is up to the Germans; it will take place and almost immediately after the
               18 Mar GDR elections. The question is its political packaging as well as the need to
               find a formula for the controversial external aspects.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">9. As Genscher put it to NATO caucus, Shevardnadze was “certainly not shy” in
               describing Soviet public sentiment on the issue. To SSEA, Soviet FM<note xml:id="e3946">Eduard Shevardnadze.</note> said “leaders of FRG seem to understand
               they have gone too far.” Shevardnadze had impression that FRG partisan political
               process was in some respects forcing events as three FRG parties view to outdo each
               other with escalation of promises. Genscher in his private conversations places
               stress on haemorrhaging conditions in GDR. Exodus is now at 3,200 a day; most basic
               public services are jeopardized. Genscher was man driven at Ottawa conference by
               historical feat of achieving unification. His explanation for urgency rang true, as
               did his satisfaction as a German statesman, but his instincts as party politician
               were not wholly obscured, and as Woerner<note xml:id="e3949">Manfred Wörner
                  (1934–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57417">dodis.ch/P57417</ref>,
                  Secretary General of NATO 1.7.1988–12.8.1994.</note> candidly acknowledged at
               private dinner hosted by Associate Defence Minister Collins<note xml:id="e3955">Mary
                  Collins (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57452">dodis.ch/P57452</ref>,
                  Canadian Associate Minister of National Defence 1989–1995.</note>, both CDU and
               FDP have to work hard to compensate for obvious advantage held among GDR voters by
               SDP.</p>
            <p>10. Point of these internal FRG political points is that we are told Gorbachev and
               Shevardnadze are themselves going out of their way to understand them. They are
               reasoning like politicians now because like all the others at Ottawa conference from
               Eastern Europe (except Fischer<note xml:id="e3963">Oskar Fischer (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P51055">dodis.ch/P51055</ref>, Foreign Minister of the
                  GDR 3.3.1975–12.4.1990.</note>) they now have to. But they expect their own
               domestic political interests to be respected by political process. Shevardnadze put
               it to Baker on issue of unification, “we have to be participants, not victims.”</p>
            <p>11. This was central impulse for creating 2 plus 4 and its importance for USSR
               explains why NATO allies were prepared to tolerate complete absence of consultations.
               Both Hurd<note xml:id="e3971">Douglas Hurd (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57401">dodis.ch/P57401</ref>, British Secretary of
                  State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs 26.10.1989–5.7.1995.</note> and Baker
               seemed prepared to recognize that a gaffe had been committed over mandate for the
               foreign ministers of five (GDR becomes academic) to discuss “the issues of security
               of the neighbouring states.” They offered in NATO caucus at SSEA urging to ensure
               close ongoing consultation in NATO but Genscher was indignant and uptight about the
               issue. This may only mean that 2 plus 4 solution was still very fragile. Our
               impression is that USA-USSR formula that “internal aspects of unification are
               entirely up to Germans while external aspects need to be discussed with others” is
               going to be harder to agree upon with both USSR and German partners in practice than
               in theory. Dutch FM<note xml:id="e3977">Hans van den Broek (*1936), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57462">dodis.ch/P57462</ref>, Dutch Minister of
                  Foreign Affairs 4.11.1982–3.1.1993.</note> (supported most strenuously by
                  Italian<note xml:id="e3983">Gianni De Michelis (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57415">dodis.ch/P57415</ref>, Italian Foreign
                  Minister 22.07.1989–28.06.1992.</note>, Belgian<note xml:id="e3989">Mark Eyskens
                  (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57464">dodis.ch/P57464</ref>, Belgian
                  Minister of Foreign Affairs 19.6.1989–7.3.1992.</note>, Norwegian<note xml:id="e3995">Kjell Magne Bondevik (*1947), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57465">dodis.ch/P57465</ref>, Norwegian Minister of Foreign Affairs
                  16.10.1989–3.11.1990.</note>) asked, “if it is a question of Polish borders only,
               why not say so?” There was no satisfactory answer, and since Genscher has made it
               very clear FRG will confirm current eastward borders expeditiously, there is
               potential for 2 plus 4 to be used for much more. Genscher needs it to finalize
               unification itself in rapidly changing landscape.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">12. Question is whether it will also be used to pre-negotiate relationship of
               unified Germany to NATO as this relates to all of the other central security
               questions. This unanswered (probably unanswerable) question had non-participating
               NATO foreign ministers worried but fact remains that tacit purpose of 2 plus 4 is to
               give USSR entree to process with all of the preoccupations they bring to bear and way
               this plays out is hard to predict. French would argue (point made to us by Political
               Director Dufourq<note xml:id="e4005">Bertrand Dufourq (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57455">dodis.ch/P57455</ref>, Political director in
                  the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs 1.10.1988–27.10.1998.</note>) that there
               was nothing to negotiate with USSR on issue, since they had no leverage. However, USA
               preoccupation with USSR leadership comfort levels would suggest using 2 plus 4 as
               forum for arguing out at least respective points of view on stationed foreign forces
               and possibly more.</p>
            <p>13. President Bush said in his press conference 11 February, “I suspect, though I
               cannot prove it, that some of the WTO countries want us in Europe: not as a threat,
               but as a stabilizing factor”. From what was said privately and publicly here in last
               few days, President Bush’s suspicion is probably right. Shevardnadze said to SSEA
               that he would see USA and Canada and USSR troops all out of “Europe” by 1995 and by
               year 2000 all forces in Europe on a nationally-stationed basis and with a defensive
               posture. But he also said to SSEA “we are not afraid of Canada but of Bundeswehr”. He
               made it clear it was not with his friends Genscher and Kohl<note xml:id="e4013">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> at
               helm that Russians had this fear but with view to decade or so hence. All of this to
               suggest that process of German unification has deepest political and security
               preoccupations for USSR. Emotional memories of WW II are political reality. They will
               seek satisfaction on fundamental issues, probably in two plus four grouping.</p>
            <p>14. This may well have implications for NATO in terms of established institutional
               prerogatives and process and it will have to be worked out as a NATO matter.</p>
            <p>15. NATO fretting on this point is ironic counterpoint to most frequently made Ottawa
               conference joke. As WTO delegations inadvertently and repeatedly wandered into NATO
               caucus meetings to retrieve briefcases, or Shoppers Drug Mart purchases, left at
               previous session, they ritualistically intoned when they realised where they were,
               “We are joining, but not quite yet.”</p>
            <p>16. In public debate, WTO members at conference were relatively restrained. Plenary
               debate was remarkable in that almost all of the speeches from WTO and NATO used same
               speech-writers lexicon of political phrases about rights, democracy, openness,
               stability, security, etc. and for once words used meant the same to all the users.
               Privately, WTO delegations (except for hapless East Germans) acknowledged WTO was
               finished. Publicly they continued to refer to value of alliances for accelerating
               force reductions and arms control. To the extent that they can indulge in long-term
               thinking, they see arms reduction activity shifting toward an alliance-free forum, a
               new CSCE, but as Dienstbier<note xml:id="e4025">Jiří Dienstbier (1937–2011), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57467">dodis.ch/P57467</ref>, Foreign Minister of the
                  CSSR 10.12.1989–2.7.1992.</note> put it privately, he and others can hardly
               strategize past the end of each week. Shevardnadze spoke eloquently to SSEA about the
               serious disconnect in timing in Eastern Europe and the USSR between political reform
               and economic reform. The economic reform task is much more enormous and difficult
               than Westerners think, he said. Laws have to be re-written, debated, approved on such
               fundamental issues as the nature of property. Even more significant is the
               established command economy network both between the USSR and the COMECON countries
               and within the USSR itself, which is a lot easier to wish away than to actually
               replace. The real problem here is frustrated expectations, a basic ingredient of the
               dangerous instability which so troubled the USSR internally and externally. These
               realizations no doubt tempered behaviour of the other foreign ministers from Eastern
               Europe, who (except for Poles and Czech undercutting of Karpov<note xml:id="e4031">Victor Karpov (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57456">dodis.ch/P57456</ref>, Deputy Foreign Minister of the Soviet Union
                  1990–1991.</note> during negotiations on Open Skies communique) did not take issue
               with the USSR (except perhaps for Czechoslovakia), bearing in mind perhaps that it
               was Gorbachev and perestroika which had helped put them here.</p>
            <p>17. However, all accepted that Ottawa conference represented a new departure in
               attitude and direction. The question is where will it lead.</p>
            <p>18. Given that stability and predictability are the goals, and that existing
               institutional structures are in flux or in case of WTO virtually defunct, tendency is
               to think ahead to an englobing security framework which seems to be a more muscular
               and more effective CSCE.</p>
            <p>19. All delegations here were in favour of a CSCE Summit before end of 1990 –
               virtually all anticipated signature of CFE Agreement to be a prominent achievement of
               summit. But there was a range of views as to substantive preparation of summit,
               substance to be expected from summit, and thus from renewed CSCE itself.</p>
            <p>20. As you know, USSR position has been in favour of “institutionalizing” the CSCE
               process, which seems to mean giving it ongoing secretariat and member state presence
               and functions to propel negotiation, consultation, and programs in political
               security, social, economic, and environmental areas. Shevardnadze told SSEA they saw
               the summit identifying the CSCE as the successor agency for the CFE I process and as
               the locale as well for consolidating the final post-WW II settlement process. The
               summit should set a mandate to enable the CSCE to encourage and eventually to codify
               the conversion of states to defensive military postures, as well as to engage in the
               other critical economic, social and environmental adjustment activities.</p>
            <p>21. Deeper Soviet interests were also acknowledged. Shevardnadze spoke with reference
               to German unification of the importance for stability of USA and Canadian presence in
               the CSCE. He wishes to “accelerate the process of englobing structures in the CSCE.”
               USA officials told us that in their view USSR is also looking to stable pluralistic
               framework of CSCE as sort of counter to Federal instability within USSR itself. USA
               considers this a serious concern and will probably upgrade their own creative
               attention to CSCE potential in consequence. USA officials privately accept
               inevitability of an institutionalized CSCE.</p>
            <p>22. Genscher also spoke of CSCE as locale for next phase of conventional weapons
               negotiations and as “permanent stage” for disarmament process. On unification, FRG is
               going to report to CSCE Summit on details, but does not intend any discussion or
               negotiation there, which, of course, remains to be seen re external aspects.</p>
            <p>23. French too see CSCE as useful to englobe changing security situation but our
               conversations with Dufourq do not reveal much in way of French thinking regarding any
               substantive ongoing role for CSCE itself apart from preparing 1992 FU<note xml:id="e4051">Follow-up meeting of the CSCE.</note> meeting. Other delegations
               including Canada do not wish to disrupt or replace 1992 meeting but believe events
               require concrete strengthening of CSCE before then. French views are probably
               unexpressed pending EC discussion and settlement of Paris-Vienna venue contest (Paris
               will win; <add type="edition">[other]</add> delegations cannot swallow even proximity
               of Waldheim<note xml:id="e4057">Kurt Waldheim (1918–2007), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15484">dodis.ch/P15484</ref>, President of Austria
                  8.7.1986–8.7.1992.</note> to summit of this character.) Surprisingly, Hurd foresaw
               quite considerable security role for new CSCE including notion of conflict resolution
               mechanism which interested SSEA.</p>
            <p>24. These divergent views on CSCE need urgent reconciliation, at least to point where
               a preparatory process for summit can be identified. There were various proposals for
               an officials prepcom, use of Vienna CSBM forum, ministerial meetings either on the
               margin of Budapest Open Skies finale, or Copenhagen Human Dimension conference or a
               special prepcom at separate ministerial meeting. SSEA in chair at both impromptu NATO
               caucus and closed session of 23 <add type="edition">[on]</add> 13 February was not
               able to draw out a very open discussion of positions we know existed.</p>
            <p>25. Tendency now will be for serious official discussion to proceed on all these
               issues in various venues: bilateral, 2 plus 4, and EC 12, and only then in NATO,
               though summit seven sherpa meetings may provide opportunity.</p>
            <p>26. For these reasons, steps by posts to dialogue at most senior levels of host
               governments will be important. There is considerable credit available from Open Skies
               host functions and SSEA leadership to draw upon. You will have read PM and SSEA
               statements to Open Skies plenary. As general supplementary guidance, we would add
               that a reinforced and more effective CSCE process is very much a Canadian objective.
               SSEA found in discussion with Shevardnadze there is much Canada and USSR shared on
               this issue and on proposals for an active preparatory process. We shall provide more
               specific guidance on CSCE and on other issues shortly.</p>
            <p>27. This telegram is to try in haste to return some very tentative analysis to those
               of you who have so thoughtfully contributed in recent months to our understanding of
               these truly momentous issues, and specifically to preparation of this very important
               meeting of 23 ministers which has, we think it fair to say, worked out very well.
               Accurate and substantial political understanding of the various needs and positions
               at play in the unfolding of these events will now be needed more than ever if
               Canadian opportunities and interests are to be aptly assessed and advanced. We count
               on your contribution and we shall do our best to ensure you are well positioned in
               regard to thinking here. More detailed and factual reports on specific meetings and
               sessions are, of course, going out to those concerned in usual way.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>