<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52932</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52932">dodis.ch/52932</ref>
               <title type="main">Memo<note xml:id="e6325">Memo (translated from German):
                        <idno>Austrian State Archive ÖStA, AdR, BMAA, II-Pol 1990, GZ.
                        22.17.01/176-II.3/90</idno>. Written and signed by Ernst Sucharipa, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57511">dodis.ch/P57511</ref>; also published in
                     Wilson Center, doc. 165726. Distributed to the Federal Minister, the General
                     Secretary, the section heads, all departments of the Political Section, and the
                     Austrian diplomatic representations in member states of the CSCE. The
                     information was also part of the preparatory file for Franz Vranitzky on the
                     occasion of the visit by Lothar de Maizière to Austria scheduled for 25 and 26
                     July 1990. See <idno>ÖStA Arbeitsbesuch von MP Lothar de Maizière 25./26. Juli
                        1990, Kreisky Archives, Depositum Franz Vranitzky, AP, box BM Choonhavan
                        Chatichai (Thailand), MP Calfa CSFR 1990 PM Silva (Portugal), MP Singh
                        (Indien), Pres. Dubcek (CSFR), PM Kang Young-Hoon (Korea), PM Bhutto
                        (Pakistan), Pres. George Vassiliou (Zypern), MP Maiziere Lothar (DDR)
                        25.7.90)</idno>.</note> by the Austrian Ministry of Foreign Affairs</title>
               <title type="sub">German Unity, Soviet Position</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Vienna, 19 July 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">In addition to the information of Dep<add type="edition">[artment]</add> II.1.
               (GZ. 22.17.01/173)<note xml:id="e6341">Document 56, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52930">dodis.ch/52930</ref>.</note> the following
               should be noted regarding the current Soviet position on the German question:</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">1) The concessions made by President Gorbachev<note xml:id="e6351">Mikhail
                  Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>,
                  General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991,
                  Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and
                  President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> to Chancellor Kohl<note xml:id="e6357">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> on
               16 July go far beyond the expectations of those who ultimately considered Soviet
               consent to the NATO solution for a unified Germany under the prerequisite of a
               special solution for “East Elbia”<note xml:id="e6363">A term subsuming all former
                  Prussian territories East of the Elbe.</note> possible. The solution agreed to by
               Kohl and Gorbachev in the Caucasus provides for the future, that is the period after
               the withdrawal of Soviet troops, to a limited extent only, a special military status
               for the territory of the present GDR, cf. the not entirely clear commitment of Kohl
               that no foreign troops will be stationed in this area. In contrast, all other areas
               of Germany as a whole will engage in a complete security policy integration. (The
               last three issues of the prestigious American magazine “Foreign Affairs” include a
               series of articles from known American specialist authors – Kirkpatrick<note xml:id="e6366">Jeane Kirkpatrick (1926–2006), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47062">dodis.ch/P47062</ref>, Political
                  Scientist.</note>, Mc Bundy<note xml:id="e6372">McGeorge Bundy (1919–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P37402">dodis.ch/P37402</ref>, Political Scientist at
                  the Carnegie Corporation 1990–1996.</note>, etc. – who all indicated that they did
               not expect a consensual NATO solution.) It therefore seems legitimate to question the
               reasons why the attitude of the Soviet Union, or – more accurately – Gorbachev, went
               beyond all positive expectations:</p>
            <p>2) The position taken by Gorbachev can on the one hand be explained as the result of
               a combination of newly confirmed domestic policy strengths of the Soviet President
               having “won” his party congress, and on the other hand the recognition of foreign
               policy weaknesses in his country: Fully aware that the confirmation of his
               (currently) unchallengeable role had increased his foreign policy scope, Gorbachev –
               apparently without further coordination with other still relevant forces (military,
               etc.) – and perhaps at the last possible moment successfully attempted to gain as
               much capital (figuratively as well as in the true sense of the word) as possible out
               of the Soviet withdrawal from East Germany and the renunciation of older positions of
               the Soviet Union’s policy on Germany (insisting on the neutrality of a unified
               Germany).</p>
            <p>3) Gorbachev secured at least the following advantages for his country:</p>
            <p>– The reduction of the total German force level to 370,000 men and thus (including
               the manning level of the NVA) an overall drop of 45%;</p>
            <p>– The obvious assumption by unified Germany of the – substantial – costs of Soviet
               troop withdrawal (see letter of intent concerning agreement on effects of
               DM-conversion);</p>
            <p>– Further active efforts by the FRG to gain Western aid for the Soviet Union;</p>
            <p>– Commitment to complete a bilateral comprehensive treaty (probably political
               consultations and economic assistance);</p>
            <p>4) The agreement between Kohl-Gorbachev has been completed without informing the
               Western partners in advance, thus also signaling a future autonomy of German foreign
               policy.</p>
            <p>5) President Gorbachev could speculate with the idea that after a Soviet troop
               withdrawal the negative sentiment towards foreign military presence could generally
               grow further in the FRG and thus perhaps a traditional goal of Soviet policy could
               still be achieved in the longer term.</p>
            <p>6) In total, the agreements of 16 July are – as Gorbachev himself says – a matter of
               successful “Realpolitik.” Whether the Soviet President will succeed to domestically
               secure this result, will also depend on the further reaction in the West: too loud a
               triumph may be harmful, but on the other hand, in light of the Germans “going it
               alone” (see above) it is not to be expected.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>