<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52942</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52942">dodis.ch/52942</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e341">Coded telegram (incoming, translated
                     from Hebrew): <idno>Israel State Archives MFA9537/11</idno>. Delivered by:
                        <orig>28 October 1989.</orig> Addressed to Europe divisions 1 and 3.</note>
                  from the Israeli Ambassador in Bonn, Benjamin Navon<note xml:id="e344">Benjamin
                     Navon (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57507">dodis.ch/P57507</ref>,
                     Israeli Ambassador in Bonn, 1989–1993.</note>, to the Israeli Foreign
                  Ministry</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Secret/Usual <add type="edition">[priority]</add>
               </add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 27 October 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">Today I had a long talk with Wolfgang Mischnick<note xml:id="e359">Wolfgang
                  Mischnick (1921–2002), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57508">dodis.ch/P57508</ref>, Chairman of the FDP faction in the Bundestag of the FRG
                  1968–1991.</note>, the chairman of the FDP faction. Mischnick returned 48 hours
               ago from a visit to East Berlin and was in fact the first Western politician to meet
               with Egon Krenz<note xml:id="e365">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54794">dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and Chairman of the GDR State Council
                  18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note> and the East German leadership.</p>
            <p>In interviews with the media he spoke of his optimistic impressions with regard to
               expected developments in East Germany.</p>
            <p>When talking to me, he admitted that he had taken this line not so much because he
               believes it is actually correct, but because he tends to believe that in this case
               impressions and public reports about them can influence the process. His impression
               is that there is indeed an atmosphere of change and a strong expectation <add type="edition">[of it]</add> among the public, but in private he would not dare to
               predict that this atmosphere of change will become reality.</p>
            <p>He mentioned that Krenz and Gorbachev<note xml:id="e380">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary
                  of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the
                  Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet
                  Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> had studied at around the same time at the
               senior Party college in Moscow, and it is not impossible that this will influence
               Krenz. He emphasized repeatedly that in the USSR change is coming from the top down,
               whereas in East Germany it is coming from below. It is being adopted – even if only
               partially – by the local functionaries who are trying to pass it up the line, but it
               is not certain to what extent this will go through. In his opinion a process like
               that taking place in Hungary or Poland is not to be expected, due to the significant
               difference caused by the German aspect.</p>
            <p>First, <add type="edition">[concerning]</add> the justification for the existence of
               a second German state if it is not socialist and second – the question of a possible
               reunification.</p>
            <p>I told him about the Israeli-Jewiss dilemma with regard to East Germany, especially
               that country’s unwillingness to relate to its past. I also described the traditional
               hostility of East Germany towards Israel and its unsuccessful efforts to gain support
               in the U.S. by displaying a seemingly positive attitude to the restoration of a
               cemetery and a synagogue and the employment of a rabbi for the tiny Jewish community
               in East Berlin. He told me that at the end of January 1990 he would visit East
               Germany at the head of an FDP party delegation and we agreed that we would discuss
               the latter subject before he leaves.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>