<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52946</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52946">dodis.ch/52946</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e5123">Telegram (incoming, translated from
                     Hebrew): <idno>Israel State Archives MFA7352/18</idno>. A handwritten note was
                     added: <orig>1. For the minister 2. The GDR file</orig>. Another handwritten
                     note was added: <orig>I don’t know if Benny Navon is clever, but modest he
                        isn’t</orig>. The name “Navon” means “wise” in Hebrew.</note> from the
                  Israeli Ambassador in Bonn, Benjamin Navon<note xml:id="e5126">Benjamin Navon
                     (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57507">dodis.ch/P57507</ref>, Israeli
                     Ambassador in Bonn, 1989–1993.</note>, to the Israeli Foreign Ministry</title>
               <title type="sub">GDR – FRG – Israel. Following our Telegram No. 73 of 12.4.<note xml:id="e5134">The Israeli Embassy in Bonn and the Information Department to
                     Europe 1 Division, Eastern Europe Division and the Press Division, 12 April
                     1990, <idno>Israel State Archives, MFA7352/18</idno>.</note>
               </title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Secret/Usual <add type="edition">[priority]</add>
               </add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 16 April 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">A) For the first time a coalition government has been formed in East Germany
               which was elected by democratic process. The coalition agreement sets the following
               goals:</p>
            <p>1. Ensuring prosperity and social equality for all citizens of the GDR.</p>
            <p>2. Freedom and justice for all.</p>
            <p>3. Realizing in a speedy and responsible way the reunification of Germany after
               negotiations with the FRG on the basis of Article 23 of the Constitution (of the
               FRG). This will be a contribution to the “peaceful settlement” of Europe.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">B) In the opening meeting of the new East German parliament (Volkskammer), a
               resolution was unanimously adopted which says:</p>
            <p>… It was Germans who during the period of national socialism inflicted immeasurable
               suffering on the peoples of the world. Nationalism and racial madness led to
               genocide, particularly among Jews from all European countries, among the peoples of
               the Soviet Union, the Polish people and the Sinti and Roma [the Gypsy people] ….We
               ask the Jews all over the world for their forgiveness. We ask the people in Israel to
               forgive us for the hypocrisy and hostility shown in official GDR policy towards the
               State of Israel, and to forgive the persecution and degradation of Jewish compatriots
               in our country, also after 1945…. [The new government must act to establish] We
               declare that we will strive for [the establishment of] diplomatic relations with the
               State of Israel<note xml:id="e5157">See the English translation of the declaration in
                     <idno> Israel State Archives, P 4731/2</idno>. Navon’s translation into Hebrew,
                  given in square brackets, is slightly different from the original.</note>.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">C) Paragraphs A and B give expression to the subjects which interest us:</p>
            <p>1. The temporary existence of the GDR, which will pass through most or all of the
               stage of union with the FRG within one to three years.</p>
            <p>2. The GDR’s confrontation with its past and request for forgiveness and pardon from
               the Jewish people and the State of Israel.</p>
            <p>3. Expression of a wish to establish diplomatic relations with the State of
               Israel.</p>
            <p>To this we must add the unambiguous FRG aspect, which is that the President<note xml:id="e5172">Richard von Weizsäcker (1920–2015), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P5944">dodis.ch/P5944</ref>, President of the FRG
                  1.7.1984 –30.6.1994.</note>, the Chancellor<note xml:id="e5178">Helmut Kohl
                  (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>,
                  Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> and Foreign Minister
                  Genscher<note xml:id="e5184">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and
                  Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note> have
               encouraged and approved the idea that we should establish diplomatic relations with
               the GDR. The Israeli aspect is also quite unambiguous. East Germany has fulfilled our
               conditions (which we never defined as such) for opening negotiations on establishing
               relations.</p>
            <p>Things had already begun to move during Hans Modrow’s<note xml:id="e5192">Hans Modrow
                  (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of
                  the GDR Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note> term as prime minister
               (both in his letter <add type="edition">[to Yitzhak Shamir]</add> and the statements
               made to Michael Shiloh<note xml:id="e5201">Michael Shiloh (*1934), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57526">dodis.ch/P57526</ref>, Adviser on Diaspora
                  affairs in the Israeli Foreign Ministry and Israel’s representative at the talks
                  with the GDR in Copenhagen.</note> in the Copenhagen talks) and received official
               status in the resolution of the East German Volkskammer quoted above.</p>
            <p>The question may be asked why establish relations at all with a German state which
               will disappear in the foreseeable future. To this I suggest four replies:</p>
            <p>1. Our support in principle for universal relations between states.</p>
            <p>2. The GDR’s fulfillment of our “conditions”.</p>
            <p>3. The political leadership of the GDR, where the parties are largely a reflection of
               the parties in the FRG, will rapidly merge into the leadership of the FRG as
               reunification approaches and will become part of the leadership of Germany. East
               Germany of today will become five of the sixteen states of united Germany. It is
               essential to encourage this leadership as part of Germany’s future leadership.</p>
            <p>4. In our negotiations with the GDR, we must tactfully and with restraint make a case
               for our demands from that state, in the knowledge that the burden of answering those
               demands will fall mainly on the FRG.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">D) We no longer have any reason to play the game of the SED – the game of
                  Honecker<note xml:id="e5221">Erich Honecker (1912–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46563">dodis.ch/P46563</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED and chairman of the GDR State Council 29.10.1976–18.10.1989.</note> and
               Oskar Fischer<note xml:id="e5227">Oskar Fischer (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P51055">dodis.ch/P51055</ref>, Foreign Minister of the
                  GDR 3.3.1975–12.4.1990.</note>. Bonn is no longer in the eyes of the East German
               government of de Maizière<note xml:id="e5233">Lothar de Maizière (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54809">dodis.ch/P54809</ref>, GDR Prime Minister
                  12.4–2.10.1990.</note> and Markus Meckel<note xml:id="e5239">Markus Meckel
                  (*1952), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54793">dodis.ch/P54793</ref>, Foreign
                  Minister of the GDR 12.4.–20.8.1990.</note> “the capital of the revanchists”,
               where everything is bad. On the contrary, Bonn is the capital of the state which the
               GDR will join according to Article 23, in the foreseeable future. We should not,
               therefore, continue with the anachronism of showing consideration for the outdated
               SED ideology, consideration which may definitely be seen in the FRG as attempting –
               even if only symbolically – to continue the division of Germany.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">In the light of all the above, I propose a decision on opening negotiations to
               establish relations between us and East Germany, on the lines that have been
               mentioned. The site of the talks should be Bonn. I have no doubt that the GDR
               government will accept this and the FRG government will approve. The symbolism will
               be clear. I would be grateful to be appointed as the head of the delegation for the
                  negotiations<note xml:id="e5249">This sentence and the last one are
                  underlined.</note>. Since we will establish relations with a state which has
               adopted as its slogan its temporary status and the end of its existence by means of a
               merger with West Germany, it is appropriate that our relations with it should reflect
               this situation. My status as non-resident Ambassador in East Germany will certainly
               be welcomed in Bonn and East Berlin.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>