<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52943</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52943">dodis.ch/52943</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e1830">Coded telegram (incoming, translated
                     from Hebrew): <idno>Israel State Archives MFA9537/11</idno>. Addressed to
                     Europe division 1.</note> from the Israeli Ambassador in Bonn, Benjamin
                     Navon<note xml:id="e1833">Benjamin Navon (*1933), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57507">dodis.ch/P57507</ref>, Israeli Ambassador
                     in Bonn, 1989–1993.</note>, to the Israeli Foreign Ministry</title>
               <title type="sub">FRG–GDR</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Restricted/Urgent</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 14 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Under separate cover, priority “Immediate”, a survey on relations between the FRG and
               the GDR<note xml:id="e1848">Telegram No. 114 from Benjamin Navon to Europe division
                  1, from 14 November 1989, in the same file.</note>.</p>
            <p>Below a paragraph <add type="edition">[of background information]</add> in
               preparation for the question in the Knesset:</p>
            <p>The question of the reunification of Germany is of interest to Israel only in the
               context of a rise in German nationalism.</p>
            <p>The question of unification is perhaps on the “almost messianic” agenda in Germany
               but is certainly not on the practical agenda. No one is dealing with it as a
               practical problem and feelings are very mixed. My recommendation is thus to avoid
               dire predictions about a powerful wave of German nationalism. I would remind you of
               the statement by the Republican leader Schönhuber<note xml:id="e1860">Franz
                  Schönhuber (1923–2005), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54840"
                     >dodis.ch/P54840</ref>, journalist and politician of the FRG, founder and later
                  chairman of The Republicans.</note> about the East German refugees, “Soll das<note
                  xml:id="e1866">In the original: <orig>SOLL GSD PACK DRUEBEN BLEIBEN</orig>. The
                  letters “GSD” are most likely a spelling mistake for “das”.</note> Pack drüben
               bleiben” (it would be better that the gang should stay there). If Schönhuber, who has
               no qualms about exploiting nationalist feelings for his political needs, is not
               adopting this issue, there is reason to assume that nationalism and reunification in
               the Germany of today do not necessarily go hand in hand.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
