<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52945</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52945">dodis.ch/52945</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e4242">Telegram (incoming, translated from
                     Hebrew): <idno>Israel State Archives MFA 7352/17</idno>. Addressed to Europe
                     division 1.</note> from the Israeli Ambassador in Bonn, Benjamin Navon<note xml:id="e4245">Benjamin Navon (*1933), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57507">dodis.ch/P57507</ref>, Israeli Ambassador in Bonn, 1989–1993.</note>, to
                  the Israeli Foreign Ministry</title>
               <title type="sub">Summary of the Foreign Minister’s<note xml:id="e4253">Moshe Arens
                     (1925–2019), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57439">dodis.ch/P57439</ref>,
                     Israeli Foreign Minister 22.12.1988–11.6.1990.</note> Visit to Bonn</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Secret/Immediate</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 20 February 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">During his visit the Foreign Minister had three working meetings:</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">Breakfast with his colleague, Genscher<note xml:id="e4270">Hans-Dietrich
                  Genscher (1927–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>,
                  Vice-Chancellor and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">A meeting with the President of the FRG, von Weizsäcker<note xml:id="e4279">Richard von Weizsäcker (1920–2015), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P5944">dodis.ch/P5944</ref>, President of the FRG 1.7.1984 –30.6.1994.</note>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">A meeting with Chancellor Kohl<note xml:id="e4288">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the
                  FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>.</p>
            <p n="1"/>
            <p n="1">3 subjects ran through the meetings like a scarlet thread.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">A) Our attitude to the reunification of Germany.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">B) The sanctions of the Commission<note xml:id="e4306">In January 1990 a
                  proposal by the European Parliament to break off scientific ties with Israel
                  because of its policies in the Occupied Territories was presented to the European
                  Commission. Israel feared further sanctions.</note>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">C) A report on our contacts with the GDR</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">1. Michael Shiloh has reported at length on the breakfast with Genscher<note xml:id="e4316">Michael Shiloh (*1934), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57526">dodis.ch/P57526</ref>, the Adviser on Diaspora Affairs in the Israeli Ministry
                  of Foreign Affairs to the Bureau of the Foreign Minister, 18 February 1990,
                     <idno>Israel State Archives MFA 7532/13</idno>.</note>. We would add that
               Genscher’s office asked us to refrain from publishing Genscher’s support for
               continuing our contacts on establishing relations with the GDR.</p>
            <p n="1"/>
            <p n="1">2. The conversation with the President.</p>
            <p>The Foreign Minister opened by passing on greetings from President Herzog<note xml:id="e4328">Chaim Herzog (1918–1997), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P52578">dodis.ch/P52578</ref>, President of Israel 5.5.1983–13.5.1993.</note> and
               expressing his hopes to welcome von Weizsäcker in Israel soon.</p>
            <p>The Foreign Minister reported on our contacts with the GDR. In this context he
               mentioned that Foreign Minister Genscher supports this step and its continuation.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">He said that he sees the reunification of Germany as “a foregone
                  conclusion”<note xml:id="e4340">English in the original.</note>. He has faith in
               the institutions and the democratic tradition of the FRG. He sees the extension of
               this tradition to the GDR as a positive development. Israelis and Jews speak, for
               understandable reasons, of the past, but obviously it is necessary to look towards
               the future.</p>
            <p>The President thanked Foreign Minister Arens for his words about reunification and
               added that there is no way to foretell when it will happen.</p>
            <p>The President thinks it is necessary not only to carry out the formal process with
               the Four Powers, but also to give Germany’s neighbours a feeling of confidence in a
               united Germany. He sees giving this feeling as a kind of unofficial legitimacy. As an
               aim he quotes Politburo member Yakovlev<note xml:id="e4347">Alexander Yakovlev
                  (1923–2005), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54805">dodis.ch/P54805</ref>, member
                  of the CPSU Politburo 1987–1990.</note>, who said that the aim should be not a
               German Europe but a European Germany.</p>
            <p>The President spoke emphatically about the Eastern border, and said that on this
               point Germany would leave no room for further doubt.</p>
            <p>The Foreign Minister said that he does not see a significant difference between
               Germany with 61 million residents and Germany with 77 million residents. The
               President said that perhaps there are some neighbours who fear that the size of
               Germany would lead to a nationalist awakening, but he dismissed this fear on the
               spot.</p>
            <p>He went on to dismiss the concept of “Fortress Europe”. He mentioned that the USSR
               was the last colonialist empire.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the Foreign Minister reported on the issue of sanctions <add type="edition">[on Israel]</add> at the Commission, and expressed his confidence
               that Foreign Minister Genscher would be able to solve the problem at the Council of
               Ministers. After this the Foreign Minister reported on the peace initiative and
               expressed his hope that a three way meeting would take place within a few weeks.</p>
            <p>The President spoke of the need to hold negotiations with parties and organizations
               with which one does not agree, and said that the Palestinians must be helped to
               overcome their past mistakes. In reply the Foreign Minister compared the attitude
               towards the refugees in the Arab world, to that in other parts of the world while
               giving the concrete example of how Europe would look if the Sudeten refugees were
               still being held in camps along the border.</p>
            <p>The President said that he would visit Czechoslovakia on 15.3., the anniversary of
               the entry of the German army into Czechoslovakia. He asked us not to publish this
               until it was made public in both capitals.</p>
            <p>The whole conversation lasted over an hour although only 45 minutes had been
               allotted. It was exceptionally marked by a most sympathetic atmosphere.</p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">3. The conversation with the Chancellor.</p>
            <p>The conversation, which was fixed for the day of the Chancellor’s announcement on
               East Germany in the Bundestag, a meeting with the prime ministers of the states
               and/or with Mitterand<note xml:id="e4376">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> in the Elysée palace, was originally allotted 15
               minutes. Nevertheless, it lasted over half an hour, in a positive atmosphere. The
               Chancellor apologized for having so little time that day and added that he could not
               “resist the charms of the Ambassador” despite the lack of time. The Foreign Minister
               started by sending greetings from the Prime Minister<note xml:id="e4382">Yitzhak
                  Shamir (1915–2012), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54271">dodis.ch/P54271</ref>,
                  Prime Minister of Israel 20.10.1986–13.7.1992.</note> and expressing the hope that
               their exchange of letters had not left any bitter aftertaste. The Chancellor said
               that the problem for him was non-existent.</p>
            <p>The Foreign Minister said that he has faith in the democracy of the FRG and the
               extension of that democratic tradition to the GDR is desirable and a good thing. The
               Foreign Minister reported on his conversations with Genscher and gave details about
               our contacts with the GDR. He said that the East Germans had informed us that they
               wanted to establish diplomatic relations. We had presented a number of prior
               conditions.</p>
            <p>The Foreign Minister mentioned Modrow’s<note xml:id="e4392">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                  Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note> announcement and said that we
               are asking ourselves, in view of the approaching reunification, if there is any point
               in continuing contacts with the GDR. He added that Genscher supported these contacts
               and the establishment of relations with the GDR. Kohl replied to this that he shared
               Genscher’s stand but qualified this by recommending that it should not be done for
               the next 4 weeks (that is, until the elections in the GDR). After this, Kohl spoke at
               length about developments in the GDR. He said that although he had not had much
               belief in the stability of the regime, he did not expect such a rapid collapse. He
               mentioned his 10 point plan which had 3 stages. He had thought then of elections in
               the GDR within a year. In fact the first two stages (that is, the treaty relationship
               and confederation) have already been consigned to oblivion. He mentioned that there
               are already firms in the GDR today doing their accounts in (West) German marks. There
               are parts of the GDR which are breaking away from the crumbling central government.
               In one district the president decided to open all the borders and to declare all the
               Christian festivals as district holidays. A considerable number of the leaders and
               the mayors are in prison or under investigation. Policemen do not turn up for work
               since they do not want to be seen in uniform.</p>
            <p>Kohl mentioned that a citizen of the GDR must be at least 79 in order to remember
               what free elections are like.</p>
            <p>With reference to the members of the Round Table, he said that they are idealists
               without any experience. He described Modrow himself as an honest man and said that he
               is aware that his days in power are numbered and will end on 18 March. He spoke
               sarcastically of the retirement terms offered to party functionaries and so on, who
               have been promised that they will receive their salary for the next two years. Kohl
               said that it is as if the Gestapo members had received their salary for two years
               from 1945 on.</p>
            <p>He then spoke of the question of monetary union and the GDR’s demand for 16 billion
               marks – a sum that will last, in his opinion, for two weeks. According to Kohl there
               are 200 companies in the FRG which are ready to start economic activity immediately
               in the GDR, if they are given suitable collateral for their investment. He mentioned
               that three nuclear reactors in East Germany are “in a worse state than Chernobyl”.
               Despite all this, Kohl is optimistic, since the GDR is situated in the traditional
               industrial area of Germany. Later he spoke briefly about the fears of their
               neighbours on the subject of the two <add type="edition">[military]</add> alliances
               and the presence of 380 thousand Russian troops in East Germany. He said that he had
               told Gorbachev<note xml:id="e4407">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the
                  Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet
                  Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note> that if there was a clash in the GDR between
               demonstrators and the soldiers – that would be the end of perestroika. Kohl sees a
               united Germany as a factor stabilizing the peace between Eastern and Western
               Europe.</p>
            <p>There is no Fourth Reich and there never will be. The new Germany has a new axis. The
               Versailles settlement was a historical error, but the errors of that time were not
               repeated. The economic axis is in the south-west, and the Rhine is the decisive river
               in Germany. We all have an interest in Gorbachev’s success and in his remaining in
               office. If it were not for the developments in Germany, there would be no reform in
               Hungary and Czechoslovakia.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of the conversation Foreign Minister Arens told Kohl that he had
               mentioned the sanctions in his talk with Genscher and with President von Weizsäcker.
               He said that Genscher had promised to act, Kohl said definitely that he opposes
               sanctions and in this context mentioned his stand, together with the British Prime
                  Minister<note xml:id="e4417">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of the
                  United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note>, against sanctions on South Africa.</p>
            <p>The Chancellor asked us to keep him up to date on this issue.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>