<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52944</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52944">dodis.ch/52944</ref>
               <title type="main">Letter<note xml:id="e2589">Letter (translated from Hebrew):
                        <idno>Israel State Archives MFA7352/17</idno>. Copies to Sallai Meridor,
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57514">dodis.ch/P57514</ref> and Moshe
                     Melamed, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57515">dodis.ch/P57515</ref>.</note>
                  from the Assistant Director-General for Eastern Europe, Yosef Govrin<note xml:id="e2598">Yosef Govrin (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57509">dodis.ch/P57509</ref>, Assistant Director-General for Eastern Europe in the
                     Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs 1989–1993.</note>, to the Director-General
                  of the Foreign Ministry, Reuven Merhav<note xml:id="e2604">Reuven Merhav (*1936),
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57513">dodis.ch/P57513</ref>,
                     Director-General of the Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs 1989–1991.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">Subject: Israel-GDR</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Jerusalem, 17 December 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. In the calls by the leaders of the GDR to establish diplomatic relations
               with Israel which we have witnessed over the last few days, we can see some
               difference in their content and their tone. (“Without prior conditions”, “The GDR
               expects capital investment from Israel even before the establishment of
               relations”,”The GDR intends to discuss payment of compensation to the victims of the
               Nazis”, “East Germany cannot pay compensation – especially not when it is in economic
               difficulties – but will be ready to give humanitarian aid to Holocaust victims” etc.)
               (The quotations are taken from press reports and may not be accurate).</p>
            <p>2. However, they have a marked interest in discussing the subject of establishing
               relations and the question of compensation with us. As well as the GDR’s interest in
               improving its image in the West and getting help from it and from Israel to
               reconstruct the economy, it seems to me that the reason for the recent offensive is
               the assumption that the GDR of today sees Israel and world Jewry as a partner in
               opposing “German reunification”. And relations with it may give the current regime a
               stamp of diplomatic approval, while it is disassociating itself from the methods of
               the previous regime in the GDR.</p>
            <p>3. The wish to discuss normalization of relations with us was passed on, as you know,
               through me in March this year, while I was serving in Bucharest<note xml:id="e2620">As Israel’s Ambassador.</note> – as an official message: <add type="edition">[a
                  proposal]</add> to hold a diplomatic dialogue (in Bucharest) and a meeting of the
               two Foreign Ministers at the UN General Assembly. It may be that this was the
               intention of the East German Prime Minister, Modrow<note xml:id="e2626">Hans Modrow
                  (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of
                  the GDR Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note>, when he mentioned in an
               interview with a Haaretz<note xml:id="e2632">Israeli daily newspaper.</note> reporter
               (Today) “We have approached Israel directly. I hope that the answer will be
               positive”. As far as I know there has been no other approach up till now.</p>
            <p>4. Events in the GDR are still developing and it is too early to judge if there will
               be a significant change in the East Germans’ attitude towards our issues. Therefore I
               would recommend that for the moment we confine ourselves to the expression that was
               already published in our name at this time, that is, “that the GDR must first
               recognize its responsibility for the Holocaust and the crimes of the Nazis and
               arrange the payment of compensation to the victims of the Nazis.”</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>