<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52957</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52957">dodis.ch/52957</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e399">Telegram No. 177 (incoming, translated
                     from Dutch): <idno>Netherlands Ministry of Foreign Affairs BZ, 5e BloK</idno>
                     <add type="edition">
                        <idno>[NA 2.05.392]</idno>
                     </add>
                     <idno>, inv.nr. 2128</idno>. Delivered by: <orig>8 November 1989, 8.17
                        p.m.</orig>
                     <idno/>
                  </note> from the Dutch Ambassador in East Berlin, Egbert Jacobs<note xml:id="e405">Egbert Jacobs (*1945), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57545">dodis.ch/P57545</ref>, Dutch Ambassador in East Berlin 1989–1990.</note>,
                  to the Dutch Minister of Foreign Affairs, Hans van den Broek<note xml:id="e411">Hans van den Broek (*1936), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57462">dodis.ch/P57462</ref>, Dutch Minister of Foreign Affairs
                     4.11.1982–3.1.1993.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">GDR Internally</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>East Berlin, 8 November 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">Is there a more significant symbol imaginable for the “revaluation of all
                  values”<note xml:id="e425">Quoted in German: <orig>Umwertung aller Werte.</orig>
               </note> in this country than a high official from the Ministry of the Interior who in
               a forum discussion on GDR-TV calls upon his fellow countrymen on their way to the
               Federal Republic to be sure to travel via border post a and not border post b,
               because at border post a there is less traffic and things can therefore be arranged
               much faster?</p>
            <p>For all observers here reporting on the state of affairs in the GDR is now at least
               as difficult as jumping on a speeding TGV as it passes. Now the Politburo has
               resigned as well! The international media provide a good overall picture of the
               situation, and in particular the West German media also offer enough grounds for
               analysis and reflection. Nonetheless, I will not exclude you from some personal notes
               regarding the past week.</p>
            <p>
               <title type="doc">1.</title>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">The big demonstration of last Saturday in Berlin has – apart from the exemplary
               peaceful and at times even somewhat playful sequence of events – brought to light a
               few interesting things. First, the credibility problem still hangs like a millstone
               around Krenz’<note xml:id="e439">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54794">dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and Chairman of the GDR State Council
                  18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note> neck. The rapid succession of concessional gestures,
               steps and decisions in the first weeks after his leadership acceptance has not
               provided a “benefit of the doubt” position for him. During the rally the functionary
               whom we would call the Dean of the Order of Attorneys in the Netherlands gave a
               speech. Among other things, he openly praised Krenz for his de-escalating
               intervention shortly after the heavy-handed police action on 6 and 7 October, when
               the tension in the country was high. A deafening protest was the speaker’s reward.
               The same thing happened when the speaker suggested that Krenz should be judged in the
               GDR on his actions and not for his words on the events in Beijing in June. A lot of
               water – and mercury – will need to flow under the bridge over the Elbe before Krenz
               will manage to get into a position where the man in the street <emph>will</emph> give
               him the benefit of the doubt. This is especially true because <emph>the</emph>
               skeleton in his closet for him is not so much his statement about Beijing, as his
               presidency of the “Election Committee” of 7 May last. Now that the pressure to
               introduce a radically new electoral law is becoming irresistible, it is inevitable
               that and in the margin of this – also fundamental – discussion, the electoral fraud
               of May will be brought to the fore, which is still fresh in the memory. Krenz will
               not be able to separate himself from this.</p>
            <p>A second noteworthy aspect to last Saturday’s big rally (which, as far as I know, has
               not been reported internationally) was the total – repeat total – absence of
               references to re-unification. Most of the banners that were carried had slogans with
               a fierce political content in relation to this country – not a subject remains
               undiscussed in the streets, in public and “teach-in”-like meetings, and also on the
               nowadays in any case worthwhile GDR-television – but about re-unification there was
               not a word, not a slogan, not a chorus and not a banner. The preoccupation of both
               the leaders of the block parties that were awakened from their hibernation and the
               leaders of the “Initiative”, and of the demonstrators in the street is still the
               reformation of the GDR. In Dutch newspapers I also read reflections of more or less
               authoritative opinion makers who all assume axiomatically that the end of the present
               turbulent developments can only be re-unification. “The more freedom, the less GDR”,
               as it is crisply put. Be this as it may, the now unleashed public discussion in the
               GDR, which has no taboos, gives <emph>no</emph> evidence of this axiom. But maybe
               that does not apply to axioms.</p>
            <p>
               <title type="doc">2.</title>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">The Volkskammer also awakes. The concept of the “Travel Law” had hardly been
               published before the standing committee on justice completely rejected the draft.
               Personally, and admittedly based on conspiracy theories, I had assumed that the
               design would have some room “built in” for amendments by the Volkskammer, after which
               a draft as amended by the Volkskammer would receive force of law. Although I do not
               know the composition of this permanent committee it may be assumed that it will have
               a majority of SED members. On this politically white hot GDR issue with which
                  <emph>all</emph> representatives would like to show themselves aligned, the
               budding profiling drive (<emph>also</emph> of the SED-representatives) has apparently
               overcome the usual party discipline.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile the permanent committee for “Constitution and Law” of the Volkskammer has
               charged the Presidium in unambiguous terms with laxity and has demanded an emergency
               session with plenary debate.</p>
            <p>
               <title type="doc">3.</title>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">In close interaction with the awakening of the Volkskammer the awakening of the
               block parties is taking place. I have reported before on the pioneering role of the
               liberal LDPD and its chairman Gerlach<note xml:id="e463">Manfred Gerlach (1928–2011),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54812">dodis.ch/P54812</ref>, Chairman of the
                  Council of State of the GDR 6.12.1989–5.4.1990.</note>. He continues to fulfill
               this role. As the first person belonging to the political establishment he recently
               questioned the “claim to power and truth”<note xml:id="e469">Quoted in German:
                     <orig>Machts- und Wahrheitsanspruch.</orig>
               </note> of the SED. In the past 2 months Gerlach has shown himself to be a good
               director of the interaction between his own statements and the street protests, and
               there need be no doubt in my opinion that the promised new electoral law will in fact
               defray with the “leading role”<note xml:id="e474">Quoted in German:<orig> führende
                     Rolle.</orig>
               </note> of the SED. The question remains how the lawyers will shape things, taking
               into account that the Minister of Justice<note xml:id="e479">Hans-Joachim Heusinger
                  (*1925): <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57546">dodis.ch/P57546</ref>, Deputy
                  Chairman Council of Ministers of the GDR 1972–1989.</note> – now obviously
               outgoing – is the only LDPD member in the government.</p>
            <p>Gerlach has already been nominated for the presidency of the Volkskammer by his party
               and he appears to me a good contender, also given the fact that Krenz clearly wants
               him to (co-)play a prominent role. This would boost the activation process of the
               Volkskammer and would enable the LDPD, with a new chairman, to distance itself from
               the past, and therefore from the SED.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile the NDPD has chosen a new chairman, the CDU is still working on this. The
               potential importance of a credible CDU-chairman is of course fundamental for the
               recovery of good relations with the churches, because these were in fact
               non-existent. And should it come to that, then it needs no argument that a strong,
               potential oppositional block could arise. The general break-up has now taken its
               first victim in the Evangelische Kirche: the legion of “public officials who have
                  resigned”<note xml:id="e489">Quoted in German: <orig>zurückgetretene öffentliche
                     Persönlichkeiten.</orig>
               </note> has been reinforced with the Bishop of Greifswald<note xml:id="e494">Horst
                  Gienke (*1930): <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57547">dodis.ch/P57547</ref>,
                  Bishop of Greifswald 1972–1989.</note> a few days ago, the most state-loyal
               Landesbischof in the Evangelische Kirche, the man who in July received Honecker<note xml:id="e500">Erich Honecker (1912–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46563">dodis.ch/P46563</ref>, General Secretary of the SED and chairman of the GDR
                  State Council 29.10.1976–18.10.1989.</note> at the consecration of the restored
               basilica in Greifswald, to the apprehension of his colleagues.</p>
            <p>
               <title type="doc">4.</title>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">Amidst all the powder vapor it remains significant that still no personality
               with even a glimmer of charisma has risen to report “to speak”.<note xml:id="e513">Quoted in German: <orig>zu Wort</orig>.</note> The line-up of speakers at the
               large Berlin rally included a number of well-known artists, Prof. Reich of the Neue
               Forum, and also the former HVA-chief Markus Wolf<note xml:id="e516">Markus Wolf
                  (1924–2006), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57548">dodis.ch/P57548</ref>, GDR
                  spymaster and head of the STASI (Hauptverwaltung Aufklärung) 1952–1989.</note>,
               all of whom are speakers of an almost sleep-inducing dullness. The SED secretary in
               Dresden, Modrow<note xml:id="e522">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                  Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note>, now internationally typified as
               a “reformer”, is in the lead in a demonstration that specifically demands the
               “renunciation of the monopoly on power and truth”<note xml:id="e528">Quoted in
                  German: <orig>Verzicht auf Machts- und Wahrheitsmonopol.</orig>
               </note> of his own SED, but in his public appearance he has the characteristics of an
               alderman from Ootmarsum<note xml:id="e533">Village on the eastern border of the
                  Netherlands, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/G15397">dodis.ch/G15397</ref>.</note>.
               The same applies in my opinion to Günther Schabovski<note xml:id="e539">Günter
                  Schabowski (1929–2015), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P56902">dodis.ch/P56902</ref>, member of the SED Politburo and spokesman of the GDR
                  government 1989.</note>, who incidentally was the only major SED-functionary
               (Politburo) to speak at the big Berlin rally and hardly got a word in, because he was
               constantly being shrieked down. A bad omen for this “reformer” who will presumably
               receive a heavier portfolio within the Politburo (economy?, media?).</p>
            <p>Also noticeably absent from the stage are actors with a conservative background. If
               there is a GDR-Ligachev<note xml:id="e547">Yegor Ligachev (*1920), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57414">dodis.ch/P57414</ref>, Second Secretary of
                  Communist Party of the Soviet Union 10.3.1985–14.7.1990.</note> he dares not
               manifest himself as such. I find this deceitful, because it is difficult to conceive
               that there is no conservative wing within the SED. In the euphoria of the moment it
               is too easily assumed that there are really no communists left in the GDR.</p>
            <p>
               <title type="doc">5.</title>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">Today the Central Committee of the SED has gathered for its 3-day meeting. It
               is expected that this assembly will also demand an emergency session of the
               Volkskammer, with plenary debate, bringing forward the date of the elections for the
               Volkskammer (which Krenz mentioned were tentatively planned for mid- ‘91 just two
               weeks ago), a special SED Party Congress to be held this year – the regular Congress
               is scheduled in May ‘90 – a directive statement on emigration (which will take into
               account the rejection of the draft submitted by the government), on a new electoral
               law, on the economy, and a new Politburo. At the very least.</p>
            <p>
               <title type="doc">6.</title>
            </p>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">And finally: there are still no strikes. Instead people are working extra time,
               more and more. How is it possible.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>