<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52953</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52953">dodis.ch/52953</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e2643">Telegram No. 3280/3281 (incoming,
                     translated from German): <idno>Political Archive of the German Federal Foreign
                        Office PA/AA B 1, Bd. 178922</idno>. Delivered by: <orig>19 December 1989,
                        9.12 p.m.</orig> Also published in: <idno>Die Einheit. Das Auswärtige Amt,
                        das DDR-Außenministerium und der Zwei-plus-Vier-Prozess, ed. by Horst Möller
                        et. al. on behalf of the Institute for Contemporary History Berlin–Munich,
                        Göttingen, 2015, doc. 33.</idno> Ref.: <idno>Telegram No. 3235 – Pol 330.00
                        and No. 3236/37 – Pol 322.00 of 13 December 1989</idno>.</note> from the
                  Ambassador of the FRG in Paris, Franz Pfeffer<note xml:id="e2646">Franz Pfeffer
                     (*1926), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57451">dodis.ch/P57451</ref>,
                     Ambassador of the FRG in Paris 7.11.1987–31.1.1991.</note>, to the Ministry of
                  Foreign Affairs of the FRG</title>
               <title type="sub">French Position on the German Question, Franco-German
                  Relations</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add><emph>Extract</emph> Confidential and very urgent</add>
               <dateline>Paris, 18 Dezember 1989, 3.54 p.m. </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>For information</p>
            <p>I herewith present a report by the Embassy’s Political Section on the French position
               on the German Question. The focus is on critical aspects of which our Head Office
               should be aware.</p>
            <p>Based on my experiences in colloquia and talks, I note the following:</p>
            <p>1. “La France profonde” (“deep France”) of the provinces and simple, decent people
               has reacted in a very healthy way to the fall of the Wall and developments in the
               GDR. Joy, solidarity and willingness to help can be felt in the letters we have
               received. These people are also the reason for our good ratings. This part of France
               is impressed by the resolve and moderation that allowed the peaceful revolution to be
               achieved without bloodshed. Young French people feel the same way or at least a large
               percentage of them do.</p>
            <p>2. The political class in France is full of doubt and scepticism. Concerns range from
               a resurgence of Bismarck’s<note xml:id="e2669">Otto von Bismark (1815–1898), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P3822">dodis.ch/P3822</ref>, Chancellor of the German
                  Empire 1871–1890.</note> Reich to German economic predominance. But only a very
               few people say they do not want German reunification. Most are waiting to see what
               will happen and playing for time. As always, Mitterrand<note xml:id="e2675">François
                  Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775"
                     >dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France 21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> is able
               to see furthest. He is apparently convinced that there will be reunification, but
               would like to help guide the process in an orderly fashion, in particular to ensure
               that the European integration process is not adversely affected.</p>
            <p>We should not underestimate those in the French civil service who would like to put
               the brakes on further developments. These people also cause difficulties for us in
               other areas (from talks on disarmament to the project on integrated Franco-German
               embassies). Only a few civil servants are as pro-European and convinced of the need
               for Germany and France to take a joint stance as Secretary General Bianco<note
                  xml:id="e2683">Jean-Louis Bianco (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57454"
                     >dodis.ch/P57454</ref>, Secretary General to the President of France
                  1982–1991.</note> (Elysée) and Permanent Under-Secretary Scheer<note
                  xml:id="e2689">François Scheer (*1934), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P56758"
                     >dodis.ch/P56758</ref>, Secretary-General of the French Foreign Ministry
                  1988–1992.</note> (Quai).</p>
            <p>3. Almost immediately after the “euphoric phase” of the fall of the Wall, the media
               switched to criticism and concern. At times, it is downright malicious, with talk of
               the danger of a re-emerging Third Reich and the rebirth of anti-Semitism. The media
               gives the impression that the conditions for reunification must be dictated to us
               again (it must be peaceful, democratic, in a European context, accepted by the Four
               Powers and recognise the Oder-Neisse Line).</p>
            <p>4. Our public diplomacy efforts are now of crucial importance in France. I have been
               able to present our position several times on television and on the radio. Colloquia
               are held frequently and the German problem is the topic of every conversation.</p>
            <p>The more calmly and controlled we present our views, the sooner we can make use of
               the situation and the more respect we will receive (as a western extension of the
               moderation shown by our compatriots in the East). Depending on the forum, the
               important thing is to present the principles of our policies in a simple or more
               subtle way, namely that the shared goal with France and the other Western partners is
               to overcome the division of Europe and thus also the division of Germany (as part of
               a peaceful evolution, avoiding destabilisation, exercising the right to
               self-determination in the GDR, and speeding up the West European integration process
               in order to maintain a firm stance and to be able to help the reforming countries in
               the East in an effective way).</p>
            <p>Presenting our views in this way always enables us to deflect further argument.
               Particularly when speaking to a young audience, such as students, I have received
               resounding applause for such points.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>Annex (drafted by Elfenkämper<note xml:id="e2707">Helmut Elfenkämper (*1947), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57453">dodis.ch/P57453</ref>, Councellor at the
                  Embassy of the FRG in Paris 1987–1991.</note>)</p>
            <p>I. Summary:</p>
            <p>Since the summer, the position taken by French officialdom on the “German Question”
               has become increasingly rigid as events in and around the GDR have accelerated; under
               certain circumstances, this position could prove to be a burden on Franco-German
               relations for a longer period of time, not least because French motives are
               wide-ranging and the country’s stabilisation endeavours can not only be seen from the
               perspective of a current transition crisis that is regarded as potentially
               dangerous.</p>
            <p>It is currently unclear whether France will manage to bring itself to play a
               constructive role in an emerging trend towards a stronger German position in Europe
               and to make use of the privileged Franco-German relationship in this regard or if it
               will try to postpone such a development for as long as possible as allegedly not
               being in its interest. In the latter case, this could give rise to longer-term
               problems in official Franco-German relations. Should these problems go on for longer,
               they could also rub off on the deeper layers of Franco-German relations that have so
               far not been affected. This type of development must be avoided.</p>
            <p>In the Embassy’s opinion, we should do everything we can in the short term to create
               as much common ground as possible between France and Germany. The French President
               will visit the GDR immediately after the Federal Chancellor’s visit<note
                  xml:id="e2721">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852"
                     >dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998. He visited
                  Dresden on 19 and 20 December 1989 and François Mitterrand visited East Berlin and
                  Leipzig from 20 to 22 December 1989.</note>. These visits could serve as a test
               case for a dovetailed, coordinated division of labour between France and Germany.</p>
            <p>At the same time, we should work on the French media, but remain aware of the limits
               of our ability to shape French opinion towards us in France. We should also explore
               to what extent the various levels of the comprehensive and special Franco-German
               consultation mechanism can be used more intensively, e.g. for joint discussions on
               the question of how far the current developments in Europe will affect security
               policy.</p>
            <p>
               <add type="edition">[…]</add>
               <note xml:id="e2732">For the complete version of the document in German cf. <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/52953">dodis.ch/52953</ref>.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
