<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52960</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52960">dodis.ch/52960</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e3489">Telegram No. 73 (incoming, translated
                     from Dutch): <idno>Netherlands Ministry of Foreign Affairs BuZa 1985–1990, blok
                        Z-299, </idno>
                     <add type="edition">
                        <idno>[NA 2.05.392]</idno>
                     </add>
                     <idno> inv.nr. 4601 </idno>
                     <add type="edition">
                        <idno>[2129]</idno>
                     </add>
                     <idno>.</idno>
                     <idno/>
                  </note> from the Dutch Ambassador in Bonn, Jan van der Tas<note xml:id="e3498">Jan
                     von der Tas (1928–2009), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57557">dodis.ch/P57557</ref>, Dutch Ambassador in Bonn 1986–1993.</note>, to the
                  Dutch Minister of Foreign Affairs, Hans van den Broek<note xml:id="e3504">Hans van
                     den Broek (*1936), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57462">dodis.ch/P57462</ref>,
                     Dutch Minister of Foreign Affairs 4.11.1982–3.1.1993.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">Visit Minister Ter Beek<note xml:id="e3511">Relus ter Beek
                     (1944–2008), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57561">dodis.ch/P57561</ref>, Dutch
                     Defense Minister 7.11.1989–22.8.1994.</note> to Defense Minister FRG<note xml:id="e3517">Gerhard Stoltenberg (1928–2001), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46108">dodis.ch/P46108</ref>, Defence Minister of
                     the FRG 21.4.1989–1.4.1992.</note>
               </title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 8 February 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p/>
            <p n="1">On the 7<hi>th</hi> of this month, the Minister of Defense Ter Beek paid a
               visit of about three hours to his FRG colleague Stoltenberg that began with a full
               military ceremony. In the first hour discussions were held between both ministers
               accompanied only by state secretary Pfahls,<note xml:id="e3534">Ludwig-Holger Pfahls
                  (*1942), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57562">dodis.ch/P57562</ref>, State
                  Secretary for Defense of the FRG 1987–1992.</note> Stoltenberg’s aide and myself,
               followed by a delegation meeting lasting over one and a half hours, to be reported on
               separately.</p>
            <p n="1"/>
            <p n="1">Situation in the GDR</p>
            <p>Stoltenberg began the initial small group conversation by expressing the desire that,
               in addition to bilateral issues, security-political topics would also be discussed.
               He introduced these with remarks about the dramatic situation in the GDR, which, as
                  Modrow<note xml:id="e3546">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR
                  Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note> had said to Kohl<note xml:id="e3552">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> in
               Davos, was now really on the verge of administrative, economic and social collapse
               which is also existentially threatening for all neighbors of the GDR. For this reason
               the federal government is forced to first deal with the economic and internal
               problems of German unification and shift the recognized external, status- and safety
               aspects to a future date for the time being.</p>
            <p>This, according to Stoltenberg, had just now led to a governmental decision to
               formulate an offer to the GDR government to enter into, albeit under a number of very
               strict conditions, a monetary and economic community. This decision is of a political
               nature and is clearly outpacing Stoltenberg, faster than can be acceptable to his
               successor Waigel<note xml:id="e3560">Theo Waigel (*1939), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54838">dodis.ch/P54838</ref>, Finance Minister of the
                  FRG 21.4.1989–27.10.1998.</note> or Bundesbank president Poelhl<note xml:id="e3566">Karl Otto Pöhl (1929–2014), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P51405">dodis.ch/P51405</ref>, President of the Bundesbank of the FRG
                  1980–1991.</note>, but Modrow and also people like Berghofer<note xml:id="e3572">Wolfgang Berghofer (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57586">dodis.ch/P57586</ref>, Mayor of Dresden 1986–1990.</note> stipulate that there
               is no time to lose in remedying the situation in the GDR: the number of
                  “Übersiedler”<note xml:id="e3578">
                  <orig>Übersiedler</orig>: Migrants moving from the GDR to FRG.</note> has already
               risen to three thousand per day and if this continues hundreds of thousands will
               arrive in the west in the near future. One can hardly hide the fact that the proposal
               cannot be regarded as entering into a monetary union between equal partners, but that
               in fact the entire currency policy and an important part of economic and social
               policy must be placed in the custody of the Bundesbank. There will probably be no
               time to adjust the Legal Statute of the Bundesbank<note xml:id="e3581">Quoted in
                  German: <orig>Bundesbankgesetz.</orig>
               </note> and the speaker did not deny that there was a risk that the German position
               of preserving the independence of the Bundesbank, an absolute priority of stability
               policy and a condition of economic-political harmonization for monetary unification
               might thus be placed in a peculiar light for some interlocutors of the FRG. (see also
               my 72 of today)</p>
            <p n="1"/>
            <p n="1">SNF</p>
            <p>Minister Ter Beek asked his colleague about the current views of the FRG government
               on SNF and at what point would this topic need to be discussed in the alliance.
               Stoltenberg did not consider this subject to be appropriate for public discussion at
               present, but a negotiation concept on substrategic weapons must be formulated timely
               within NATO before a second round of CSE. In the federal government there is
               agreement on two points, namely 1) the Soviet preponderance must be phased out and 2)
               a responsible NATO concept is also possible with fewer than the current number of
               substrategic nuclear weapons. Presently, among other things, technical research is
               being carried out to determine whether one could do with a minimum of exclusively air
               based SNF. Against this, there are of course significant objections because of the
               vulnerability.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, a lot has changed politically. Stoltenberg believed that the
               Americans are also more relaxed with regard to this subject, even if the Bush<note xml:id="e3594">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> Administration is certainly prepared to fight
               in Congress to keep the SNF option open. Stoltenberg thought it important in future,
               and perhaps soon, to speak on this subject in the first place confidentially and at a
               high political level, since this – it could not be denied – carried a considerable
               emotional charge in the Federal Republic. (Minister Ter Beek had pointed out by way
               of introduction that apparently Genscher<note xml:id="e3600">Hans-Dietrich Genscher
                  (1927–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>,
                  Vice-Chancellor and Minster for Foreign Affairs of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>, Dregger<note xml:id="e3606">Alfred Dregger
                  (1920–2002), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54837">dodis.ch/P54837</ref>, Chairman
                  of the CDU faction in the Bundestag of the FRG 1982–1991.</note> and Bahr<note xml:id="e3612">Egon Bahr (1922–2015), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P39530">dodis.ch/P39530</ref>, Member of the SPD.</note> – representing the three
               largest parties – had come together in the rejection of SNF.)</p>
            <p>Minister Ter Beek, pointing out that it is a deterrent weapon should of course be
               able to hit the enemy wherever he was, underlined that the political debate in the
               Netherlands remains ongoing and that it will take place in a new political context.
               For the time being it is best to study the case thoroughly, yet with the certainty
               that the subject will be on the table again after CSE-1. In response to a question
               from Minister Ter Beek as to whether SNF would not automatically become an election
               theme in the FRG, Stoltenberg replied that it would probably be a theme, but after
               all that has happened recently it will not be the center of gravity in the election
               battle.</p>
            <p>Stoltenberg repeated once again that on the one hand the FRG does not want a
               denuclearized Europe, and on the other hand it had not yet fixed its position on the
               SNF issue. Much would depend on whatever truly binding treaty agreements might be
               reached with the Soviet Union in the short term. However, it was certain that nuclear
               artillery could very well be abolished.</p>
            <p n="1"/>
            <p n="1">French position</p>
            <p>Minister Ter Beek asked his colleague how the French had spoken about a.o. Pluto and
                  Hades<note xml:id="e3628">Pluton and Hadès were French nuclear-armed short-range
                  ballistic missiles launched from mobile platforms.</note> in confidential
               discussions. His impression was that the French regarded these weapons as
               predominantly insurance of access to the negotiating table in the event of a possible
               conflict, a trauma that has persisted since the end of the Second World War.
               Stoltenberg acknowledged that the French remained very cautious on this point and
               that it is important to appeal to them increasingly. It is desirable that the French
               participate in ever more political forums and structures within NATO. In this
               context, French discussion partners like to hide behind the exclusive competence of
               president Mitterrand.<note xml:id="e3631">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> Stoltenberg appeared to avoid for the time being the
               question of whether the WEU might play a role here. Mitterrand is no fan of the WEU,
               but also for the Federal Republic France’s further integration in NATO would be
               conditional on lending more substance to the WEU consultations, so that the WEU will
               not function as a competitor but rather as a supplier to NATO. In conclusion to this
               theme, Stoltenberg pointed out that the present French Prime Minister Rocard<note xml:id="e3637">Michel Rocard (1930–2016), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57459">dodis.ch/P57459</ref>, Prime Minister of France 10.5.1988–15.5.1991.</note> is
               known to have views of his own on this issue, so that one can perhaps regard
               potential French cooperation with a little more optimism.</p>
            <p n="1"/>
            <p n="1">German unification</p>
            <p>In response to a question from minister Ter Beek as to whether Mr. Stoltenberg has a
               timetable in mind for German unification he answered negatively. It is clear that a
               democratically elected GDR Parliament could very quickly decide to open negotiations
               with the FRG about unification, which, moreover, is coming about increasingly fast in
               a factual sense. However, apart from very important domestic political decisions, the
               “political completion”<note xml:id="e3649">Quoted in German: <orig>Politische
                     Vollendung.</orig>
               </note> of this process requires the solution of the external problems concerning the
               neighbors, the Allies, the “Schutzmächte”<note xml:id="e3654">
                  <orig>Schutzmächte</orig>: the Allied Powers protecting Germany.</note> and
               especially the Soviet Union. Regarding the time span that will be needed from the
               beginning to the end of this process there are at least three views in the Federal
               Government. The key question here is obviously what demands the Soviet Union will
               make related to formal unification.</p>
            <p>The Federal Government knows and recognizes that the Soviet Union will make demands
               and also has legitimate rights in this matter, but even the United States does not
               know where a Soviet “bottom line” might be and it is questionable whether the
               Russians know it themselves.</p>
            <p>About the conceivable military configuration in a united Germany, Stoltenberg said
               Genscher had, as usual, released all sorts of trial balloons, but he was now resigned
               to the official line of the Federal Government, which has also been accepted by
               Minister Baker<note xml:id="e3661">James Baker (*1930), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P56605">dodis.ch/P56605</ref>, United States Secretary
                  of State 25.1.1989–23.8.1992.</note>, although apparently this has once again been
               contested by Fitzwater<note xml:id="e3667">Marlin Fitzwater (*1942), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57564">dodis.ch/P57564</ref>, White House Press
                  Secretary 1987–1993.</note>. A central question in all of this is of course how
               much longer Soviet forces will (be able to) remain on the territory of the GDR.</p>
            <p>In connection with the relevant conversations held at the 27<hi>th</hi>
                  Wehrkundetagung<note xml:id="e3678">
                  <orig>Wehrkundetagung</orig>: annual conference on security issues, held in
                  Munich.</note> (ref my 66) Stoltenberg answered the question on how representative
               the opinions of Bahr and Voigt<note xml:id="e3681">Karsten Voigt (*1941), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57565">dodis.ch/P57565</ref>, member of the Bundestag
                  of the FRG for the SPD 1976–1998.</note> were for the entire SPD by noting that
               their position certainly represented a basic current in the SPD, but that otherwise a
               number of SPD leaders, including Vogel<note xml:id="e3687">Hans-Jochen Vogel (*1926),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P55169">dodis.ch/P55169</ref>, Leader of the SPD
                  14.6.1987–29.5.1991.</note>, would also have great difficulties. Much would depend
               on the question of whether a real safety structure can be constructed in the CSCE
               context built on the three pillars: the Soviet Union, North America and Western
               Europe.</p>
            <p/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>