<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52963</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52963">dodis.ch/52963</ref>
               <title type="sub">Telegram<note xml:id="e6651">Telegram No. 394 (incoming, translated
                     from Dutch): <idno>Netherlands Ministry of Foreign Affairs BuZa 1985-1990, blok
                        Z-299, </idno>
                     <add type="edition">
                        <idno>[NA 2.05.392]</idno>
                     </add>
                     <idno> inv.nr. 4601 </idno>
                     <add type="edition">
                        <idno>[2129]</idno>
                     </add>.</note> from the Dutch Ambassador in Bonn, Jan van der Tas<note xml:id="e6660">Jan von der Tas (1928–2009), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57557">dodis.ch/P57557</ref>, Dutch Ambassador in
                     Bonn 1986–1993.</note>, to the Dutch Minister of Foreign Affairs, Hans van den
                     Broek<note xml:id="e6666">Hans van den Broek (*1936), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57462">dodis.ch/P57462</ref>, Dutch Minister of
                     Foreign Affairs 4.11.1982–3.1.1993.</note>
               </title>
               <title type="sub">Situation in GDR</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 9 August 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">The first economic counsellor<note xml:id="e6680">Berend van Gorkom (*1942),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57576">dodis.ch/P57576</ref>, First economic
                  counsellor of the Dutch Embassy in Bonn, 1989–1990.</note> had a conversation with
               Ministerialdirektor Dr. Becker<note xml:id="e6686">Jürgen Becker (*1953), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57577">dodis.ch/P57577</ref>, Director General for
                  Industry at the Ministry of Economic Affairs of the FRG.</note>, Director General
               for Industry at the Federal Ministry of Economic Affairs and also leader of the
               Leitungsstab Deutschland, in which all economic aspects of the German reunification
               were coordinated.</p>
            <p>Dr. Becker acknowledged that industry in the GDR is in big trouble, but this was also
               generally expected. On questions regarding the economic background of the
               increasingly rapid acceleration of the unification process Dr. Becker replied as
               follows.</p>
            <p>Both the government and the civil service apparatus in the GDR are apparently
               functioning worse and worse, now that real difficulties arise. The government started
               with enthusiasm at the time, but is showing less and less effectiveness. The
               ministers do not do much other than catalogue what kind of money they all need. The
               Minister of Finance does nothing apart from making sums for one thing and another and
               sending them to Minister Waigel<note xml:id="e6696">Theo Waigel (*1939), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54838">dodis.ch/P54838</ref>, Finance Minister of the
                  FRG 21.4.1989–27.10.1998.</note> with requests for more money. The Minister of
               Finance of the GDR is thus no counterweight to the demands of the other departments.
               Everything is shifted on to the FRG. The civil service is in fact still the old
                  Honnecker<note xml:id="e6702">Erich Honecker (1912–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46563">dodis.ch/P46563</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED and chairman of the GDR State Council 29.10.1976–18.10.1989.</note>
               apparatus. Becker did not want to claim that all officials are ideologically
               motivated to thwart progress, but at the very least they lack insight into the market
               economy. Furthermore, they are not used to making decisions, for fear of being held
               financially responsible for policy actions (sale of land to investors) and finally
               they are completely uncertain about their position. Becker said that of the 5,500
               employees at the GDR Ministry of Economic Affairs, only some 400 would be taken on by
               the Federal Ministry of Economic Affairs. The rest will soon be dismissed, a
               perspective that is not exactly motivating.</p>
            <p>If one arrives at the communal level in the command chain, individual responsibility
               or initiative is completely absent. Here orders from above are still awaited. Because
               of this, the government guidelines at work level remain virtually unnoticed, much to
               the detriment of investment activity from the west. If one adds to this picture the
               Volkskammer, which time and again passes laws that seriously impede entrepreneurship
               resp. investment (limitation of the possibilities for workforce reductions etc.),
               then it becomes clear, says spokesman, that real positive economic development in the
               GDR awaits political unification. This must be achieved as soon as possible, the
               sooner the better. This will of course not solve all problems immediately but will
               enable a start to build up from.</p>
            <p>In this context he also considered it of great importance that reunification
               coincides with elections taking place, so that the new government (hopefully with a
               solid majority) can intervene effectively. A reunification in September or October,
               but with elections on 2 December is not very attractive for the Federal Government,
               according to the speaker, also for reasons other than strictly electoral ones. It
               will immediately be held accountable for an increasingly poor economic situation but
               will not really be legitimized for the GDR population and will, moreover, be
               powerless just before elections, like all democratic governments. The SPD naturally
               sees tactical advantages in such a constellation.</p>
            <p>Counsellor then brought the conversation round to the activities of the
                  Treuhandanstalt<note xml:id="e6714">Trust Agency, established 17 June 1990 by the
                  GDR authorities to privatize East German enterprises in the process of
                  reunification.</note> and the issue of a threatening “liquidity collapse”.
               Spokesman admitted that indeed the money appears not to circulate in the GDR. Wages
               received are spent on imported goods from the west. The companies in the GDR (i.e.
               those companies that are in the hands of the Treuhand) thus receive no income.
               Moreover, what they still sell is not or in any case not immediately paid for.
               Therefore, there must be a new injection of liquidity every month, which the banks
               will only do if the Treuhand guarantees this. Since in this so-called watering
                  can<note xml:id="e6717">Quoted in German: <orig>Gießkanne.</orig>
               </note> method all companies receive credit, including those that will almost
               certainly go bankrupt in the coming months, the need for selection becomes
               increasingly urgent. Dr. Becker emphasized that this is absolutely necessary to
               quickly rid the companies of the already existing view that one only needs to hold up
               a hand. Spokesman therefore expected many applications for bankruptcies in the near
               future from manifestly hopeless cases. On the other hand, the potassium mines etc.,
               for example, which certainly belong to the hopeless category, will be spared for a
               while because they provide 15,000 jobs in a region where practically no other
               employment is available. Gradually one must try to get a grip on the flow of sub‑
               sidies.</p>
            <p>The rise in unemployment that is already detectable has not so much to do with
               company closures, but is primarily the result of reducing the infamous
               “overstaffing”. Many inspectors and other unproductive forces are now made redundant.
               All this was foreseen. Spokesman was surprised that this is now causing such astir in
               the press. Everybody has known for months that if unemployment in the GDR remains
               below one million at the end of 1990, one can<note xml:id="e6724">Handwritten
                     note:<orig> “could have spoken”, because now already 1.2 million
                     unemployed!</orig>
               </note> speak of a development that is better than expected.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>