<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53171</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53171">dodis.ch/53171</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e2339">Telegram No. 0-2787/IV (incoming,
                     translated from Polish): <idno>Archives of the Polish Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs AMSZ, ZD 24/91, w. 11, w. 37</idno>. Delivered by: <orig>30 November
                        1989, 12.20 a.m.</orig>
                  </note> from the Polish Ambassador in Cologne, Ryszard Karski<note xml:id="e2342">Ryszard Karski (*1926), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57590">dodis.ch/P57590</ref>, Polish Ambassador in Cologne 1987–1990.</note>, to
                  the Polish Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs, Bolesław Kulski<note xml:id="e2348">Bolesław Kulski, <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P50550">dodis.ch/P50550</ref>,
                     Polish Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs 1988–1990.</note>
               </title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Immediately Cologne<note xml:id="e2356">The Polish Embassy in the FRG was
                     situated in Cologne.</note>, 29 November 1989, 6.20 p.m.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">Assessment of Chancellor Kohl’s<note xml:id="e2361">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the
                  FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> 10-point “German policy” programme presented at
               the Bundestag on 29 November (résumé by diplomatic cable, full version 29
                  November<note xml:id="e2367">
                  <idno>Archives of the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs AMSZ, Dep. IV 31/92, w.
                     2</idno>.</note>).</p>
            <p>1. Kohl’s address marks a new quality in Bonn’s reunification policy, a transition to
               its operative and concrete phase.</p>
            <p>2. The programme he set out involves the creation of a political and economic
               infrastructure, the concept of confederation followed by federation of the two states
               (while pursuing the aim of full reunification of Germany), but without defining a
               specific timeframe. The vision is very compelling and broad, without precluding any
               modifications and other solutions heading in the same direction.</p>
            <p>3. Kohl’s concept meets the expectations of West German political circles and its
               public; it allows the Chancellor and government to seize the initiative on this
               subject matter, both with respect to the GDR and internal politics of the FRG. Given
               the broad support for the programme from all major political parties (except for the
               “Greens”), it can be viewed as a national mission.</p>
            <p>4. Kohl’s political and – crucially – economic offer addressed to the GDR (immediate
               assistance in many fields, substantial increase in such assistance in the future,
               facilitating links with the EEC) on condition of fundamental and irreversible
               internal changes in the GDR is aimed at invigorating and enhancing reunification
               sentiments among the public and the political circles of the GDR (notably in view of
               discussions ahead of a convention of the Socialist Unity Party of Germany (SED), and
               the important decisions about further development at home and relations with the
               FRG). Special importance is attached to free elections in the hope that they will
               change power relations and make it easier for Bonn to achieve its objectives.</p>
            <p>5. It is apparent that Kohl is making a strong connection between reunification and a
               future European architecture, the CSCE and disarmament process, and W<add type="edition">[estern]</add> E<add type="edition">[uropean]</add> integration so
               as to alleviate widespread concerns (harboured also by the Allies) that the
               integration of both German states is proceeding too quickly and could slip out of
               control. However, the very fact that Bonn has introduced such an initiative at this
               stage is due to a belief that is gaining ground in the FRG whereby both the East
               (including the USSR) and the West are less and less capable of slowing down the
               dynamic process towards reunification. At the same time, attempts are being made to
               create an impression that Bonn’s current actions are being taken with the consent of
               the main Allies, including the USSR (as suggested by Teltschik<note xml:id="e2386">Horst M. Teltschik (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57413">dodis.ch/P57413</ref>, Foreign policy advisor to the Chancellor of the
                  FRG.</note> at an internal briefing for leading West German journalists on 27
               November).</p>
            <p>6. From the Polish point of view, it is unfavourable that guarantees for the
               Oder-Neisse border should be completely left aside (even though Bonn is aware of
               Poland’s strong position, which was communicated during Kohl’s visit, and the fact
               that the FRG’s allies – especially France – have been raising this issue). Practical
               implementation of the programme outlined, which gives absolute priority to relations
               with the GDR, creates the prospect – despite official assurances – of our country
               being side-lined in FRG policy (especially in economic collaboration) behind the GDR,
               USSR and CSSR.</p>
            <p>In the present situation, we believe that it would be advisable to:</p>
            <p>– Consider reiterating the Polish position, notably by highlighting territorial
               guarantees as one of the fundamental conditions for any further examination of the
               development of the “German problem”;</p>
            <p>– Step up efforts to coordinate views on this subject matter with the most interested
               stakeholders in the East and West.</p>
            <p>It is especially important that the broadest possible consensus should be built at
               home over German affairs, which are of vital importance to the nation and state.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>