<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53170</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53170">dodis.ch/53170</ref>
               <title type="main">Minutes of conversation<note xml:id="e1738">Minutes of
                     conversation (translated from Polish): <idno>Archives of the Polish Ministry of
                        Foreign Affairs AMSZ, Dep. IV 31/92, w. 2</idno>.</note> by the Polish
                  Ministry of Foreign Affairs</title>
               <title type="sub">Minutes of the Conversation between the Foreign Minister of the
                  People’s Republic of Poland Prof. K. Skubiszewski<note xml:id="e1743">Krzysztof
                     Skubiszewski (1926–2010), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57377"
                        >dodis.ch/P57377</ref>, Polish Minister of Foreign Affairs
                     12.9.1989–26.10.1993.</note> and the Foreign Minister of the Federal Republic
                  of Germany H.D. Genscher<note xml:id="e1749">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016),
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor
                     and Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>, Held
                  on 10 November 1989 (Second Plenary Session)<note xml:id="e1755">This note is part
                     of a comprehensive record (undated) of talks held during Chancellor Kohl’s
                     visit, drafted probably on 14 November 1989.</note></title>
            </head>
            <p>After Minister Skubiszewski opened another plenary session on 10 November 1989, the
               floor was taken by Minister Genscher, who informed the meeting of Chancellor
                  Kohl’s<note xml:id="e1759">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> decision to interrupt his visit to Poland for about
               24 hours following the developments in the GDR (opening of the border with the West
               and the mass movement of people from the GDR to the FRG). He added that the
               Chancellor planned to call an extraordinary cabinet meeting and that the Polish side
               had shown full understanding of his decision.</p>
            <p>Next, Minister Genscher declared that in light of the events in the GDR, he wanted to
               present a position on the matter to the Polish side. After Minister Skubiszewski
               accepted this departure from the official programme for the session, Minister
               Genscher discussed the following points:</p>
            <p>– Situation following the opening of the border with the West by the GDR; masses of
               East Germans crossing the border and being given an enthusiastic welcome by FRG and
                  W<add type="edition">[est]</add> B<add type="edition">[erlin]</add> residents;
               events had yet again confirmed that the ideal of German unity was alive and that the
               aspiration of the Germans to live in freedom and democracy had not diminished;</p>
            <p>– What had happened in the GDR posed no danger whatsoever to Europe. It also posed no
               threat to Poland or anyone else. On the contrary, the embrace of change by the GDR
               could enhance the continent’s security and stability. The drive for freedom and
               democracy should not be considered as a threat, but rather as an important
               contribution to the stability of European relations;</p>
            <p>– No one should exploit the thrust and drama of developments in the GDR; on the
               contrary, the GDR’s neighbours and other countries of the continent ought to show
               responsibility and far-sightedness;</p>
            <p/>
            <p>In these circumstances, Chancellor Kohl’s visit to Poland was taking on a new
               dimension, becoming a symbol of the Polish-German aspirations for freedom.</p>
            <p>In his reply, Minister Skubiszewski thanked Minister Genscher for familiarizing the
               Polish side with the West German position on the GDR. He added that he understood and
               appreciated Bonn’s intentions in this matter. Minister Skubiszewski took the
               opportunity to share his impressions following a recent visit to the GDR to mark 50
               years since the outbreak of World War Two. He recalled the lukewarm reaction to the
               incumbent state leadership by members of an official march, and the popularity
               enjoyed in the GDR by Gorbachev<note xml:id="e1785">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31707">dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the Communist Party of the Soviet Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the
                  Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union 25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet
                  Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>, which was manifested by gestures and
               spontaneous chants “Gorbi, Gorbi.”</p>
            <p>Then, Minister Skubiszewski referred to Minister Genscher’s statement, emphasizing
               that:</p>
            <p>– Poland welcomed the democratization measures adopted by the new GDR leadership;</p>
            <p>– The GDR was an important factor in European balance, Poland’s close and friendly
               neighbour, and we took a keen interest in all developments within the GDR. In this
               context, we were very interested in stabilizing the country for both national and
               European reasons;</p>
            <p>– Events in the GDR had significantly reinvigorated various tendencies related to the
               possibility of German reunification. We were of the opinion that the changes taking
               place in the GDR would above all reinforce its sovereignty and identity, while the
               process set in motion would progress without interruption or difficulty. We
               recognized the right of all nations, including the Germans, to self-determination.
               However, one had to bear in mind that the issue of German unity depended on the
               attitudes of victorious powers on the one hand and on Germany’s neighbours and the
               remaining European countries on the other. In these circumstances, German
               reunification was not a live issue; it was not on the agenda and could be considered
               as lying in a distant future.</p>
            <p>Adding to his previous statement and commenting on the views presented by Minister
               Skubiszewski, Minister Genscher pointed out the following:</p>
            <p>– The Poles and Germans both lived in Central Europe, making them a significant
               element of the European balance. Both look back on some painful experiences, which
               has heightened their sense of responsibility;</p>
            <p>– The lost war and the ensuing catastrophe led to the overcoming of nationalism in
               Germany. That was because the German nation could not overthrow dictatorship on its
               own and had to be liberated by other countries. This was also why it wanted to
               preserve the memory of those who had risked their lives to fight against this
               dictatorship. For this reason, we wanted to honour the anti-Nazi Kreisau Circle<note
                  xml:id="e1805">This reference is to a German anti-Nazi opposition group which
                  operated in the village of Kreisau during World War Two (Kreisau Circle, Polish:
                  Krąg z Krzyżowej, German: Kreisauer Kreis). The group’s founder and leader, count
                  Helmuth James von Moltke, was arrested by the Gestapo. Following a death sentence,
                  he was executed in January 1945.</note>. The Bonn offices of the Foreign Office
               feature a plaque commemorating foreign service members who had been part of that
               movement and were killed, demonstrating a new sensitivity to nationalism;</p>
            <p>– Having drawn lessons from our experience, we were not going to go our own way in
               Europe. The FRG was permanently anchored in Western European structures and intended
               to remain in them. In this situation, the Chancellor’s visit to Warsaw took on a
               special European meaning.</p>
            <p>Minister Skubiszewski replied that the concept of 19<hi>th</hi>-century Central
               Europe could not be resurrected, for back then it had served hegemonic purposes.
               Today, it is no longer possible to mark off a third geopolitical area alongside
               Eastern and Western Europe, as this would create an additional factor in European
               relations. Transformation in the East meant that we were back to normal in Europe and
               thus in international relations. It should be observed, however, that the war that
               Germany had lost in 1945 caused fundamental territorial changes on the continent,
               whose inviolability and stability underpinned European security.</p>
            <p>Taking the floor, Minister Genscher drew attention to the fact that the FRG made a
               clear distinction between “reunification” (<emph>Wiedervereinigung</emph>), which did
               not appear in the Basic Law<note xml:id="e1817">This reference is to the constitution
                  of the FRG of 1949.</note>, and unity, which it was obliged to seek under the
               constitution. Under no circumstances should this be held to mean an aspiration to
               restore the former German state. The aspiration to German unity was not of a
               restorative nature. The only solution to the problem of German unity was a European
               solution that would not infringe the agreements with Moscow and Warsaw. The line of
               division running through Germany today was of a double character, for it also divided
               Europe into two blocs. We wanted to overcome the continent’s division and realize
               German unity by overcoming the continent’s division.</p>
            <p>Minister Skubiszewski replied by emphasizing that the <emph>Wiedervereinigung</emph>
               category was not appropriate, expressing as it did the desire to return to a
               territorial order that had long been outdated. Therefore, it should not be employed.
               At the same time, he agreed that the developments unfolding in Europe at the time of
               Chancellor’s Kohl visit to Warsaw imparted an additional dimension and symbolism to
               this trip.</p>
            <p>At the end of the talks, Minister Genscher welcomed the Polish-Swedish initiative to
               convene a conference of the Baltic States’ prime ministers with the aim of protecting
               the Baltic Sea.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
