<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53324</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53324">dodis.ch/53324</ref>
               <title type="main">Political report<note xml:id="e5897">Political report No.
                     367/D.401 (copy, translated from Turkish): <idno>Turkish Diplomatic Archives
                        3180235</idno>. Internal distribution within the Turkish Ministry of Foreign
                     Affairs and to the Turkish Embassy in Bonn.</note> of the Turkish Consul
                  General in Berlin, Akın Emregül<note xml:id="e5900">Akın Emregül (*1937), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57551">dodis.ch/P57551</ref>, Turkish Consul
                     General in Berlin 30.4.1988–1.7.1992.</note>, to the Turkish Ministry of
                  Foreign Affairs</title>
               <title type="sub">Meetings of the Senate of West Berlin and the Government of East
                  Berlin</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Berlin, June 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>1) The Senate of West Berlin and the Government of East Berlin (Magistrat) gathered
               in the City Hall (Rotes Rathaus) of East Berlin for the first time in 42 years. Some
               of the decisions taken are as follows in summary:</p>
            <p>– Berlin will be the capital of the united Germany. Every kind of effort will be made
               in this regard.</p>
            <p>– Both administrations of the city will continue to make joint efforts in order to
               rapidly finalize issues such as the rehabilitation of Berlin, transportation,
               telecommunication, housing and other issues and will redouble these efforts.</p>
            <p>– Berlin should be a state with the insertion of Brandenburg.</p>
            <p>– A determined effort will be made in order to host the Olympic Games in 2000 or
               2004.</p>
            <p>– A close cooperation will be established with European capitals, particularly with
               Moscow, Paris and Warsaw so that the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe
               shall set up a headquarter in Berlin and that a bridge of friendship and cooperation
               shall be laid among European cities.</p>
            <p>– Common measures will be developed in order to ensure the peace of the city and to
               prevent violence.</p>
            <p>– A common effort will be made to create a tolerant attitude towards minorities and
               pursue an approach which is compatible with the multicultural lifestyle of the city
               and which protects the social rights of the people of Berlin.</p>
            <p>– Joint meetings will continue to be held in the City Hall of East Berlin on Tuesdays
               every 15 days.</p>
            <p>– A personnel exchange program will be implemented at the administrative level
               between the governments of the two states.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
