<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53323</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53323">dodis.ch/53323</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e5835">Telegram No. 82/9 (copy, translated
                     from Turkish): <idno>Turkish Diplomatic Archives 3180745</idno>. Copies to the
                     Turkish Embassies in Washington, Moscow, Bonn, London and Paris and the Turkish
                     Missions to NATO in Brussels, to EC in Brussels and to the CFE Talks in
                     Vienna.</note> from the Turkish Ambassador in East Berlin, Metin Mekik<note xml:id="e5838">Metin Mekik (1932–2013), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57531">dodis.ch/P57531</ref>, Turkish Ambassador in East Berlin.</note>, to the
                  Turkish Ministry of Foreign Affairs</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Normal</add>
               <dateline>East Berlin, 18 June 1990, 5.00 p.m.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">During the private session held on 17 June 1990 by GDR People’s Chamber, the
               coalition partner DSU submitted a draft providing the annexation of the GDR into the
               territory of FRG under article 23 of the Basic Law of the FRG. This vital submission,
               which is described as the end of the GDR, has been put on the agenda by a two-thirds
               majority.</p>
            <p>With regards to that development, it has been stated that if the draft is adopted,
               the GDR Council of Ministers will be repealed because the Basic Law recognizes only
               one council. Furthermore, it has been stated that President de Maizière<note xml:id="e5853">Lothar de Maizière (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54809">dodis.ch/P54809</ref>, GDR Prime Minister 12.4–2.10.1990.</note> will have to
               lay down his office on the same day and this office will be taken over by Chancellor
                  Kohl<note xml:id="e5859">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note>.</p>
            <p>While advising to be calm and cautious, President de Maizière has explained that he
               also supports an early annexation. However, it was pointed out that a second
               unification treaty including the general conditions should be made beforehand.
               Moreover, the need for federal states to also be established in the GDR before the
               annexation has been underlined.</p>
            <p>It has been asserted that in case of the adoption of GDR’s draft, this will be a
               “fait accompli” and 2+4 meetings will no longer be needed. SPD Parliamentary Leader
               Richard Schröder<note xml:id="e5869">Richard Schröder (*1943), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57559">dodis.ch/P57559</ref>, Member of the People’s
                  Chamber 5.4.1990–2.10.1990 and SPD Parliamentary Leader 3.4.– 21.8.1990.</note>
               argued that political union should be made through agreement with the “super powers”.
               CDU/DA Chief Negotiator of the Financial, Economic and Social Unification Treaty
               Günther Krause<note xml:id="e5875">Günther Krause (*1953), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57560">dodis.ch/P57560</ref>, GDR chief negotiator
                  and signatory of the German Reunification Treaty.</note> noted that the annexation
               should be carried out in the summer and the annexation procedure will be determined
               by the second unification treaty.</p>
            <p>According to Krause, this second unification treaty will enter into force following
               the election which will be held for the whole of Germany on the 2<hi>nd</hi> or
                  16<hi>th</hi> of December in 1990. Before that, GDR federal state elections will
               be held on 23 September 1990.</p>
            <p>The draft has been referred to the Constitutional Committee and the Inter-German
               Committee by a two-thirds majority.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>