<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52925</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52925">dodis.ch/52925</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e2864">Telegram No. 12 (incoming): <idno>UK
                        National Archives FCO 33/10716</idno>. Repeated for information: Priority to
                     the British Embassy in East Berlin; Routine British Military Government Berlin,
                     the British Embassies in Washington, Moscow and Paris and the UK Delegation to
                     NATO.</note> from the British Ambassador in Bonn, Sir Christopher Mallaby<note
                     xml:id="e2867">Sir Christopher Mallaby (*1936), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57461">dodis.ch/P57461</ref>, British Ambassador
                     in Bonn, 1988–1993.</note>, to the British Secretary of State for Foreign and
                  Commonwealth Affairs, Douglas Hurd<note xml:id="e2873">Douglas Hurd (*1930), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57401">dodis.ch/P57401</ref>, British Secretary of
                     State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, 26.10.1989–5.7.1995.</note></title>
               <title type="sub">The German Question: Our Public Line</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 5 January 1990, 4.41 p.m.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <emph>Summary</emph>
            </p>
            <p>1. Despite our supportive line on the German wish to achieve unity through
               self-determination, the UK is perceived here as perhaps the least positive of the
               three Western Allies, and the least important. Need to present our policy in the most
               positive light we can. Your visit to East Berlin and the GDR an opportunity.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>Detail</emph>
            </p>
            <p>2. I remain concerned that despite our consistent support for the principle of German
               unity through self-determination, the UK is perceived here as opposing, or at least
               wishing to brake, reunification. The French, on the other hand, whose doubts seem if
               anything stronger than ours, manage to maintain a more positive public image
                  (Mitterrand’s<note xml:id="e2895">François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P13775">dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France
                  21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> remarks in Kiev notwithstanding<note xml:id="e2901"
                  >President Mitterrand had met President Gorbachev in Kiev on 6 December 1989. At a
                  joint news conference he had stated: <orig>None of our countries, and especially
                     one whose weight is so great and whose geographical position is such, can act
                     without taking into account the balance of Europe.</orig></note>). The US are
               perceived as the most supportive of German aspirations even while laying down
               conditions for German unity.</p>
            <p>3. Two recent British statements have stuck in German minds and coloured their
               perception of our policy. The first was your comment in Berlin on 16 November that
               German unity was not on the agenda<note xml:id="e2906">In fact Douglas Hurd had used
                  this formula on at least three previous occasions: in a press conference in The
                  Hague on 9 November 1989, a BBC World Service interview on 10 November 1989 and a
                  BBC Radio interview in Bonn on 15 November 1989.</note>. This was true at the
               time. But Kohl’s<note xml:id="e2909">Helmut Kohl (1930–2017), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>, Chancellor of the FRG
                  1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> ten point statement on 28 November put it on the
               agenda, even if without a timetable. The second was the Prime Minister’s<note
                  xml:id="e2915">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of the
                  United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note> statement in Brussels on 1 December
               that reunification should not take place for ten to fifteen years<note xml:id="e2921"
                  >In fact at the NATO Heads of Government meeting on 4 December 1989.</note>. The
               latter continues to be quoted by German commentators as evidence of a negative and
               mistrustful British attitude.</p>
            <p>4. As against the background of Bush’s<note xml:id="e2926">George Herbert Walker Bush
                  (1924–2018), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>,
                  President of the United States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note> policy of a “Europe
               whole and free”, Baker’s<note xml:id="e2932">James Baker (*1930), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P56605">dodis.ch/P56605</ref>, United States Secretary
                  of State 25.1.1989–23.8.1992.</note> four conditions for German reunification have
               been well-received here, because of the spirit that is thought to lie behind them and
               because they are seen as designed to facilitate, rather than prevent, German unity.
               The same cannot be said of Mitterrand’s contributions. In Bonn on 3 November he said
               he had no fear of German reunification, which posed no problems for France. Three
               days later in Kiev he said reunification “is not a question for now” and that the
               question of frontiers should not be raised again. The fact is that as the FRG’s best
               friend and most important European partner, France can get away with a great deal. It
               is characteristic that Kohl should have visited Mitterrand in south-west France on 4
               January to mend fences<note xml:id="e2938">Helmut Kohl had visited François
                  Mitterrand’s private residence at Latche in Gascony.</note>. The UK by contrast is
               at present seen as neither especially important nor as well disposed. Both aspects
               can reduce our influence on the FRG at this critical time.</p>
            <p>5. Your visit to East Berlin and the GDR which is likely to be widely reported here,
               provides an important opportunity to try to put a more positive spin on our
                  presentation<note xml:id="e2943">Douglas Hurd’s visit was to take place on 22–24
                  January 1990.</note>. You could use the Strasbourg/NATO formulae (East Berlin
               telnos 003 and 007<note xml:id="e2946">The European Council’s Strasbourg declaration
                  read: <orig>We seek the strengthening of the state of peace in Europe in which the
                     German people will regain its unity through free self-determination. This
                     process should take place peacefully and democratically, in full respect of the
                     relevant agreements and treaties and of all the principles defined by the
                     Helsinki Final Act, in a context of dialogue and East-West cooperation. It also
                     has to be placed in the context of European integration.</orig> The Strasbourg
                  formula was repeated in the communiqué issued at the end of the North Atlantic
                  Council.</note>) but present them as a statement of British policy. You could also
               draw on other elements in the public line recently produced by the Department in
               consultation with this Embassy<note xml:id="e2949">Charles Powell (*1941), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57468">dodis.ch/P57468</ref>, Private Secretary to
                  the British Prime Minister, commented in a letter to the Foreign and Commonwealth
                  Office dated 9 January 1990: <orig>The Prime Minister has seen Bonn telegram
                     number 12 commenting on our public line on the German question. She thought it
                     showed a lack of understanding of our policy which she finds alarming. She
                     would like to see any reply before it is sent.</orig>
                  <idno>UK National Archives FCO 33/10893</idno>.</note>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
