<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52938</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52938">dodis.ch/52938</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e2518">Telegram No. ZQGR0559 (incoming):
                        <idno>Global Affairs Canada file 25-3-3-5-Germany / Confidential</idno>.
                     Ref: <idno>Our tels AQGR0556 28 NOV and 0574 04 DEC (NOTAL)</idno>. Info to
                     Privy Council Office, Brussels-EEC, Brussels, Brussels-NATO, London,
                     Washington, Paris, Paris-OECD, Rome, Tokyo, Geneva, Warsaw, Budapest, Helsinki,
                     Oslo, Stockholm, Copenhagen, Hague, Bern, Vienna, Delegation to the
                     Organization for Securtiy and Cooperation in Europe, Madrid, Athens, Ankara,
                     Moscow, Bucharest, Belgrade and Prague.</note> from the Canadian Ambassador in
                  Bonn, Thomas W. Delworth<note xml:id="e2521">Thomas W. Delworth (1929–2012), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P51338">dodis.ch/P51338</ref>, Canadian Ambassador
                     in Bonn 1987–1992.</note> , to the Canadian Department of External
                  Affairs</title>
               <title type="sub">German Reunification: The Street Speaks</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 6 December 1989</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Our German (West) interlocutors, such as Teltschik<note xml:id="e2536">Horst M.
                  Teltschik (*1940), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57413">dodis.ch/P57413</ref>,
                  Foreign policy advisor to the Chancellor of the FRG.</note> in Chancellor’s
               office, repeatedly have stressed to us that while Bonn recognizes dangers in pursuing
               reunification too precipitously and will remain loyal to its Western allies, it is
               the people in the streets of the GDR who will play a decisive role in this
               debate.</p>
            <p>2. FRG electronic and print media is absorbed totally in what is happening next door.
               There is one dramatic event after another as the political guillotine (without a
               Robespierre) takes its toll. Krenz<note xml:id="e2544">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54794">dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and Chairman of the GDR State Council
                  18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note> is now gone. Honecker<note xml:id="e2550">Erich
                  Honecker (1912–1994), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P46563">dodis.ch/P46563</ref>,
                  General Secretary of the SED and chairman of the GDR State Council
                  29.10.1976–18.10.1989.</note> is under house arrest. GDR state security apparatus
               is under siege and the entire SED, including Modrow<note xml:id="e2556">Hans Modrow
                  (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of
                  the GDR Council of Ministers 13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note>, appears discredited.
               Banners calling for reunification are blossoming in greater numbers. There is talk of
               advancing elections to May from the autumn and of a referendum on reunification.</p>
            <p>3. But it is not only in the GDR streets that events are happening. In the FRG,
               Bild-Zeitung (FRG and Europe’s largest circulation newspaper) yesterday ran a one
               word, three inch high headline in national red, gold, and black colours “Einheit
               (Unity)”. USA Ambassador Walters<note xml:id="e2564">Vernon A. Walters (1917–2002),
                     <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54605">dodis.ch/P54605</ref>, US Ambassador in
                  Bonn 1989–1991.</note> made a public prediction that there will be a reunified
               Germany with Berlin as its capital within five years and has sent the Bonn coffee and
               cake Hausfraus crowd to gossiping about the merits of selling their houses in Bonn
               before real estate prices in Berlin become too high.</p>
            <p>4. On 05 December it was announced by Modrow and Seiters<note xml:id="e2572">Rudolf
                  Seiters (*1937), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P57431">dodis.ch/P57431</ref>,
                  Minister without portfolio in the Government of the FRG 1989–1991.</note> of
               Chancellor’s office that an agreement had been reached on removing visas and currency
               changing requirements for West Germans visiting the East and setting up a currency
               conversion mechanism and fund for East Germans travelling West (details in separate
               telegram). This will result in massive two-way flow of Germans. A huge economic
               assistance plan is under discussion (our telegram ZQGR2473 06 DEC<note xml:id="e2578"
                  >Not located.</note>). The CDU has announced that its next party conference in
               January will be split, with the first session in Bad Krasnall in Bavaria and the
               second in Leipzig, where it says there are many CSU supporters.</p>
            <p>5. How far this integrative process, led primarily from below, will go is difficult
               to predict. It is, however, proceeding apace while statesmen talk and muse about what
               is and what is not possible.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
