<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/52931</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/52931">dodis.ch/52931</ref>
               <title type="main">Memorandum of conversation<note xml:id="e3250">Memorandum of
                     conversation (translated from German): <idno>Austrian State Archive ÖStA, AdR,
                        BMAA, II-Pol 1990, GZ. 43.18.01/11-II.3/90</idno>. Written by Hans Peter
                     Manz, dodis.ch/P57510 and signed by Ernst Sucharipa <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57511">dodis.ch/P57511</ref>; also published in
                     Wilson Center, doc. 165719. Sent to the Cabinet of the Foreign Minister, the
                     General Secretariat, the section heads II, III, IV, the Departments II.1, II.7,
                     III.7, IV.2, the Austrian Embassies in East Berlin and Bonn and the Austrian
                     Delegation in West Berlin.</note> by the Austrian Foreign Ministry</title>
               <title type="sub">GDR; Visit of Prime Minister Modrow<note xml:id="e3258">Hans Modrow
                     (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796">dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman
                     of the GDR Council of Ministers 13.11.1989– 12.4.1990.</note> in Austria;
                  Conversation FM<note xml:id="e3264">Alois Mock (1934–2017), <ref
                        target="https://dodis.ch/P57512">dodis.ch/P57512</ref>, Austrian Foreign
                     Minister 21.1.1987–4.5.1995.</note>– Foreign Minister Fischer,
                  26.1.1990</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Vienna, 30 January 1990</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>During the work meeting of the Federal Minister with GDR FM Fischer<note
                  xml:id="e3275">Oskar Fischer (*1923), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P51055"
                     >dodis.ch/P51055</ref>, Foreign Minister of the GDR 3.3.1975–12.4.1990.</note>
               on 26 January 1990 the following issues were broached:</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>1. Bilateral Issues</emph>
            </p>
            <p>1.1. <emph>Repealing Visa Requirements:</emph> The foreign ministers agreed to
               tentatively repeal the visa requirements from 1 February 1990, 0:00 until 28 February
               1990, 24:00. By then, negotiations on a corresponding agreement should be completed,
               which should come into force on 1 March 1990.</p>
            <p>1.2. <emph>Repealing Car Tax Liability:</emph> Foreign Minister Fischer handed over a
               note in which the request was put forward again. The note will be transferred to
               Department III.7 under a separate reference number.</p>
            <p/>
            <p>
               <emph>2. International Questions</emph>
            </p>
            <p>2.1. Unification of the German States: Foreign Minister Fischer emphasized that it
               would come to unification; it must be embedded in the overcoming of European
               division.</p>
            <p>2.2. <emph>CSCE process:</emph> According to Foreign Minister Fischer the
               negotiations in Vienna are going too slowly (the usual conference mechanism is
               running rampant). He therefore welcomes the initiative of Genscher<note
                  xml:id="e3297">Hans-Dietrich Genscher (1927–2016), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P15414">dodis.ch/P15414</ref>, Vice-Chancellor and
                  Minister for Foreign Affairs of the FRG 1.10.1982–17.5.1992.</note>, Dumas<note
                  xml:id="e3303">Roland Dumas (*1922), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P15651"
                     >dodis.ch/P15651</ref>, French Foreign Minister 10.5.1988–28.3.1993.</note> and
               de Michelis<note xml:id="e3309">Gianni De Michelis (*1940), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57415">dodis.ch/P57415</ref>, Italian Foreign
                  Minister 22.07.1989–28.06.1992.</note>. Given the time and effort required for a
               summit of 35, and the pressing international issues, to the GDR it seems worth
               considering following directly up in Vienna with “Helsinki II”. The holding of two
               separate summits in the current year (Signing of the agreements/European discussion)
               would, anyway, not be advantageous. The Federal Minister emphasized Austria’s
               interest but referred to the still upcoming interim conference before Helsinki
               1991.</p>
            <p>2.3. Foreign Minister Fischer spoke positively of Mitterrand’s<note xml:id="e3317"
                  >François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P"
                     >dodis.ch/P</ref>13775, President of France 21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> idea of
               a European confederation.</p>
            <p>2.4. The Federal Minister pointed out that Austria’s policy of neutrality is still a
               part of the credibility of Austrian foreign policy, even if in the light of the
               international development it no longer has the same weight it once had.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
