<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 ../xsd/tei_dodis.xsd">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>dodis.ch/53321</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
                  Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
                  Dodis</orgName>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Diplomatische Dokumente der Schweiz | Documents Diplomatiques Suisses |
               Documenti Diplomatici Svizzeri | Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland |
               Dodis</publisher>
            <date when="2019-01-01">2019</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cf. note 1</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               <ref target="https://www.dodis.ch/en/profile">Dodis Website</ref>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-01"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="doc">
            <head>
               <ref target="https://dodis.ch/53321">dodis.ch/53321</ref>
               <title type="main">Telegram<note xml:id="e1217">Telegram No. 386 (copy, translated
                     from Turkish): <idno>Turkish Diplomatic Archive 3211299</idno>. Reference:
                        <idno>our non-confidential telegram numbered 1481</idno>.</note> from the
                  Turkish Ambassador in Bonn, Reşat Arim<note xml:id="e1220">Reşat Arim (1931–2017),
                        <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P53697">dodis.ch/P53697</ref>, Turkish
                     Ambassador in Bonn 31.8.1988–26.11.1990.</note>, to the Turkish Ministry of
                  Foreign Affairs</title>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <add>Urgent</add>
               <dateline>Bonn, 11 November 1989, 10.00 a.m.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p/>
            <p>Having returned from Berlin, Chancellor Kohl<note xml:id="e1235">Helmut Kohl
                  (1930–2017), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31852">dodis.ch/P31852</ref>,
                  Chancellor of the FRG 1.10.1982–27.10.1998.</note> made a statement about the
               developments in the German Democratic Republic in the press conference organized
               following the cabinet meeting.</p>
            <p>Having stated that the Federal Government had summoned the State and Party
               Administration of the German Democratic Republic to open their gates for a radical
               change in the fields of state, economy and society, Kohl reiterated that they are
               ready for assistance. He also declared that he had had a detailed phone conversation
               with Krenz<note xml:id="e1243">Egon Krenz (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P54794">dodis.ch/P54794</ref>, General Secretary of
                  the SED 18.10.1989–3.12.1989 and Chairman of the GDR State Council
                  18.10.1989–6.12.1989.</note>, the leader of the German Democratic Republic and
               that he had informed Krenz about his appreciation of their decision concerning the
               opening of the borders, that they agreed upon a visit by Federal Minister
                  Seiters<note xml:id="e1249">Rudolf Seiters (*1937), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P57431">dodis.ch/P57431</ref>, Chief of Staff of the
                  Chancellery and Minister of Special Affairs of the FRG
                  21.4.1989–26.11.1991.</note> to Berlin on 20 November to conduct preparatory
               meetings with the Administration of the German Democratic Republic and that Seiters
               would meet with Krenz and the Prime Minister of the German Democratic Republic<note
                  xml:id="e1255">Hans Modrow (*1928), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P54796"
                     >dodis.ch/P54796</ref>, Chairman of the GDR Council of Ministers
                  13.11.1989–12.4.1990.</note>, who will have been elected by then. He noted that
               they would want to know in these meetings the concrete steps which the Administration
               of the German Democratic Republic intend to take, especially how and when they will
               organize the free elections which have been announced. He also stated that Krenz and
               he decided to meet somewhere outside East Berlin in the German Democratic
               Republic.</p>
            <p>Having indicated that he had also had telephone conversations with President
                  Bush<note xml:id="e1263">George Herbert Walker Bush (1924–2018), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P47406">dodis.ch/P47406</ref>, President of the United
                  States, 20.1.1989–20.1.1993.</note>, President Mitterrand<note xml:id="e1269"
                  >François Mitterrand (1916–1996), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P13775"
                     >dodis.ch/P13775</ref>, President of France 21.5.1981–17.5.1995.</note> and
               Prime Minister Thatcher<note xml:id="e1275">Margaret Thatcher (1925–2013), <ref
                     target="https://dodis.ch/P32055">dodis.ch/P32055</ref>, Prime Minister of the
                  United Kingdom 4.5.1979–28.11.1990.</note>, Kohl also declared that he informed
               his colleagues about his visit to Poland and he mentioned his first impressions of
               the opening of the Berlin Wall, that he was in constant contact with Gorbachev<note
                  xml:id="e1281">Mikhail Gorbachev (*1931), <ref target="https://dodis.ch/P31707"
                     >dodis.ch/P31707</ref>, General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet
                  Union 11.3.1985–24.8.1991, Chairman of the Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union
                  25.5.1989–15.3.1990 and President of the Soviet Union 15.3.1990–25.12.1991.</note>
               and that he had notified Gorbachev by telephone an hour earlier about his assessment
               of the situation.</p>
            <p>Having reported that Germans from the German Democratic Republic were still coming to
               stay in the Federal Republic of Germany despite the first indications of change in
               the German Democratic Republic, Kohl said, “I absolutely object to the fact that the
               notable social democrats now try to provoke embarrassingly the excitement and
               feelings against these citizens”, and called on the public for help. He also declared
               that there was still a long way to go to reach the target and that all the Germans
               had not yet gained the right to self-determination and he recommended being
               moderate.</p>
            <p>At the end of the press conference, Kohl reported that he would resume his visit by
               returning to Warsaw that afternoon.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
